considered in your exam however it will
be very helpful for you to take a look
at it because
they are the cutting-edge technology
relating to OS now
um right now if if you are working on
operating system research almost
um
so very few of people are working on
pure kernel when they working on the OS
research related research almost almost
like 19 percentage of the person
researchers are working on the system
which system virtualization technology
Also regarding about like how to do the
CPU virtualization memory virtualization
this is very important and uh
that work virtualization Network IO
virtualization
um and we are very familiar with like
Amazon Amazon ec2 right AWS ec2 AWS S3
which is the storage service AWS logdb
storage service they are almost all of
them built on the system virtualization
technology
that is why this is very important so
the key difference is um let me mention
that a little bit okay the key
difference is between the virtual
machine and the non-virtual Machine is
that virtual machine adding
another obstruction
[Music]
between the OS and the hardware oh sorry
it's like after the OS layer so if you
look at this we have the kernel we have
the hardware and then we have the kernel
kernel is where the OS the most of the
OS code lies right so for the system
virtualization they have an actual layer
after extra layer which is
between the kernel between your OS code
and the hardware and we call this we
call this hypervisor
virtual motion hypervisor
so virtual machine manager and the key
the key differences between the
um so the key technology they are using
is to virtualize the CPU Hardware
virtualize the CPU Hardware
yep we like I'm the only person if I'm
the only person using the the laptop
right I may not feel it is a virtual
machine but in order to ensure like
several people can walk in together to
use this the same Hardware the OS needs
to virtualize many CPUs for each of the
users then that is the CPU
virtualization technology so how to do
that the key Technologies were then
propose this is a very famous uh virtual
machine using a parallel virtualization
and what what he proposed is that using
the
um the concept of rings the Rings is you
can think of this is a priority
priority level he make the OS income
you make the hypervisors you see the
ring zero is the kernel modes okay Rings
you know it's the kernels who are going
to manipulate the hardware and then
rinse 3 is the user mode so where is
ring one and ring two so then ring one
and the ring two
is where the system virtualization
virtual machines resize in
okay
and then also after see some versions
after recipient virtualization so let's
look at the memory virtualization the
key concept for memory virtualization is
the it's called Shadow page Shadow page
table instead of using one page table so
virtual machine are going to use a New
Concept called Shadow page table so
Shadow page level if you look at these
pictures
it's very it's very uh a straightforward
right it's going to cut the tables into
several parts so each parts belonging to
one virtual motion so whenever you
create a virtual machine we are going to
get some spaces from the page table and
we call this page table of shadow of age
table Shadow so each Shadow page table
is for each virtual motion so that is
the key technology for memory
virtualization
then for i o virtualization the key
concept is here this is for the i o
virtualization
um so they are using uh
there you seeing something we call a
circular buffer this is a new data
structure
here we have a hardware right in
Hardware above the hardware we need to
run several virtual machines so several
virtual machines they are going to share
the same network pocket network sockets
they are going to share the same ports
then how to how to ensure their IO their
data inputs and output data can go
through the same ports concurrently and
ensure they have the fair share they
have the fair share when we do virtual
machines we need to ensure like three
virtual machines we need to ensure
everyone can get 30 percentage of the
resource right five virtual machines we
need to ensure everyone can get 20
percentage of the resource so the same
thing as this so to do the i o what are
the system modularization
obstruction data is that they're going
to put all the data in a circular buffer
so different color you can think of
difference
and then using a producer and a customer
queue to come to produce and consume
this data okay
and then you can think of that and they
are going to share this circular buffer
they're going to share secure buffer
oh that is the um
virtual machine
so let me look at this
so this is the virtual machines picture
if you look at this slides we can see
that virtual machines we have virtual
virtual machine one washing machine two
and virtual machine three right they are
managed by a hypervisor they are not
manager they are not going to be manager
by your OS they have their own OS
instead of the OS code each virtual
machine will like each that's the top
server they have their own OS code so
initially your OS code is directly on
top of the hardware but for this for the
virtual motion Concepts
we are going to have a virtual motion
manager which we call the hypervisor and
then on top of the hypervisor we have
the OS code
okay so that is the
there is the virtual motion then there's
another New Concept it's called
container you are going to use that in
your project five
um so I'm not going to speak too much
about that
the key differences between the virtual
machine container is that container will
not have any OS code you will not have
any OS code so it's very lightweight
when we container is it's not developed
just in recent year is actually
developed 20 years ago however at that
time it was not popular
then only for the recent five years it
becomes super popular container is just
a technology of process virtualization
it's a technology process virtualization
In This Very lightweight it's very
lightweight the key difference is
between the container and the OS the
virtual machines that container does not
need any OS code but the virtual machine
needs their own OS code if you see they
have the gas OS code right each virtual
machine have the one specific Os Os code
is super long right and maybe like
several gigabytes so that is why virtual
machine is super is very heavy weights
but the container is very lightweight
the container does not need any virtual
machines just needs some
some kernel kernel calls libraries and
whenever you need new library it's going
to import that from the remote storage
and it's going to download it you can
think of that when it's when we crease
the container it will continually
downloading the necessary code or
libraries from some remote storage
is unlike the virtual machine when you
create a virtual machine you do not need
to connect to the virtual machine to the
network you can adjust the directory
install it because the OS is already
inside of it
okay so that is the system
virtualization and Technology
and you
just
it needs to have what is Boost operating
system
if you you you are using Windows right
you download the virtual motion and you
can you need to install this virtual
machine or operating system it can be
Ubuntu it can be
Microsoft it can be any c but it needs
the its own operating system
but for containers it's not it is not
necessary they just need a part of the
OS code
okay
um
so this is for your final exam review
I'll try my best to draw
um to capture the uh the most important
points okay so the scenes that for the
um your final exam it will focus on the
chapter after a chapter in the memory
file system and IO
um
however it will also cover a little bits
about the dialogue processing stress
um an introduction
um
so still um for the operating when we're
talking about the introduction we're
talking about the operating system
architecture right we talk about what is
operating system and operating system
benefits
um
and we're talking about the computer
architecture we have a picture about the
how the CPU memory IO devices and the
input output the the monitors are
connected through a main bus so
um
the computer so here the here the
takeaway is that
we need to we need to know what is dma
and we need to know the
or three communication models of the um
in this page so we have the i o by
polling all right we have the i o by
interrupts and we have the dma directed
memory access so you need to know the
differences between these approaches
um for for example sometimes we may need
i o by polling right when we have very
um
much less data
and with
why we need i o by polling and then if
we have more data we may need i o by
interrupt because it will be more
efficient so
the CPU is not going to busy waiting
here and then if we have a huge amount
of data we need the dma
and we're also talking about the
pipeline so we need to understand why
why we need CPU pipeline what is CPU
pipeline
and uh um this is how the rcpu respond
to the interrupts so um
New Concept here like
um interrupts Handler right a system
core user mode kernels
I could have in the workflow
the workflow
of handling the interrupt
Andrew could you tell us how to handle
interrupt
yeah and you
know
it goes into kernel mode and it puts the
interrupt code into the register and
then the kernel will handle
uh we'll go into the table and look up
which Handler to use
and after
the
call is done it returns to the user
program under stores the state
very good
see some cool
um
so here when we talk about season call
we
what's the differences between seasonal
core and or interrupt
majis
system call instead is kind of from like
user code like
um
they're very good so so uh interrupt is
more
um worldwide concept interrupts can be
can come from many sources right and see
some coins just
um so they have many so system code you
can think of it's just a software
style of the interrupt
oh let's continue
with those Process Management
so when we're talking about process we
need to know what is the process process
is a
active it's it's a it's active program
right so why we think what why why we
say that it is active
because it's not just a code you need to
load the code from the
from your disk to the memory and then
executing it and when and by that time
it becomes active then what is the
process so when we're talking about
process you always need to mention that
the system stays of the process
the systems they liked statues of the
process right where the process is that
is called the memory address space of
the process right and you need to think
of that the data about this process and
maybe in the register it may be in
memory
so that is the process
another dress phase this is this is a
process how the process looks like we
when we load the process in the memory
they are going to be
in many memory address
spaces
so each process views its memory as a
continually set of logical materials
addressed so the operating system
management translation of The Logical so
so you can think of this is a virtual
virtual address right virtual address to
the physical address so how to how to
convert from the virtual address to this
to the to the physical address we use
the page table right
we use page table
so what is the process with stress we
have um
um
you need one sense so thing is that the
key difference is that the contact
switch of the threads
if the server is belonging if multiple
threads belonging to the same process
then the complex reach of this threads
will prevent much more lightweight than
the contact switch between different
process
okay so this this one this one I hope
everyone can
can understand it can I'll draw this
picture the three stage you need to
here you need to understand the
different states running State block
State Ready States and you need to
understand how they
how they the the directions directions
over there translation okay the
directions of their translation
converts like from the ready states to
the running state from running state to
the block stage but you cannot directly
from the Block state to the running
stage right because you need to go to
into the ready queue first
no like this we need to push the push
the process into the radical then it can
be scheduled to run that is why that is
why if you look at this we can we cannot
go from the Block States
to the running States we need to go to
the right stage first and then go to the
running stage and um
okay
so what is the contact switch
and this on scheduler metrics so um the
CPU utilizations reports wait time
service type turn runtime and response
time so here
response time
so not this no response time
turn around time okay turn around time
what is the turnaround time Alan
always turn around time Ellen
how long the process takes to finish the
job so it starts from the
the start time is the time the process
joins the system right the process is
submitted to the system that is the
start time and what is the end time the
enzyme is the we finish processing the
pro we finish
processing the that we finished
processing the uh finish the job of the
process right then you you use the end
time minus start time you have return
runtime for process
so and we talk about several different
algorithms
um
so short is the job short is the job
shot is the drop
scheduling algorithms has to minimize
the turnaround time right as the
minimizer turnaround time
okay so IPC interprocess synchronization
um
here you need to understand what is race
condition what exactly risk condition is
um
why why there is a race condition why
there's a race condition
so the loot code the loot of the problem
stands from the context which occur in
the middle of the execution of the
critical section right so we're talking
about that in the um you know code so
first of all solutions we have the
software solution like you design or
alternative block you design alternative
log
and uh it can be it can be a Peterson
Peterson's approach which you have a
ring of the logs it can be adjusted
automatic lock that is a true Force lock
so that is a software solution
what is the disabling interrupts that's
a hardware solution right so remember we
have the hardware specific Hardware one
a process entering into the critical
section we are going to disabling
the interrupt
this is the hardware solution so if we
disable in the interrupts no one can
block that that process then that
process can finish it so only one
process is entering one critical section
and using one the resource shared
resource but it's not that it's not that
efficient or safe why it is not safe so
it's not safe right white is not safe
I'm generally talking about producer
customer problem with the producer
customer problems called
to
um to introduce some vulnerable tax we
tested that in the midterm so what is
the sum for and what is mutex the
difference is between the sum foreign
mutex right
we may repeated testing that
then memory management okay memory when
we're talking about memory
we first was talking about the memory
hierarchical structure it has the
registers cache memory
then we have the disk SSD SSD and then
the the disk
original disc
memory management units so what is
memory management units used for voice
memory management used for
memory management use units
yes one juice
memory yeah Andrew
yes it is managing the
um the mapping right the mapping between
the
virtual memory to the physical virtual
memory address to physical memory
address so how it manages how it manages
it's managing the page table right it's
managing the page table is using is
using the page table to manage it right
so before the page table we have a New
Concept called tlb
what is tlv
mojis
translation look
look up
translation look up
Lucas translation look outside buffer
right yeah translate so where is it tlv
where is it
yes
it's in the memory management units
yes Andrew
so
so tlb so that's that's a tricky
question so um every different Hardware
they use different place to store the
DLP we didn't you do not need to
remember that the page table is most of
the time the page level is not stored in
the CPU because the page table is huge
the page table is huge especially right
now we have very large of my more
physical memory right I have I recently
built a PPC I have
128 gigabytes of memory and I built a
server for my lab I have
1208 18
Library yeah I feel it's very expensive
the thing is that you cannot the
mappings of the memory is huge right the
memory the mappings will be also a lot
of entries so most of time we cannot
store the page table in my in the
register see see the hierarchical
structure
this is where is this is very small the
registers the registers and the cash
down they are in the CPU so they are
very small so most of time the page
table
is in a memory so tlb tlb is in the
register tlb is in the register
sometimes it's
units sometimes it's not just as if you
use a register to save the tlb entries
yes
MDR and Mar that's a good question for
Africa there are whole names but it's I
think it's uh relating to the um to the
address translation
um
okay for this it's very important okay I
hope everyone come
sometimes a lot of time
to learn how the paging works
we're definitely going to test that
so you need to know how the page works
how to trans how how so
let me show you a slides
it's not here
can you see this
so this is the
um
you need to know if I give you a virtual
address
you need to know how to translate this
virtual address to the physical address
right so you need to know how to
translate that you need to
understand this understand why
the size what is the meaning by the size
of the page table what is meaning by the
offset of the um yes
so officers what is the concept of the
offset
and what's the name
easy
right oh like yeah
you think you you are the easy queue you
you're the let me see
easy Q Loma
great great idea he's also the one who
got very performative for good in our
midterm yeah easy queue so what is
offset
is the page offices is the page set so
it says it's not the page set
[Laughter]
do you know that
looking inside of the page looking
inside of the page where the
where the
your processes right for example you
well
we
um let me see if I can
okay so here's the thing
let's say okay let's say
oh this is
foreign
what do you want to say
I'm trying to explain okay I'm trying to
explain the
is anything interesting
oh okay so we are we are trying to we
are trying I'm trying to explain the
the differences between the index and
the offset the induction offsets
so here's the things here's the thing
if I'm cutting here if I'm cutting here
then
this part this part is that I'm screwing
it with the page table
it's the page sorry it's the page table
number it's a page table not so this is
the virtual address okay virtual address
this is a virtual address okay this is
the some virtual address right some
virtual address
it's my points to cause points to some
code so points to some code let's say we
have a
a lot of Records so we have a virtual
address points to this
then the CPU needs to needs to encode it
needs to decode this virtual address
code this virtual address to find out
the physical address relates to that
virtual address then the first thing you
need to find out
you need to find out the page table the
page table number for that virtual
address
we are going to tell you how large the
page
the page sizes then you need then you
can
you can do you from the
um size of the pages then you know what
is the what is coin the offset what is
the page number so this will be the page
number then you see the virtual address
is page number
you look at the table the table will
show you
the table will show you
the mapping the mapping between the
virtual page to the physical page it
will show you the mapping between the
virtual page to the physical page so you
find out that okay this virtual this
virtual
page number
points two you need to find out where
the the physical address is points to so
in this case
so one one
foreign
physical address what would be the
physical address
the physical address will be the zero
zero one
plus right plus the same offsets
white plus the same offices
because this one is
inside of the page inside of page where
this exactly code is
so this is the you need to you you need
to bring you to the address translation
you find out the
is exactly a physical page okay then
you're using that physical page you go
inside of the physical page add in the
offsets then you can get the physical
address get the physical address
that was a virtual page number
it's not the offset it's the mapping
mapping so
see
so the page table right the page table
shows the virtual page number to the
physical page number so
that is how this works this is the
so in this case 0 0 1 0 is the virtual
page number right it's the virtual page
number so what is 0 0 1 0 is 2 right
it's two is equals to two right you know
how to calculate 0 0 1 0.
you know that right
it
so virtual page
so the first step is
zero zero one zero is the
okay
I think this is
how large is this zero zero one one
first like let's see zero zero zero one
hologies is equals to
is equals to one right then zero zero
one zero equals two
two
you guys okay so zero zero one one
equals two
three right three right okay
then let's look at this
zero zero one zero is two right it's two
right
so it points to one one zero one one
zero is the
physical page number right physical page
number
So Physical page number is how much one
one one one one one one zero one zero is
one one zero one one zero it's how much
then
six right
six so six so this points to six it's
like one one zero and then you need to
add in the offset the same of that right
see this the same officers so in this
so here
this is the
this is the uh this is your your
physical address right physical address
um Okay so
so you need to know that
neutrons of this because this is the
most important Concepts in our um in the
memory chapter so this is the technology
of paging okay
yes Andrew
which this one yeah
and it doesn't matter
the physical page will not the physical
the physical
memory is smaller than the virtual
memory right
that is why the number of the physical
Pages the number of available physical
pages may be smaller fewer than the
number of the virtual pages right
now and you didn't ask that well you
need to yeah I cannot tell you exactly
what I'm going to test but that's not
that's not good yeah so I'm I'm going to
point to you this is important so you go
back and understand they are trying to
yeah easy
you think of that okay think of that I
cannot say
yeah let's give this okay I speak too
much for this
okay that is four page okay that is for
page so we need to you need to know
the size of the page is the same as the
size of a physical page frame right
the size of the page is the same size of
the physical page frame it does not mean
the size of the virtual page name table
is that it's the same as size of the the
number of the entries in the physical
page
it's only the size of the page it's the
same as the size of the page frame okay
now how to handle the page fault how to
handle in the page font you need to we
have a workflow so someone still
remember that you have that in your
homework
is Lucas here
okay who still remember that how to
calculate the page four how to handle
the page font
yes
no no how to handle the page Force the
first thing you need to really you want
to say
yeah you definitely need to include tlv
and update
reach the disk to do what reach this
yes
cash
TRV is in the cache right
yes
it puts the file from the disk to the
page right to the physical page and then
you update
your update the page table can remember
the sequences
we first look at tlv we first look then
we look at the page table if both means
we locate we look at we look at the disk
to find out the file that we need then
we retrieve it and then put we find our
empty page frame to to put that page to
put that files in then we update the
page table of all the entries okay the
new mappings and then we update the tlb
right and then yes we will have a
question
very good very good you can mention that
yeah very good
very good if if we find out like there's
no empty page frames then we use the
page replacement algorithms to
in weeks the on user Pages out and then
put the new pages in then we update the
page table right updates the tlv
okay
so why virtual memory this is also
important why virtual memory
why we use virtual memory
yes magician
s
I forgot what it's called
it's called basically you can fit more
programs in game yeah then
how to say that
in another way why we need a virtual
memory yes easy
yeah we are in shortage of the memory
physical memory that is why we need
virtual memory because physical memory
is in short region we want to The
Limited memory to support us many
programs the same time so we need to
have the virtual memory
okay page four it's okay page four we
just mentioned that handling the page
Force 100 years Andrew
well that is a very good internal
fragment any students know internal and
external fragmentation
yes
what is external what is external
what is the external fragmentation
so um so do you still remember the wrong
loving algorithms we mentioned about
this this very similar to this why one
for the round-robbing algorithms we we
design we settle Quantum right to each
process to run right if I set the column
to be very large the main space are
wasted
right the same thing is in a paging
algorithm is a sets the page to be very
large
then a process emoji
yes that is internal fragmentation then
what is external
yeah very good so when we're talking
about external fragmentation we're
talking about in the differences between
the swapping technology and the patient
technology remember that we talk about
the swapping and then we introduce the
um
different algorithms like link release
the speed map continue the allocation
and then we're talking about the
the paging right so the external
fragmentation is relating to the
swapping technology
and we're saying that we're using the
swapping technology and then we use a
continual allocation of the memory
resources to the process then new
process comes in or process comes out it
will create many holes between the
process and that is the external
fragmentation
you have external fragmentation is
relating to the swapping technology we
talked about in the memory allocation
chapter memory allocation approach we
talk about swapping technology right and
then we talk about two algorithms one is
called
continuity allocation right in a
continual location we talk about the
b-maps right bitmap approach and linked
list approach
and any student remember who which which
approach was the external fragmentation
bitmap or linked list
foreign
technology
bitmap linked list
it's a tricky question it's very tricky
it's very tricky but you remember what
I'm talking about right we we have the
we're talking about swapping technology
and we talk about virtual memory that's
the two technology to handle the memory
allocation in the memory chapter
let me find those slides
here here here here here
this you see this
Swati
surviving Technologies this
then we talk about bitmap
and the linked list
who caused the external fragmentation
yes
it doesn't matter both because the
external fragmentation guys because they
are using swapping technology right
so do not do not make the the so the
concept is that swapping Technologies
technology we swap the process out and
put the new process in the memory is
going to be allocated continually
through the process and then the
algorithm is is relating to that
technology we can use different
algorithms to implement the same
technology but no matter what kind of
algorithms we use to implement that
technology the disadvantage is still the
disadvantage right
so that's no matter what the algorithm
we use to build map or linked list
the swapping technology caused the
external fragmentation that is why we
use the virtual memory right virtual
memory but they each of them have their
own yes
internal fragmentation is about the page
the page size
foreign
what's the difference between that they
have a different read performance like
um how to say that the red amox
um
the b-map have the compact way of the
keep track of my memory but the bad
things needs to search the memory right
such a memory so if you need to find out
the same side some specific size of
available resources you need to search
it from the beginning to the end the
linked list they have better approaches
because they will show you
how large of the link list is
okay page your replacement algorithm
do you need me to go over that
you can do that right you can do that
right okay so I'm not going to go over
that so in if I'm give you the um page
reference Stream So I really still needs
to know
how the page replacement algorithms
works and also the least reason to use
the algorithm placement algorithm used
Volcan said working search model so what
is a working search
um
okay so I'm going to skip that I file
system management file system in the
file system management
so every student needs to know I know
what is inode what is the uh this
partition okay this partition
or the votes records first I node what
is the directory what is the files
also these blocks
so what is a file it files the ordered
collection of data blocks it's all good
collection of data blocks
directory and file system
um
so what is inode table why we need I
node table
can we just store the I know in the
memory instead of I know the table
you have do you have any thought about
that
yes Andrew
speak louder I cannot hear you
why why we need I know table
say again I didn't get you
you were not you are not having enough
memory for that right now I can I can
how about I just save the I know that
I'm currently using inner memory
I know this where is the eye notes where
is the eye note
you remember the disc in the disk where
is it
where is it where in physical it is
Andrew
speak for before the low directory in
the partition in the page in the disk
partition in the disk partition we have
we first have some like an MBR right
the boots records we have the super
block right and then we have the
we have the I node and then we have the
loot directory and then we have the
files right that is where I noticed I
noticed in the disk in the disk right I
know this in the disk so my question is
that
my question is that
where is the eye table so let's first
get
also in the disk and you still don't
have different softwares a table I know
table why we need I know the table
foreign
ode table
Lily
you're a good accessing you can is I
know table you can easily using the
table you can easily find out the way
that I know it is so we put most we put
the I know table in memory it's because
it's just the map it's very easy it's
very easy to implement the app the first
context is the integer and then the
other is the like the the
right what is the number is right it's
just the integer you can see I know
table okay
yes
so
let's see this okay
I know the table I know table what I
know table is first we need to know I
know the table
another table is show the number the
unique number about the inode right so
in which it will you know tells you
where you can where I know this it may
be in the disk it may be in the memory
you cannot we cannot store like what
Andrew said we cannot store all the high
load in the memory because it will be
huge it's not huge but what we can do we
can put all the I know the I know table
the numbers we can put all the numbers
in the memory and the numbers what tells
us the I node is okay well I know this
now the question is that can we just
keep the I know table we just we do not
use I know table anymore we just sort of
I know what I know in the memory can we
do that the answer is yes we can't do
that but there's disadvantages you need
to know what is what are the
disadvantages
it will be
in my slides okay if you look at the
slides you can you then you you can get
the idea for example
we may not be able to store all I knows
in the memory right you can only install
the frequently used so it
and the what's the benefit the benefits
you do not need to go to the I know
table you can directly find the inode
right you do not you can reduce the jump
you can reduce the jumps
you do not need to go to every time you
find a directory you do not need to find
out the I know table first and then I
node and then the subdirectory is I know
table and then I know the subdirectory I
know table and inode
so if we totally remove the I know the
table we can just go to directory for I
know to I know to I node
yes
say it short
I didn't get that
a symbolic link that is for the uh
for the shared link is
not that related we can't order after
class okay yeah what do you want to say
I was wondering if like there's an i o
table for every directory because that
kind of resembles the output of an LX
of like the command line
let me put the slides okay we have the
very good slide for that
not for this
see
remember this so we're looking at the
hey
I think this
you you're looking you're always looking
at the I know table I I know I know
table to find out that I know the number
right so you look at the I know number
to find out where exactly it is and then
you look at another I know the number
because if it's a directory definitely
has a I know number
okay
there's another
one no I'm not saying that I'm saying
that
you need to think of many design
questions related to inode so in
currently in the Unix file system
design
they're using the eye note table to
store them to ask at the actual layer to
store the order I know the information
so the benefits is that
it can it can help you quickly locate
where the I node is each I node is can
help you quickly locate because you have
a table you have a table to just store
the what I note
but the disadvantages that we are the
current file system is adding some
actual searches because every time if
you look at the directory no matter the
loot directory or self-directory you
need to always go to the I know the
table to find out so
well it is right you need to always find
out where is this so the question is
that can we get rid of that and if yes
then why if not then why not okay this
is an open question
um
see this we're saving our known numbers
instead of I node in I know the table
that's the question I'm asking why
saving the item number instead of I node
why we have the I know the table well we
have three why we have the I know the
table
when saving was saving the I know the
numbers itself I know the United table
like like can we get rid of that oh no
you cannot eat sorry
hmm
I'm singing I know tables instead of I
know they know I know table okay
hmm
yeah
we're saving iron alt number instead of
I knows you know I know the table
so directory links
um
what is hard link what's the software
link
okay I node
so this is I know why we need several
layers of the iron it's some some I know
that has several layers why why we have
that why we need that
okay now I all under the logs IO
I will so IO by Pauline what is the io
by polling
um problems with pouring purpose is IO
polling my slides has the answers
I hope I interrupts the problems of I
over interrupt
problems of value interrupts
so we see see this this picture are
actually likes this very much so if you
see that we can see this is actually how
you handle the interrupts right we have
to received reader devices and then we
go to that and then we go to the
interrupter Handler and the handle us
and then goes back so the interrupt or
how the OS deal with the interrupt
okay that looks
um the key concept for dialogues is that
key consumer for dialogues is that
there's four conditions for the dialogue
to happen so the only if we satisfy all
the four conditions do you still
remember that four conditions Lily
yes
chain yes
preemption
yeah there's four we need to four
Mutual exclusion right exclusion so um
you need to know how to draw the
resource allocation graph
we haven't already attached to that
right
so do you know how to draw that the
resource allocation graph
this is an example see the process holes
are
right this is the resource allocation
graph right you need to know how to
how how to draw that right and then and
then you need to know whether there will
be a deadlock or not whether there will
be there
so remember and then for the dialog what
we have
I'm not going to test you that
Mutual exclusion so to exclude the
mutual exclusion what we are going to do
to ask so to avoid them hold on a weight
so what you can do to avoid the down
preemption what you can do and to avoid
the circular weight what you can do
so um
okay so that is basically
so that is basically the our review
um
review key points
uh
which it seems that my um I hope you can
go over your your Section Quiz is the
your assignments every chapter we have
our assignments right I'm going to
you have all the assignments right so
I'm going to upload my solution soon the
example Solutions tool yes
yes there should be do you have that no
oh oh okay the TA should um yeah I'm
going to ask her him to upload that and
I'm going to upload my solution
my solution soon okay
um
on the textbook
um so here's the thing if you need the
solution menu ask my ti I cannot post
that in Converse is illegal so you
answer the TA and the promise you are
not going to distribute it and then he
will give you to you okay that sounds
fair so the textbooks so they have
salute we have a solution menu and uh
for the exam review session
oh yeah that is for this session the
Section Quiz is the assignments
um and then slides so
yeah if you finish that you should be
fine you should be fine yes easy
well this is our tricky question
there will not be the exam either
exactly the same questions
there will not be the exam exam exactly
same questions but the concepts are
still there
yes
uh
yeah so
yeah it will be on the exam yeah
let me see what
the Costa that is my tea if
he so here's the thing hdfs will not be
beyond the exam so you may still need to
understand that a little bit okay
um
because it's part of the file system but
for the others
um P2P containers this one see some
virtualization I'm not going to test
that because I didn't teach uh
fortunately yeah so I'm not going to
test you that
um
but for the others it will be in the
exam yeah
yeah
okay so then our next class
um
our next class I will still be here I
will be hold a QA session
so you can't ask me any questions that
you have
uh
and then your exam will be on the
15 instead of 15s
oh I know that's another thing I want to
remind you we have the I think ta posted
that I don't know if you'll receive it
right because I received many emails
every day about the asking me to regret
in the midterm I'm not going to regret
that for you but ta can do that
because I do not know they are grading
criteria I gave them a solution but I do
not know how they grade so they have
their own creating criteria if you if
you need regret you can ask them feel
free to ask them okay
um if you send me email I'm still going
to afford that to them it takes time yes
didn't the shop
well you have to you have to print it
right you you have that scanned
I do not know that part you can ask well
yeah okay good luck with your final okay