foreign
we cannot
scheduling for you for makeup the exam
for any travel reasons for example you
said you want to you need to travel from
to some place or you have any travel
plans
that is something I cannot do anything
so you need to schedule it in advance
like make sure that you are there in the
exam day so I cannot schedule any makeup
exam for the travel reasons travel or
commentation reasons this is the first
thing and the second thing later you're
gonna you maybe hopefully this week
maybe next week you'll get your grades
for midterm there's there's no
opportunity for retaking the exams
so um you got a grade if you find out
there's problem with your grades then
you can ask the our TA and Tao
um
or look look forward for you okay but
yes no
retaking exam okay you cannot retake the
exam that's the second thing another
thing in case of any emergency happens
in the exam day
let's say
you like some
for example
um you have some urgents medical issues
you need to go to the Urgent Care you
need to go to
um
like the hospital or something like that
we we need some documents you do not
need to tell me exactly what you have I
do not need to know that your privacy
but I need some me or TA or the school
may need some documents to
uh to prove that you have this situation
um
okay
uh
okay so that is a photo of final our
final will be in the June 15th June 15th
it's already there in the uh seller base
so you can see that okay it will be the
June 15th
okay so any questions for example
okay so then we can start with our
memory management chapter so
uh
some memories memory management let's
starting with some basic concepts okay
um
so in this chapter we are going to study
how the operating system creates
abstractions from memory and how they
managing them
so um
give me one second
here
okay
so first let's review the memory
hierarchical structure we have learned
that so in the memory hierarchical
structure we have the in the top is
actually the register and then we have
cache we have the main memory and we
have the disk so
so the register is usually very
expensive but it's very fast cash is
fast main memory is a medium and in this
case is slow
um during the recent years we have
developed the SSD right it's it's also
very fast so it's between the memory
main memory and the disk so it will be
much faster than the um
the old disk
so that is the memory hierarchical uh
structure why we need the memory
hierarchical structure the reason is
that we do not have we do not have
inference Ram okay Ram is any anyone
knows that this Ram what Ram means
yes
yeah random access memory so uh so
what's the difference between IAM and
ROM
and ROM what's what is difference
yes
oh yeah yeah very good so
um so for the Rams Although our main
memory when we're talking about main
memory we usually means that it is a ram
okay
so the thing is that it is when we power
it off it'll go into clear everything it
will not remember every anything but for
the
om I am which like
like the disk what what they do is that
even we power it off it's still there
and the main memory the memory
obstruction the main memory abstractions
means the uh in this part okay in this
part in the
REM okay I am
so um so one
here this chapter in this chapter I will
not directly tells tell you what exactly
the our modern operating system
did
it could because it's well here's the
thing even I tell you what they did you
may not understand it
for everywhere why because the my the
system computer systems changes every
day it may change this year next year I
made using different structure so what
we are going to learn in this chapter is
that we are going to learn from the very
beginning the old memory memory is
somehow the old memory system do and
what and then eventually learn what our
modern operating system did form to
creating the memory abstraction so
the concept that you may heard of the
urban you may not understand it quite
well it's the tlb paging page map
mapping virtual memory virtual memory
address
address space all these concepts are in
the category of model operating system
so before we go to the model operating
systems we're starting from see what all
the system did for the memory management
okay so here so think of that now you
are the software engineering now you
when you run only one program at a time
in memory how are you going to do that
okay
the simple the simple let's see the
simplest yes sure
oh yeah yeah that is from what you can
see there in uh in this picture so
here's the thing let's starting from the
simplest implementation so we have
let's say we just have one program what
we can do is that why is why why why why
they give this three pictures right you
need to you only needs to design because
we only have one program right one we
you have to you have the program you
need to loading that into the memory
processes
so you only need to design where each
resides where the program is
then you design where the OS is because
when we're loading loading booting up
the computer right the first thing the
OS needs to booting up then you have one
program so the only thing you need to
decide is that where I put my OS code
where I put my own program code that is
why they give you
these three structures so
the first choice that you can have you
can have the OS code here right at the
beginning of the memory at the beginning
of the bottom of the beginning of the
memory address space you can have it at
the
starting from the end right at the top
of it or
you can push the OS code at the bottom
and the device drivers code
in the ROM and in the top okay
so what are the disadvantage what a
disadvantage of this approach
think of that over the disadvantage of
this approach
yeah sure
foreign
let me rephrase it a little bit so
here's the thing if we know exactly
where the OS code is no matter if it is
here where it is here or it is here no
matter where is it
if we know if any programmer know where
the OS code is then it's easy for them
to change it
it will be easy for them to change it so
um
so like what Cheryl said that if we it
is not safe okay Joseph it's not it will
cause a lot of bugs
and another disadvantage is that if we
only have one programs in memory at a
time if we
we
How about if in the case that if we want
to run multiple programs more than one
if we want to run
more than one programs all right
so what we need to do we need to wait
until the old one finished because you
can only support one program at a time
in memory then you need to wait it to
finish it then swap it out put the
results into the disk and then load the
new one that is not really concurrence
so that is not really concurrence then
how people did so think of that how
people did then right a natural way to
do that is
is we divide the memory into many parts
right memory is a it's a space sharing
approach I want multiple programs use
the memory dish using the space sharing
it's not like CPU they use the time
sharing but for memory they use space
sharing so we only have this
we only have let's say we only have
these one rooms but we have so many
students I cannot just teach one student
unless one student in room so what I did
is that I divided the space into many
parts like each one of you can get a
seat so I at the same time I can support
I can teach many students in the
classroom that's the same idea in the
memory in the memory but the difference
is that some of you may be very huge and
big some of you may be very tiny and
small
so it's it it will be difficult for me
to decide
who are there and who is other back who
is at the front
and some of you may live very soon some
of you may stay very longer so it's very
difficult for memory to manage them then
that is what we are going to learn in
this chapter okay
so the first concept we are going to
learn is that address space
so what is the address space
we are going to create abstract memory
space for programs to exist in to each
program each program has its own set of
address right what this addresses the
memory address and the address is
recorded address space okay the address
phase a difference for each program so
each program they have
their own address space
so we call it all draft space so that is
the concept of address space so it's
very easy to understand the address
phase is just
the address the minor address that the
program resides in the memory so since
different programs have different
start an ending address like address in
the memory so they will have different
address space
now to now to represent a program's
what are the units of that what we
should do like you want to see some
designer right now you have you have
your program you know the size of the
programs
now
how do you use like variables to
represent its memory address space yeah
I think
um no no no you not not about the units
not about the units it's maybe buy
things maybe or it may be different
no we I'm asking for example
we have uh like
we have the address the memory address
like this right like this
is from 0 to
0xff is very large value okay then each
we have several we may have several user
programs they each of them have their
own address space right so then what
kind of variable you the OS is just
called a code like your project is part
of the code so in the code you let's say
I can create a class saying okay this is
the address space so in the class what
kind of variables I need to set
to represent this program's address
space
emergence
you need to you need to wear this user
program is right but how to represent
this address these user programs address
yes
something what's inside of the address
table what inside of that
yes
no that's
Andrew
yeah very well let's say we use
variables but how can I how how can I
use variables to represent the address
of this
yes munchies
yeah there's specific location yeah
okay then let's say I'm I'm following
you okay so let's say we just used like
some variable like a to represent the
address of the these programs burden
these programs maybe maybe very long or
maybe very short this I tell you right
this program may be very long or maybe
very short
let's say this the starting address of a
this address of B
what if it is very long
yeah
yes very cool that is how the um
old people did they haven't start and
the end they have to start address and
the ending on address this is what I'm
asking you can use the start of the
dress or the size of the size of the um
programs right and that is just the
differences of
of the like the start and ending okay
so we have we're using what we are using
so the first generation of operating
systems that you're using base and the
limits registered so they set a base
a base variable and the limits variable
to represent the starting address of the
memory oh sorry the program and the
ending address of that program will use
and push these two variables in the base
register and limits register
so the base contains the beginning
address of a program the limits contains
the length of the program okay the
limits that is what Andrew did said okay
the base and the limits and we push that
into two registers into two register the
registering the CPU okay then we're
using Dash we're using darts to
represents where
this program
is in the memory the position the
location
in the memory okay
so the disadvantage of this this
approach is that the addition and
compression have to be done on every
instruction so let's see look let's look
at it why okay
let me show you example
this is your memory okay this is your
memory
foreign
so we divide the memory this this is the
memory okay the whole memory okay it's
it's very long okay let's start into
from zero okay from zero to
um
let's say each each unit says just so
okay let's say four units the units can
be word can be biased can be whatever
okay the page uh you you can use any
units but let's say just the four okay
four
so eight twelve
no
no so we have the address we have it's
the memory the whole memory the whole
memory from 0 to 64. okay so the size of
the memory is 64. right 64. okay now
what is the
a dress space a program's address space
program or program can be any size right
the program can be any size let's say
let's say the program has the size of
has a size of eight have the size of
eight then we use the limits name it's
Ace represents the size of the program
and we have to start
this is called a base
let's say the base of the program is on
the 16th okay 16 okay 16. then where
this program is then we use these two
variables two variables to represent the
address space memory address space for
this program
so the program P ones
address memory address space
so are we clear about that part the
first difference difference so different
programs they have different address
space it's different they have different
base they have different limits and they
are non-overlapping they cannot overlap
with each other
so if also
so if for this program for this program
let me down
so if for this program so if for this
program it has the base of 16 and limits
of the age so it will going from here on
this side zero so that's it
zero this is four I think that's it it
will go from here
right
so this this will be the
P1 p1's memory address space so P1 would
resize here P1 will resize here
right then think of that what is the
disadvantage of this approach the
disadvantage of this approach is that
whatever yeah
yeah it's very good whatever you need to
the programs may be very long right and
right now you see the limit is eight so
it has at least eight uses a slice of
the code has eight slice of the code so
whenever you do one instruction whenever
you do one instruction let's say I point
to this point to this whenever I do any
instruction of the code points to this I
always need to add in adding the base
okay we need to add in that
we need to
add it so let's look at the how the uh
here this has a simulation
but this is a good example
so one approach process is run the base
registers loaded with the physical
address where this program begins in
memory and the limits right this is
loaded with the length of the program
with the lens of the program so let's
say if this is the
what is jump one problem saying John 28
so this is the program's code one
program saying jump 28 for example is
saying like you need to
push that valuable into this array
something like that then you need to
jump to that line of the code when you
say in the John 28th because this is the
start of the program start of the
program when you say jam 28 you cannot
directly jump to the 28th it's another
accurate you need to add in the 28
with the base register to adding it
add it and then find out okay that is
the jump to here something like this
okay that is why so we need to add in
this the start the Base address 228 and
the resulting jump to this for every
instruction you need to do that this is
very very
coastery that is very costly
so you may not
yeah in my notes are strange forward how
costly it is but if think of that you
have
you have this we have different process
programs right we have different
programs like different programs they
have their own let's say P2 is there
they have the orange stars in the the
space and the limits they have their own
base and limits so for any instruction
each process did like P2 they're saying
like jump if if in their code they just
want to jump to some Discord the next
code is jump to this position it can
it's not jump to
jump two this needs to
adding tool with the 32 with their base
so for every process whenever they do a
new instruction they need to add it to
their base it will be very
closely very closely for the OS
so this approach may not good then in
Singapore are there any better
approaches
okay
now uh after we we we we know this space
and the limits registers okay so this is
the old obstruction now think of that
here we we may run multiple programs
multiple programs inside of the memory
at the same time right you write at the
same time
how to ensure that you can run as many
programs as possible in the main memory
at once how to make sure you can do that
how to make sure you can do that
so the question is like this
we have P1 P2 right I may have another
is P3
P3 and another is P4
it's like a bing packing problems
for the OS we need to improve the
throughputs so
let's say we've already uh
design the limits base and limits
instruction obstructions for each
programs now I need to hold as many as
possible programs in the memory
simultaneously
the first question is that
how do you design which programs resize
in which place the first question second
question is that how do you track their
values for example one process is
donated it's not live okay you need to
remove it from the memory so how are you
going to track that how are we going to
make the best tracking of the
you remove it then there will be an
empty hole there right
okay my Josh you have
yeah
okay this process is at this place this
process is in this place so yeah you
probably want to find a way to implement
a process table
s yeah um well I'm not asking uh
obstruction right now I'm asking a
resource management
mechanisms for that Resource Management
mechanism for that so simply this you
have the I have the memory this memory
may be very large now I have I know that
many importances are coming many process
is coming they may come at the same time
they may come at a different time so I
think over as the process different
process keep coming and they have
different size they have different
service times now how can how can you
make the best uses of these resources to
ensure many processes can resize in them
need as much as possible
yeah very good yeah try to try to feel
all the holes in the memory and what if
at the first study has a very large
process
comes in right it takes all the holes
and then
there's only little horse left the only
little processes can resize in then the
other long process needs to wait forever
how to handle that no think take this in
mind take this in mind because we are
going to learn that in our later
uh section okay
so the question is how to run more
programs than fit in memory at once okay
we cannot keep all the process in the
memory because there are too many they
are too big so there's two approaches
swap under virtual memory so we are not
talking about virtual memory right now
we only look take a look at the swap
swap is the first generation OSD the
swap the swap is bringing programs in
and running for a while and then swap a
new program so this is what the
um
what's your name Irene
Aaron yeah this is wearing a propose is
that we pack them we pack them we pack
them like a bin parking put them in the
memory
then let's look at the water potential
problems of this approach the swapping
approach okay so we wrap them and put
them in a memory
so let's say so this is a this is the
first uh Comfort server pouch okay so
let's say we have the poor program a
comes right program a comes we put it in
the memory
then program B comes we put it
so we're starting from this right base
the base
we're starting from the base okay
so this this is the address space and
then the OS resizing here
then we're starting from the this
address to put a after we feel a then
process becomes then B
resides here
process C comes we put C there
then as time goes as time goes on
process a leaves process a leaves
because we already finished that or we
already it's not alive it's not active
yeah
the or the most recent or the most
recently freed um freed up uh thought in
the memory right
um let's think about that later so let's
look at the strange forward approach why
do a straightforward approach did we
have the memory right memory we have the
OS code here then we a comes we put a
here then B comes with B here and then
after a
it's not active after a finish okay then
we let it go then we put this there
okay then B after B finish B leaves and
then we can load a again okay this is
the approach this is called a swapping a
big picture of a swapping
now
of that it's not just a b c d f g true
it's huge number of
the process they are using this first
circum first serve approach and whenever
they finish they we just swap it out and
let the new process comes in what is
what are the disadvantage of this
approach the most
disadvantage of this approach yeah
from E to G like a has to wait until B
is done before it can enter Because
by that space
yeah but what is the disadvantage that
is that is the truth that is the truth
right what is the disadvantage of this
approach single from the system side
this is what happens right we we can see
it we can see what happens in the
picture but that is not a disadvantage
this is the
choose right the facts this is how the
algorithms goes the swapping technology
runs what is the disadvantage of the
approach
think of that not just the ABCDEFG
eventually let's say we ranked for
a whole day let's say we run for whole
day there's thousands of the program
program thousands of programs different
sides different size different process
time any disadvantage of the pro of this
of this approach
yeah process map
probably stops but
this advantage of that
what kind of process going to be stopped
in your example
question like what the difference
between starvation and the dialogue in
the return we have that how you answer
that
just take up too much memory and because
it has to fit in like a certain amount
of space that's available that process
will never actually be used
you are very close you're very close
emojis
it's not that long I'm just sinking over
the dialogue okay starvation is in this
case
yeah so um well so the thing is that the
things that think of that we run if we
run for a long time
the there will be the memory will be
full of little holes four little holes
that is the answer think of why think of
why there will not be a very large holes
if we call it the continually address
space is uh is a whole then eventually
if we're using this swapping approach
the memory will be full of little holes
what what is the little holes okay let
me show you
this is a memory at first that is so
this is the OS code the rest is empty
right memory Mt so at the beginning we
have a big hole we have big hole and
then if we're using the swapping
approach let's say the new process goes
in and goes out goes in and goes out so
at first we may have we we may have
let's say a big
some big processes they take this space
they say they take this space right some
big process take this space and then the
big process goes out and eventually
there are small process goes in and
taking the space taking the space
so as time goes by or time goes by more
and more there may be more and more
small persons taking this space and
creating many little
horse so this is the little
horse so I need a horse
happens when needle holes happens no big
no big process can get in because it's
it's just this empty space no big
process can get in they have to wait
there for a long time so that's the
course many big process in our
starvation status right in Starvation
status but so come back to the midterm
starvation does not mean or dialogue
right
the starvation starvation dialogue is
dialogue right you made salvation for a
long time but you may not in the
dialogue situation right the download
situation is you we need to ensure right
the circulation the lung preemption the
holding ways right the mutual exclusion
by starvation
does not mean that they're locked okay
so in this case the big process my
starvation for a long time and we create
so many holes this is a disadvantage of
the swapping technology so we are going
to go back there later
okay so let's have let's think of the
approach okay let's see let's continue
and continue this story this is the
first generation of operations from the
right
in summary
the first generation what we have
learned in summary we have what we have
learned so far is that we do not have
used any obstruction OS abstraction we
just put the OS in the memory and then
we gave each process a base and the
limits to represent their address space
and since the memory is a space sharing
approach we want to hold as many process
as possible so we put them together in
the memory and we use a first come first
serve approach plus the swapping
process swapping
to managing this to managing this memory
to manage this memory now the now let's
say we already have this design so far
it will continue following this design
let's keep thinking what what the other
disadvantage okay
after I use the first come first
software approach plus swapping approach
plus bass and limits to represent
to represents the memory address space
after I using I create these Up
structures these obstructions then the
next thing I need to think of that is
that how can I keep track of this empty
spaces even there's many holes how can I
keep track of them why do why why do I
keep why do I need to keep track of them
why do I need to keep track of them
because while a due process comes in I
can easily find out where it is where
should it be right
how do I keep track of these empty
spaces empty spaces there are many
approaches but use your creativity to
think about what data structure you are
going to prefer to keep track of this
empty spaces
I thought it should be more difficult to
answer
right this is the memory I give you the
memory you know this is the input okay
you know the size of the memory you know
the size of the memory
this is the input the size of the memory
okay you
the size of the memory you I give you I
gave you a flow of process each process
they use two variables the base and
limits the base
and the limits to represents
to represent where it should be resizing
the memory in the size memory now what
when they resizing in the memory there
are many empty spaces right how are you
going to keep track of these empty
spaces
how you can do that
how we can keep track of these empty
spaces in the memory
many there are many importers is
hundreds thousands of them we do not
have thousands of registers to to to to
to remember every process based on the
limits
so I only need to yeah
English is a very good what others
options
so there's two approaches so one is the
bitmaps one is linked list okay this is
the textbook gives us so let's first
look at bitmaps okay so you let's say I
give you the solution bitmaps how you
going to design using a bitmaps to
yeah Mojo
very good if the space is taken you mark
it with one if space is not taken you
mark it with zero so that is how the
build map approach do so if here
with the beam map okay with the memory
is divided into allocation units a small
a few words and us
corresponding to each allocation units
in the in the base in the bitmap 0
represents
zero represents the space is free okay
the unit is free one represents the
units is taken the memory units is taken
so take a look at this we have the this
is the B okay this is the
disability approach is the B map okay so
we have the
we have the memory so this is the memory
right we have one two three four five we
have five process they are recite they
resize in the memory
so for process one is one one one right
it's good it's because it's taken right
process a and then zero zero zero means
that there's empty space and then we
have B
so B has
this started with the a so it has the
sixth age 10 units okay 10 units
oh sorry it's the
still has a one two three Ace
this one two three this represents this
represents the process B
process B and this represent these four
represent the process C and we have two
empty spaces then two empty spaces
this is the empty spaces
empty spaces
so the main problem of this approach now
you understand how the bitmap works
right and so how to beat Map works yeah
yeah what question and question yeah
no no this is just that this this here
look at this
this is the beam map the link array is
another approach yeah
no here here's the here's the thing they
only use one beam a very large B map to
represent the whole memory
to represent the whole memory you will
use a one big big map to represent the
whole memory this is the whole memory
so that is it it may be a vector that's
very very long
very very large
hmm
it's not 2D or right no no no not think
of the this this can be wait this can be
any it can be it can be um
what this is based on your
implementation right
in this skill can be just a one one line
one row it can be multiple rows it
doesn't matter the approach is that we
use a bitmap up
structure data structure to represents
the whole memory the whole memory
yeah everyone what's your question
yeah yeah there's no my question
remember
how do you manage in the free memory my
question is that how do you manage the
free memory I'm not asking you how to
track the the other process I'm asking
you how do you manage in the free memory
yeah so they just use a bitmap that is
why they do not differentiate so if that
this is taken by a or if this is taken
by B this is just approach
to
tracking the free memory yes
you can just use one joint integer
you know it's
it is very it's very lightweight it's
not heavy it's not heavy right but if
you if you are using another like
Advanced data structure to represent the
bitmap like a vector hash table it may
be a heavy but you think of that just
using an integer or drawing the integer
it's not that
or you can use several integers to
represent several parts of the memory
it's not that heavy right so the
disadvantage is more like that what is
the disadvantage of this approach so
we're using the bitmap to represent the
free map to track the free memory yes
um
find the net the net uh to find to find
out like like to find out that where
yeah it's kind of hard for me to say but
to find out the entire size of a yeah
finding out the entire size of a size
of the space that's taken would be like
order n and finding that finding the
next and finding the next
um not taken state from like fighting
throughout all the empty spaces
basically finding the size of something
would go in linear time and that could
be inefficient which I'm going to get
from cover by the link
yeah very good so the so the digital
Advantage is that because you you will
never know how many continuous zero will
be there
so let's say if I want to find out 1000
continually zero zero right empty space
one thousand I have to go from the very
beginning to search that because in the
bitmap there's no
no signature or no pointer to point out
like the the size of the zero the size
of the continuity zero consequently zero
in each place all right I need to search
it every time so the main problem is
that wine come you need to when it has
been decided to bring a k unit process
into the memory so the memory manager
Master search the bitmap to find out uh
run or account sequencive consecutive
consecutive zero beats in the bmap it
it's not
it's not that easy because every time
you need to search it every time you
search that you may take that space so
every time the second time you may need
to search it again and search it again
so it's not that in patience the reason
why we think of the approach about the
link release so the link list approach
is that
is it will use the P to represent it a
process or not and using the edge
represent the whole the whole mean
starch is it's a it's an empty memory
space and using the zero to represent
water
the starting right the base the base of
our process using here another variable
to represent the limits right the base
and the limits
so take a look out of this linked list
and think of that one of the good thing
and what the best thing about linked
list approach
ES
paper of your frame the next hole is
also Constantine
is
yeah that could be very uh memory yeah
that could be less memory efficient than
like the than the um
it's got to be more
music
you're basically
um got a correct sound so yeah beam map
is very lightweight build map is very
lightweight it's very efficient very
compact way increasing a way to keep
track of the free memory resource
let's let's say we're just using a very
long integer to represent that this
right and for the but for the linked
list it is
um
the good thing about the linked list
the P map is a compound way of keep
track of the memory the bad thing is
that you need to search memory 4K
conspusive zero to bring your file okay
you need to know right so you need to do
it every time so and then that is the
advantage of the link list for for link
release is very easy for searching you
can easily you just needs to search it
you just don't need to search the linked
list right like if if you need let's say
I need to find out the three available
resources so what I did is that if it's
p then I go to the next then if it's
Edge then I just check the size of the
edge
I'm looking for let's say if I'm looking
for a size of the uh the first size of
five then um this has only size of three
so it will not working so I go to the
next one is p so because it's already
taken p means taken so it's not working
so I go to another it's a render P it's
not it's not working go to the next okay
it's h here H then I see the size of the
edge this two so it's not working so I
go to key I go to P now go to the edge
so something like that it's very easy
it's very easy to search
disadvantages that is
is more highways and more heavy weights
now
so this is the link list okay this is
the linked list so the now think of that
the
disadvantage of the linked list is that
is very heavy ways right very hard way
but look at this approach this let's try
to improve the algorithm let's try to
improve the algorithms a little bit we
still are using the leaked list we still
using the link crease we're still using
the linked list to find out the
available
the available memory space available
memory space so for the
for very light for strength forward
approach for example I say
I need to find an edge with some minimum
size of five so in this picture you may
there's no solution because every Arch
has a old that's like three just less
than three so if but the link list may
be very long now my question is that
okay I need to find out the
the hole that is larger than five the
whole is larger than five
then you can search the link list right
you can search the link list let's try
to improve it a little bit the strength
forward approach is that I gave you I
give to you is that I always search from
the very beginning search the very
beginning and find out the the first one
that fits my needs the first one that
fits my needs so any other approaches
any other approaches
but this is all design questions it's
made it all boring but that is how the
OS designed the system they in the OS we
actually have many policies and we we
are not only using one policy to manage
the memory we are using different
vertices for different types of the
process okay now singular if we're using
the link release how are we going to
the search algorithm is like that I
search it one by one to find out the
best fits the final the first phase the
first hole that matches my needs like
larger or you call them five now and in
better Solutions any better Solutions
yes
most appropriate right so that is the
the first algorithmic propose so in
several find out the first the first the
first solution that matches my leads
let's say I am after this I find out a
size of Ash that has a size of 99 in
several of 15.99 I searched the whole
link list and find out who has exactly
exactly size of the hole equal the money
it's like I'm requesting five then I
need to find out the size of five then
the advantage of this approach let me
records of course the optimal face yeah
the advantage of the approach
reduce we come to the maximum reduce the
holes the mini holes we call it a
fragmentation we can minimize the
fragmentations fragmentations
okay can you get this point
fragmentation is very important concept
so this is the best faith approach okay
the faster phase approach that is uh we
call the best fish approach the idea of
the best feature approach is that the
idea of the best piece approach is that
we have
this memory
we have this memory
we have this memory right and then we
always
these are process these are process okay
this is a process
the process
so there are there are many holes right
these are the holes
so the best surface approach means that
we always trying to find out the
smallest hole that fits the smallest
hole that fits the smallest holder fits
then it is very slow why this is very
slow why because I need to search from
the beginning to the end
we need to search the beginning from the
end unless you you find out the exactly
space if not then you need to
search from the beginning to the end to
find out the best fits
the smallest hole that fits your needs
so it's very slow it's very slow
but
it can it can minimize the
right fragmentation right and then
there's a other approaches we call the
next feed towards the fees and the Quick
Fix can you make a guess what the other
the approach that I'm using at the
beginning is called first of each okay
first week so we already know that what
the first phase means the first means
the first of it means that I always
start from the beginning I find out the
first hole that fits my list that is
called first of it and we have the best
fits now what is the next fit means
okay the next phase means
the next phase means we start searching
by other itches wherever it is so that
is the uh
that is approach
improved from the first fit so let's say
the first phase I already searched half
of the memory and for the next first of
all if I'm using the next phase approach
so for the first requirements the query
I started from the beginning then for
the second query I leave it there I
start in search the rest
so I'm not going back the points are not
going to be back at the beginning either
going to search wherever it was
okay
pass the phase means we trying to find
the smallest holes that fits the worst
surface means that we trying to
find out the largest holder fees where
the water feeds like its name is called
the worst surface is the worst okay the
button my question is
why you need the worst
why you need the worst modules
why you need that then why you need that
then you can fix the the
largest hole maybe and also I would
assume
so basically it's just good to know
where the largest thing is because you
could probably pitch the most processes
in the largest bowl oh yeah
like it would create a very small hole
that we can fit no process into but with
the worst fit if you fit in a very large
hole you're much more likely to have a
hole still in your memory to fit another
Place yeah so what I said this thingies
are it's uh it's not like the Arabic the
scenes that you we don't know let's have
we need to have this in the same page
okay we do not want to create a lot of
mini mini holes a huge number of
fragmentations no one wants that
right you do not want your memory have
not infusions in the OS there's a tool
that is called the
um I think it's the diesel tool this
tool optimization tool you may be able
to use that you can download that it
will help you to
minimize the fragmentation in the disk
that's the same idea they are going to
move the files together because to
minimize the small holes in the memory
the same thing we do not want to create
many small holes because it's very
inefficient why it is inefficient
because while new process comes
it may be medium it may be large if it
is medium it's large or it's small it
cannot fit in the tiny holes
up
in on the opposite we do not have any
holes we just everything is compact with
each other everything compared to each
other another tiny horse can be
aggregated together to become a small
horse or medium hose to be able to fit
more process our goal is to make the
best use of memory so we need to be in
the same page is that we do not want to
create many tiny holes then the worst
fish approach that is the opposite it
will create many tiny mini holes and
everywhere and everywhere why because
it's always finders largest hole that
fits okay it's always find out the
largest holder fits and the process made
ones for a very long time and eventually
all the largest spaces are going to be
taken and creating many small mini
spaces and the large space is let's say
a larger process is leaves only the
process that is smaller than the larger
can fit in and eventually the large
space will be many many small process no
big process can get in then why we still
need the word surface that is because we
do not want our approach to be like that
we need to have the upper bounds and the
lower bounds because this is for the
research respective when you are
designing an algorithm you want to know
the algorithms is good or not you first
have a optimal choice right you then you
have the Baseline choice so the worst
fees are like the Baseline
if I'm designed approach I'm just the
one percentage improvements
compared to the word surface then that
means my solution is bad
okay so that is just a baseline yeah
magician
oh yeah yeah so okay the most okay you
know in current operating systems most
approach that we use is actually Quick
Fix it's very smart idea it's very smart
idea so anyone want to make a guess
about the Quick Fix looks work quick fix
well what date
yeah
a list of common sizes
what are the common sizes what are the
common sizes
which side shows up the most like if
each side maybe has a counter we have a
priority queue of like of sight of like
locations in the of locations of holes
or something yeah using that priority
view Maybe
which side is
yeah using a counter in a priority queue
that's
yeah so uh sort of quick fix approach is
that we we so here's the the idea is
that how how do you find out the um
the horse to put the new process right
put the new process the first surface is
that I always find out the first one
that fits the next phase means that I
starting from the where towards the
pointer we do not send the point at the
beginning we start where it was okay the
best surface is that I searched from the
beginning to the end to find out the
hole that matches exactly the same size
of my process and the worst fee says
that I go to obviously I find if I'm the
size of like very tidy then I find out
the largest host I always find out the
largest holes for that for my process I
do not look at the smallest that fit my
list I look at the largest to fit my
list the Quick Fix means that it's going
to use several pointers to keep track of
the common sizes what are common sizes
common sizes for example you know in
this in the textbook it gave a solution
that it keeps tracks of every host that
is have the size of two and going to
have the pointer to point out the
addresses for every holes the size of
four and every hole says size of A's and
every hole size of 16. so starting from
the small one to the big one so they
track all the common sizes in different
categories and whenever a new process
comes in is looking at this
different category to find out what the
best category that can fit in so that is
is actually uh our model operating
system using this approach is very our
it's kind of find out the trade-off from
the
Simplicity like how easy it can be
implemented and then the efficiency it's
a trade-off it's Trader of choice so
that is the Quick Fix okay
now this is
this is over all the approaches this is
all other approaches well
so in summary
we have learned
what people did like
maybe
um
is actually maybe 15 years ago 15 50
years ago
115 to 100 years ago that is the first
raw generation of operating systems you
you are very young are you you anyone
heard of MS-DOS
Ms stores no no one
MS-DOS
this
no one no one heard of that you heard of
that
yeah yeah it's Bill Gates yeah yeah
initially there's no UI the operating
system no there's no UI it's just uh you
type you're facing your type so and
the MS stores age that is the how they
use this the swapping swapping approach
swapping swapping approach to managing
the memory now we know that
so this is the history of my memory the
history of memory we have learned these
Concepts okay
address space we use the base and limits
to represent the way the process is then
we use different data structures to
track the free resources in the memory
we have the bitmap approach we have the
linked list approach so you need to
understand the good thing about beam map
and the best thing about me map the good
thing about linked list and the best
thing about linked list so let's say we
use the linked list approach to track
the free memory
then for
how to choose how to choose the best
holes to fear my new process there are
several approaches the first feat was
the fees a second feeds best face quick
fees there are many approaches you need
to understand the differences about
these approaches now come to the
beginning swapping is that good swap
swap is not good it's not good I will
tell you why it is not good because it
basically has no obstruction has no
abstractions has no obstruction for the
memory it's just use the physical
resources of the memory it has it has
very simple resource management
to managing the hardware resources it
has no obstruction of the memory the
swap technology is not good now the
modern operating system they design a
new approach required virtual memory
virtual memory then that is the
that is the um
key Concept in this chapter the virtual
memory so let's first look at the
virtual memory history why we need
virtual memory
so and you still don't want to make a
guess about what exactly virtual memory
is what exactly virtual memory is
munchies
well that is why I writing the slides
but I did a lot of virtual library
it's it's actually ask you the um
is the motivation of the virtual memory
uh it's not a it's not a
it's not a key conception yes
virtual memory right so it looks the
program like a contiguous like
like you know block of memory but in
reality it's chalked up it's a little
slices but throughout the
very close very close so I will continue
what's your name
is marching orders one matcher okay so
here's the one Marshall I mentioned that
virtual memory is that if you will give
you you have a process and give you the
illusion that you you seems you have a
whole memory address space
but actually you just have yeah
that is how we implement the virtual
memory but it's not the it's not the
um
intuition about the virtual memory the
key idea of the virtual memory let's get
a key idea first okay what exactly
virtual memory we are going to we are
going to look at the details the
technical details later but let's get to
the key idea of the virtual memory yes
oh
uh no no I will make a real life example
okay so
um
what exactly version might make a real
life example okay
okay this is uh uh okay
okay so so here's the thing okay I I
play this is using the same example I
play A League of Legends okay so this is
very large
how large is it and you still don't know
how large is it
when you downloaded that how large is it
I think it's around four gigabytes
four gigabytes it's very large very
large you download that you downloaded
that the software is four gigabytes so
that's four gigabytes we it's it has a
client right LOL I think it's called iOS
clients
so you create the clients basically
launch that program right so when we
downloaded that this is just a program
we have not yet run it so it's just a
program it's a it's that it's not even
live so it's not process right but if we
if we click it we log in and we're
starting this process then it's become a
process right in your
if you look at your um the current
running active process you can show it
it has a lol.agents like the clients
running there okay
is as large as four gigabytes it's
larger than four gigabytes and then the
largest and large it I logic okay
so the first question is that these four
gigabytes
4 gigabytes of the code
then we launch it in May it may become
even larger because it's dynamically
allocates more memory resources right
let's say let's just say it's just a
four gigabytes
this is a program okay my first question
is that when I logic I have the ROI
clients process
are we going to put all these four
gigabytes of code in the memory
no we are not going to put the order in
a memory right
why because why think of a why why we
are not going to put all four gigabytes
in the memory
how large is your memory is
yeah
yeah the other processor the OS may
already taken
several gigabytes two gigabytes right
much
yeah many times we do not need that but
why we if let's say if you have an
inference of memory if I have influenced
amounts of memory
are you going to lower all this in the
memory
are you going to yes or no if you
if you have an infinite amount of memory
are you going to put that in the memory
or not yes or no
no anyone thinks yes
yeah Andrew you think yes yes
if I have impedance of memory I'm going
to put order in the memory if I have
inference I have 1 000 10 000 gigabytes
of memory I'm going to put everything in
the memory why because memory
hierarchical structure tells us
memory is faster than the disk
why you think this is slow in the first
slide we talk about as cash is fast
memory is fast
disk is slow cat register is super fast
if I have impedance of the memory I'm
going to put 4 gigabytes in the memory
right but the truth is that you are not
or start reach okay you can only have
eight gigabyte for memory you are for
students you do only have eight
gigabytes of memory so you sold Os Os
facing one Bill Gates they're facing all
the
students they do not have that they are
not that rich to House of 1000 of
gigabytes of memory so they they are
always when they design the OS
they are designed based on okay as long
as you have eight gigabytes of memory
you can play these games you can play
these games mean while watching the TV
mean watching the YouTube video
meanwhile using your Microsoft documents
like Microsoft I think Microsoft reward
how large it is maybe also four
gigabytes I forget right you can do
everything together you can do
everything together
and I think I have many other process
right the OS the OS may take other two
gigabytes then you have other like UI
the drivers they also take several like
one gigabytes so we cannot hold
everything in the memory because we have
the very limited size of the memory
then we design virtual memory then what
exactly virtual memory anyone maker can
make a guess
anyone can make a guess
or this is the what this word means like
it's not a physical so this is the
physical the 80 gigabytes is physical
right
then where are the maps
the wire is virtual space
in the next internet internet is not in
the internet
in the cloud not in the cloud okay not
in the cloud where the
very good natural disk okay this is the
concept of the virtual memory student
that's the concept of virtual memory I
have a very large six software while
software I can load load everything
inside of the memory at the same time
why because I have very limited meaning
limited memory size so what the OS can
do for me is that it gave me the
illusion that I have already loaded
everything the memory but actually not
actually not it gives me so this is what
I face okay the four gigabyte memory I
may only use one gigabytes or less than
that okay the other three gigabytes they
are in the disk they are still in the
disk okay the three gigabytes in the
disk and then one gigabyte in memory so
for this is my game but but it gave me
the illusion that I have all of them in
memory all of them in the memory so how
they give me the illusion that I have
all of them in the memory
or us give me a new obstruction called
virtual memory this software the LD of
Legends 4 gigabytes right it gives me a
virtual address he says that deleting
this is your memory it's one to four
gigabytes I gave it to you load your
process into that virtual memory it's
not real it's not real it's fake it's
fake
they gave me or you can think of just
gave you a data structure give you
illusion that you have used all this the
virtual the memory you have
puts everything in a fake memory in a
fake memory okay I post my game in the
fake memory the fake my but the fake
memory is actually some part of the fake
memory is in a disk it's some in the
disk and this other part of it in the
real memory in the physical memory then
what OS did
okay you are playing these games right
but you are not playing all the
Champions you are not playing all the
game types right you only just you may
at one time you may only use third part
of the code
right I'm playing around
148 Champion probably only one Champion
then just put this part of the Champions
that I'm using in the memory and for you
you play different Champions you play
different you put different part in the
memory everyone have their own contents
in the memory have all their own content
in the disk who decide that
all us decided so always what kind of or
how the OS decide that they're using a
lot of key Concepts
in the mom or even what are these kids
can separate that is Page table page
table
where you just mentioned that right the
page table to mapping mapping firmware
from virtual memory to physical memory
right
because you we have the 4 gigabytes of
the code right then I need to only I can
use only one gigabytes of the real
memory then you OS help me design what
part of the code is in the memory what
part of code not in the memory
and then
so page table May takes a lot of memory
than what we have we have tlv what is
tlb translation look outside buffer
translation local side buffer is just
the cache of the page table you think of
as just the cache of a page favorable it
contains the most frequently mappings of
the page table we are going to talk
about that in our last chapter but
before that we need to get the key idea
of the why we need a virtual memory
and what else so we have the page table
tlb and we have the concept while the
page frame
page frame and we have the mapping you
need to understand what is mapping and
when we think about mapping there are
some parameters to decide whether the
page is dirty where the page is not
dirty and we have we need to handle the
page forward
so these are our all new Concepts in the
virtual memory in the virtual under the
virtual memory but before we understand
the version we need to understand that
the key idea of the virtual memory is
that
they gave you the illusion that you have
the whole size of the memory but it
actually not you actually not okay you
have
so let
okay so the
so
the motivation is that why we need
virtual memory called because we want to
we need to
there's a needs okay you want to run the
multiple programs
in memory but each of the programs they
might be very large they may be very
large so we cannot fix them all together
into the memory then we have the concept
of the the virtual memory
the virtual memory can help us to do
that okay the virtual memory is that the
basic idea of the virtual memory is that
each program has its own address space
and then we divide the address space we
do not save any more about their face
and their limits instead we are going to
divide their address space into many
pages
like you guys if you are processed some
of use maybe big huge you take forces
five six some of you may just take one
six or two seats okay so I'm going to
divide my classroom into many seats okay
you some of you you take more seats some
of you may take glasses so in the memory
I'm going to divide my process into many
pages into many pages right now the
default size of the pages for four
kilobytes
and then and then we mapping that we
mapping the active page into the memory
and push the rest of the page in the
disk but you still have the inclusion
about everything is in the memory so
that is the idea key sounds concept of
the virtual memory okay so we are going
to discuss that later in our in surgery
class thank you
hi
page four page four
oh
f-a-u-l-t page Force yeah
foreign