foreign
okay
so we will have uh we will have a very
quick review about the file systems when
we start to the next chapter or as hot
topics so file system I'm going to
review all the key concepts of of the
file systems okay
um
so when we are talking about file system
the key concepts of the file systems is
that we first look at it from the user's
point of view and when we see the file
systems we actually see it as a tree
structure
and are surrounding about around this
tree structure we have we have learned a
lot of fire operations
like create a file delete a file
copy or file so those are file
operations
so that is all from the system point of
view
this is the um the file attributes and
also the file operations
so you do not need to remember
everything of it you do not need to
remember because
they are very
frequently used but here you need to
remember is that all the file operations
are were in or trigger system course
so any students know why why why every
almost every file operations will
trigger the system core
so have you think about that
so when we talk about when we learn file
system we we when we learn our first
lesson we learned that ours is an
abstraction and resource manager right
and then a file file system is the
abstraction of the disk right
the hardware is a disk and the file
system is the abstraction of the disk
so if you look at these operations so
create these open close read write there
they're almost all operations
about how you're going to manipulate the
space in the disk how user going to
interact with the hardware user user and
the hardware and the OS is in the middle
right OS providing the beautiful
interfaces for the users for the ugly
Hardware that is what we learned in the
first lesson so that is why almost file
operations will trigger the system core
because these operations almost all of
these operations user needs to interact
with the hardware Hardware of the disk
right and Os is obstruction of the disk
OS provides the file system as
obstruction of the disk that is why
they're all equals trigger the system
core
and then we learn the directories I've
already told you that directory is a
special form of file so if we look at
the system point we will see the
directory and the files they are
actually using the same data structure
and then what's the differences between
the absolute past and the
relative path
what is absolute path
so this is all from the user's point of
view what is the absolute path of the
file system
yeah I start with the loot right when we
when you when you need to locate the
file you start searching it sorry it's
you locate a file
then you
naming that file from the root directory
so that is the past names right we have
the absolute past that's the absolute
path and then what is a relative path
so there's the absolute absolute path
one of file system is organized also or
directory tree right there's two ways of
specifying file names one is we starting
from the loot directory and we look the
loop directory
let's say if I want to find I want to I
want to have the name absolute past
names of this file a we can I can start
from the loot directory then I can
locate that file another way that
are
passed from
root filed and
the relative past might just be part of
the only way
yeah where are you currently it is right
so absolute passes from the loot
directory and the relative pass starts
from the current position where you
currently is and with the let's say we
are in this folder then we can get a
file so that's the difference between
absolute past and uh
on the relative path
we also have many directory operations
directory operations
so let's starting from the Implement
implementer's point of views or the
system
when we do the system into
implementation
um
so how do we Implement a file system in
that case that is what we learned in our
last lecture
because it's been several days you may
already forget it so let's first look at
this picture
so this is a personal file system layout
so this is here this is the entire disk
we see an entire disk and we for the
entire disk
let's say that this conceit right you
need to for the disk this case like is
it looks like this this is a disk right
this is a disk so when we're talking
about this could be first thing is to
cartridge into many partitions right we
cut it into many partitions and inside
of each partition
then they have this data structure this
is a structure
so what is the block put block put block
so when we talk about block we need to
know that block what is exactly a block
is the units you you we used in a file
system to store files it's similar to
the page
in memory similar to the page the
concept of the page in the memory
chapter but in the in the in the file
system we call it every unit that we
used to store files it's called a block
a block a block you can single block
usually is 64 megabytes
so some some system 30 to 16 megabytes
it depends on different operating
systems and we have the boot block is
the starting start is the start of the
of the of the
of the disk partition right the start
block of the this partition
and then we have the super block so
super block have a includes a magic
number to include
to identify the file system type the
file system type we can have many type
of different file systems so
and the number of blocks in the file
system and the other key administrative
information in next common information
is that it's very important concept
after the Super block we have the
I node inodes I nodes so what is exactly
I know let's say another key Concept in
the file system
so what exactly is our eye notes
um
it's a number that corresponds to a
specific file it's not a number it's not
a number what is I know
yes Lily
I'm sorry
yeah it stores the index information
about the about the files right each
file has a in in I node right and then
what's the information is stored what's
the information is source
every file has an i node a directory
also has an inode
that is what yes
location of the oh okay it's not a
location of the memory
no it's not a location on the virtual
memory we we are in the file system
chapter right file system is the
abstraction of disk disk
right yeah
mm-hmm
permission yes then what else
what else what else I know
when we're talking about absolute past
and relative paths we all look at it
from the user's point of view but
actually the file can be very large your
movie is 10 gigabytes of movie you
cannot store that in one
place right Eric
um
very good very good so a file a file
will be divided into many blocks blocks
blocks is the units the smallest units
that we store the files in the disk
right and so a file can be broken into
many blocks then I know there was slowly
address information about where exactly
each block is physically in the disk so
it was it was stored mapping from the
the block number the virtual block
number two the physical block number it
will shows like the where is the
partition with the section number so
if we look at the hardware you can see
that this is the partition right then
there's a section and there's offset yes
yeah very good very good if if the if
the file is very big if a file is very
big then the inode maybe have several
layers if it has several layers then the
first I know points to the next level I
know that store the rest of the files
information
rest of that file so each file has a one
eye node that's why and then we see this
is this s here s
why this is why there's s because in the
disk in the disk partition this
partition there's tens of thousands of
files right there are many files each
file has a specific I node then we put
the inode there we put the I know there
and then starting from the next the next
wrestle place we store the Rook
directory yet at Endura
MBR is the it's because the um
oh I forgot the name it's called The
Master boot uh yeah rockers yeah yes
yeah Master boost records is used for
launching Lodge the operating system is
the starting so so useful for the BIOS
right you have the BIOS you need to you
this is the entry of the operating
system when you power it on
then operating system goes there because
they are rebooting it there's a master
boot records
yeah Andrew
yes it is it is so the sick the order
will not change
we always it's like a book you cannot
save the index information of the book
at the end of the book you always
you always puts the preface right in the
book if we open a book we see what is
the first page the first page you should
will show the orders right who is the
Watchers and the pictures and maybe some
numbers regarding the book and then the
next page is preface right preface is
like the MBR
it's like the starting of the book
preface like shows some story of why I
wrote this book and then starting there
we have the chap we have the index index
of each chapter where each chapter is
that is like this like like this
so everything in operation system using
a structure
from the uh a big summary and then
each uh each uh independent details the
same thing like file system in almost in
every file systems when we see a disk
competition we see that this is the
whole disc like this partition with we
want to see the
this the I know the information first
and then each files information okay
each files information
before we're talking about I know we
talk about several different approaches
that we used to managing the free
available spaces in the disk in this so
I noticed the last option but then we
also talking about continually
allocation linked list or location and
when we're talking about that for the
continual location it has the
disadvantage of creating a lot of
internal fragmentations right but the
good thing about that is very easy to
implement very easy to implement and
what else the good thing about that
the good thing about that
yes
goodread performance random read access
is also good okay read performance is
very good why because because the files
is stored together physically together
they are stored this is a file
there are virtually when we we see the
file we definitely see a file as a whole
we see I see a movie is just
a logo of the movie and then it's like
MP4 like that is my movie Once the movie
is a whole but physically it's also
stored as a whole it is a continually
allocation approach continuing education
approach so it's very easy to implement
the reader performance the random grid
performance random read access is super
good why because you
you locate the beginning of a big file
then you just need to know the size of
the file then you can almost point to
any position in the file because you
already know the beginning of the file
the beginning of the file is just the
plus the offset then you can jump to any
position of the file so the read
performance is good is great
and then the bad thing about that the
disk becomes fragmented over time so
because
so that is why we use continual occasion
not in modern operating system but we
use that in some like DVD or CD
there are Futures is that they are
they are read only right you cannot you
cannot you
it's like you almost like uh I don't
know if you are familiar with the CD-ROM
I used to uh
to to user user to play with it for a
long time it's in when I was 18. I
listened to the music and I have
I bought a lot of CDs and also why why
why we use continue allocation approach
to in this material because when you
listen to the music you you loaded a lot
and you
you just need to
listen the music like one by one and you
readily change it
and then we talk about another another
location approach linked list of pro
approach
so lingerless approach is the good thing
that is get rid of fragmentation but the
random access is slow it's slow because
you need to change the pointers to get
to a block think of that so you I need
to get the end of the file so I only
know the beginning of the file then I
have to I have to chase it Chase it one
by one jump it one by one because I will
never know where it ends so that's why
that's why I know the approach got
developed right okay I know the approach
got developed
so
um
the the good things about I node is that
the good things about I noticed that we
already know the files is broken into
many blocks so I know to save the
location of each block right of each
block then you only need to load I node
this I know data structure into the
memory you whenever you need to you need
to look at any position read any
position of the file you just need to
load it into memory then you almost know
every
part of the file for example if the file
has Ace blocks I need this is a movie I
want to see the middle of the movie then
I just need to check that I know this I
know the data structure I just checked
okay give me the address of the diesel
block 4. this or this block 3
give me this position right the address
the address is the physical address is
the disk address so I only needs to load
that in your memory and then ask it ask
it can you give me that
address
then
then after I got a physical address the
physical address will be looks like okay
the partition number the section number
the offset then I can directly points to
that I can answer my operations from the
point that it's very easy so the read
performance is good right the read
performance is good it also reduce
reduce the internal fragmentations why
it should reduce the internal
fragmentations any students think of
that
Maja
a smaller block a blocking from like a
smaller Gap in the whole aisle yes files
is divided in it's broken into many
blocks right It's let's say for um I
have a 1000 megabytes of file each each
blocks is 84 megabytes then I divide it
then I I know how many blocks that I
need then these blocks are spread over
all this it can be anywhere so whenever
it has empty place and it can fix that
blocks I can put that
it's it's it effectively reduce the
internal fragmentation so I know this
approach that
combine the benefits the advantages of
continually location approach and linked
list approach
okay
so in so you need to understand this
story right because we are learning a
computer system as a class this system
you need to have a you I hope that you
do not just memorize in these Concepts
you need to understand it in the exam I
may give you a question like ask you to
design a file system that fits my needs
I will tell you what I need and then you
think of approach that you learn from
this course to design it okay
so uh try to understand the advantage
and disadvantage of each Pro each of
each approach okay
oh
let's go to this
okay and then we're talking about the
shared file share file when one
for several users are going to share the
same file the same file
then how you how how can the operating
system manage it because if in many
let's say we we three people are working
on the same projects and we share some
files right so if I'm the only one
if I'm the only one to delete the file
you guys should not be affected because
you are also working on that that
folders right you may need to keep that
file so how the operating system know
that the file is no longer leaded by
anyone that who is want to share in this
file then we we have the new Concepts
it's called reference cons reference
counts and this reference comes
um this is a very simple data structure
it's just adding a variable in the inode
the I know the data structure but it's
very useful so the reference console
will give you the information about how
many people are currently share these
files and while each turns on zero when
it turns on zero that means no one no
one is using their file anymore everyone
is already
planning to delete that file then the
disks are going to recycle in that file
okay
so that is the reference count
so okay so let's
uh
so let's review the steps in looking
looking up this directory this is our
absolute spot s absolute parts so we
first what we do okay before that we
what is I know the table we mentioned
that in our last class I know the table
any student remember we know that I know
the right I know that I know to save the
fire attributes and the block address of
that file then what is inode table
what is that I know the table
yes
directory of the inode
what is I note I Note Everything
um
yes okay yes so here's the thing why we
need I know the table if you look at
this picture you see
you see where where the where the I know
the table is so what am I saying every
directory right
is almost in every directory right why
we need I know table
because because in the directory no
directory in the directory the directory
may have many subdirectories right then
subdirectory may have an in subdirectory
so this directory the I know the data
structure is very big I know this data
structure may be very big
see this is the inode structure if the
fire is Big the inode structure may have
several layers the I know the structure
is very big
then because I know the structure is
very big then we add in another
obstruction on top of the inode
structure we use I know the number this
is a unique number
to represent that the inode
I node the location
so you can think of that
you have a drive lessons right the drive
lessons have your information right but
your drive license has a unique ID right
then then the directory only saved ID
only saved ID they will not save the
whole information will drive lessons the
whole information for the inode that is
the inode table that is I know table so
whenever we look at this this like let's
see well we go we go from the new
directory right the root directory
is the rule directory will
will almost every every file system can
easily locate to the root directly why
the rule directly is directory is is
simply
after
the I know you see here
where's the new directory
check this
see where the loop directory
you see here right it's here the loot
directory is here
so when we when we when we locate any
files we always start from the loot
directory we go to the root directory
and we're looking at the us our usrtc is
a directory we need to find out the I
know the information of this we need to
locate to this I node
we need to look into this I node right
so we locate we see the ID
the load the inode ID of this directory
the subdirectory right user directory
and then we got uh the I know table we
after we find out the ID okay the ID is
6.96 then we can find out the I node we
can find out the I node okay this is the
exactly I node of that I know 6 says
that USR is in the block of
130 to 132 then we find out the block 1
32 we find out the block this is the
physical number we find the block 132
then we can find out the exactly
contents
in the dash USR and Industry since it is
also a directory so it saved it has many
subdirectories right you are not you are
not this USI is not a file it's just a
directory so it means under this it has
many subdirectories and we need to find
out the I know the ID of this directory
which is the AST AST then it has a
unique load you you see this is unique
okay unique AST okay then we look at the
inode 26 we see that I know the 26 then
we find out this here the contents the
real contents of this directory and yes
both the unique ID and the memory
yeah so it's not it's not contains the
memory address but here
the we have the I know the table right
we know the item table is from one to a
very large number right and then there's
a space the other space in the disk and
also in the memory that stores as a
sequence
to save the information so we just need
to search it that is why you use the
inode ID it's from one let's say we only
have 100 different directories and files
right files has a as I know the ID and
also directory also has iron or ID then
you can just after you know the number
then you can point to it it's very easy
it's
then you have 26 right 26 AST then we we
find out the exactly content of the 26
we find out okay this is okay the block
address of this directory is in a 406
then we go to the 406
we see
this the inode right the inode I node
number of the this file this file is
Mbox right that is I know number is 16
right there's a one step left
it needs to look at the 16th where the
16th I know the information and after
you look at that I know the information
of the 16 you can find out where exactly
this file is
uh
it's a little tricky
so so I noticed that I know the ID is
just one step before you find inode you
do not because
we cannot deal we we need to blame the I
know the right a file has I know that
you need to have a way to name the I
know that is why we use the inode ID is
it's just a unique number you can limit
to in any files or directories
and then and then we save the inode in
one place in one place in memory why we
need to save it in the disk also in the
memory that is because you are not going
to open all the files at the same time
so most so all I know the information
are in the disk but the active files I
node are in the memory
active files
I know in the memory okay so this is the
file system chapter the review of this
chapter
so let's learn another file system that
is a distributed file system is one part
of our OS Hot Topics okay
so before we go to the distributed file
system we need to we need to uh
C have some background information
okay ah
Big Data why I'm talking Big Data before
the distributed file system because
emojis
sometimes
the data like a lot of data yeah we need
a we need
yeah yeah
yeah
yeah so big data is is a trend it's very
important right now right so why why we
need to talk about Big Data because the
because this there's a lot of data right
and you cannot save it in one file
system locally we need many
machines together to constitute a
distributed file system so what it means
by Distributing the file system
distributed file system
simply makes it simply guessing it okay
one computer is not enough we add in 10
thousands of computers together and
Aggregates their spaces making them look
like a one file system then that file
system is called distributed file system
why to call distributed file system
because it is consists of not only one
machine that consists of 10 thousands of
machines and they are logically sorry
they are physically distributed that is
why it's called distributed file system
okay and then what is Big Data so big
data is oh okay this is
that is very big okay it's not that
complex
is very big a lot of formats and complex
okay large amounts so how big did you
speak or how big do you speak
these are all the data we have more data
so we are looking at the databytes
your habites of scale how big it is big
okay and it's almost increasing like it
is portion only it's increasing very big
so who is generating Big Data everyone
every one of you is generating Big Data
you may not notice wherever you are
using your cell phone your activities
are going to be locked by the back end
whenever you are purchasing an item in
the Amazon Amazon get all of your
information what you like what you do
not like what you are going to purchase
together
what kind of persons you are for example
if you always purchase the cheap items
they will not think that you are
rich person then when they give you the
recommendations you will not receive
some recommendations like
expensive item you may receive the item
that is in your range okay in the in
your intense range that is
there's a lot of study about that
I did some research about that it's like
now in my stream processing system
research part of my research okay it's
very interesting
um
you you you'll never realize how this
big these companies capturing your
activity what makes all your activities
are going to be analyzed and they have
they have many processes at the back end
to analyze your behavior
so there's a lot of big data we need to
find a way to save this big data we need
to find a way to save this big data so
before we're talking about the way that
we save this big data let's talking
about the way that we process this big
data okay so I'm going to introduce you
a very classic
model that we process the big data is
called the mapreduce model you already
know that of course your project 2 is
about it
I hope you like it because it will be
very useful USB as major students if if
you graduate and people ask you what is
examples you do not know then you should
be ashamed of all that because it's a
very classic yahoo first developed that
and then Google has been used for many
years but they recently there are of
some Modern
architecture
and disregard mapreduce however it's
very classic so what is the map reduce
mapreduce means that if you have a big
thing if you have a big task you cannot
finish the buy one
one computer one person if you cannot
finish the by a
one let's say super computer then why
not you just divide this work
into many small parts and ask
some more motions to finish it
for you and then later you as the master
you just need to aggregate the results
so that is the divide and conquer
concept we divide the work and then we
combine the results then the good thing
about this approach is that it is very
very scalable why it is very scalable
where is the bottleneck the bottom lock
is owning in the master right the master
is doing the dividing the work
give me one second
foreign
like I need to divide the work for
example I have if I have right now I
have 100 students so I prepare 100 exam
papers I gave it to you you guys finish
it and then I aggregate the results I
come back I get the results all the
results but if I have 1 000 students I
will do the same thing I will prepare
1000 papers and then distribute it and
then I come I combine the results if I
have 10 000 students I'm also doing the
same thing so I'm the only important
like the master doing the Divide work
and combined results is only important
so if it is a super it's if it is a
difficult thing then I can divide it
into many many small parts and then
divide it and hire many workers as many
as I want to help me finish it so it is
very scalable
hey
pardon distributed processing so this is
called distributed processing this
processing is long tuber it's
non-trivial why it is lounge River well
like you guys okay some of you are very
hard hard working like this course some
of you may
like the other course and do not want to
devote your time into that course so
let's say some are very productive some
are not productive right
and some even quit this course right
some fails like what happens if the task
fails how to assign to different workers
in an efficient way how do workers
exchange the results
why they need to exchange the results
if it is a graph let's say it's a graph
processing work I do not know if you are
you you have done anything about the
graph in the graph algorithms there's
algorithms called like we calculating
the page rank right we're calculating
the page Rank and we're covering the
page rank calculating the shortest path
shortest pass we calculating the
connected components
in the graph for this graph
work big graph work like in Facebook
has a super huge graph of the social
media like I'm the friends of another
person so the graph is huge is graph is
huge then when I divided the graphs I
made divided into a wrong way and the
only workers need to exchange the
results
the exchangeable results between sure
and accurate accurate
outputs so how do workers exchange the
result how to synchronize distributed
worker allocates to different workers
well I'm asking I'm asking these
questions to you you can you creatively
answer this how to assign the task code
to different workers in an efficient way
yes
if you have to say a number for how like
good they are at the job and
track of how available they are then you
know that you know what worker you want
to assign away
okay okay they're very good very good
but but the challenge I will give you
another chance the challenging is that
I I worry about the beginning I know
nothing about these workers I do not
know how good they are
you cannot guess you can just like
sync them as the same right that is why
we have when we're setting a system we
give the default settings
pardon
how are you going to yeah
yeah very good very good this is how to
see some video I'll show you I will tell
you a lot of balances why load balancer
has a low balance to keep monitoring it
like first we will not have a low
balance to keep monitoring we will have
a separate monitor sometimes we use the
software called Zone keeper to do that
um you are used to actually if you
become a software engineering because
almost all the Distributors see some
companies use that software so we have
let's say we have a Monitor to Monitor
in their progress and we found out a
worker is very slow we call it a
struggler than what we did we are going
to do what we are going to we are going
to hire another worker to do the same
work and then after we found out that he
did faster than the slower one we do a
quick replace
that is how the mapreduce system did
okay
so what happens if the task fail any
students have a
so for example if therefore I I have a
100 let's see here I have I have
hear the thing okay I have 10 gigabytes
of the word content word office like
um how to say that like documents 10
gigabytes of documents it's like 10
thousands of files I need to you guys to
try and convert it for me to convert it
from the world contents to the PDF
contents so I'm what I'm going to do is
that I have this 100 students right you
are all my workers so I divide my
documents
evenly in 100 parts and I find each of
you
like like turns out like one
ten thousand like one thousand okay each
of you got one thousand ten thousand one
hundred if I have one hundred thousand
of files okay and then each of you got
one thousand files you guys try and
convert this file from the document the
word format to the PDF format and give
me back give me back tomorrow okay what
if one of you guys
half of some emergency so you cannot do
this work
how can I ensure that I got in love for
I got the order
files for all the formatted files like
the PDF files
I have 100 000 files it then I divided
it to you each of you have one thousand
but
it's possible like some emergency
happens some students cannot finish this
work
and the guy yes
very good that is the that is what we do
okay we are going to learn that later
how we did that but you have an
intuition first
while the task fail what is tough fair
then I have backup instead of give each
one of you 1000 I give each one of you
three thousand
so you cover another two students each
of you can cover any random two students
then the chance is that
I can I can tolerate multiple failures
right I can talk because whenever a
failure I want a student fails
another two students that contains her
or his work that is called replicate
replication
how to singularize distributed tasks
located to different workers of
synchronize the same thing how we handle
the strugglers like how synchronize
their progress synchronize their
progress how we synchronize that we
learn it
how we synchronize that
synchronize
yeah array
so that is for the camp process
communication
but we learned that in that chapter we
set a barrier right when we do
synchronization it's always the concept
of barrier
b-a-r-r-i-e-r
remember this burial we saw
so let's look at how we did that okay
so big data storage is challenging it's
challenging okay we have huge size of
data
reliability of storing this data is
challenging all kinds of failures of
this failure Hardware failure Network
failure all kinds of failures
probability of failures simply increase
with the number of motions
so there's some more motions more fails
okay
that's very easy to understand so
well then so it's hard to say that so
a lot huge size of a lot of data a lot
of data and a lot of failures a lot of
failures okay so here's the solution
foreign
of the distributor file system it's like
we say the
when we talk when we
um file system is just one part of the
file system right here one type of file
signal Hadoop is just the one product of
the distributed file systems so any
students
heard of Hadoop
Hadoop
what Hadoop offers is offered as offers
okay it's
um
so Hadoop
so before we're talking about the Hadoop
with like
um you know the map reduce mapreduce is
very successful might produce
computation model is very successful
right we already know how successful it
is but the interesting thing I want to
tell you a story about that one member
use is further developed and the
researcher researchers feel very excited
he feels that his computation model is
super smart so he wrote a paper about
that and he submitted to a
like very famous conference and then the
conference rejects that
so like reject it and he submitted like
several times but it all got rejected
then he in
he
but then he
like I think he submitted to a
not-famous place and then finally got
accepted but he does not have no idea
how successful the mapreduce model would
be like my produced in a page rank or
all these models okay this is a very
interesting story and same as the Yahoo
so Yahoo Yahoo later sell this the
distributor file system to Google so
Google has been using for very long time
and then Google developed the big table
you may heard of that it's called it's
um
it is also part of the Hadoop the Hadoop
project okay so let's talk about see how
what had with Hadoop means Hadoop
distributed file system so DFS so before
we talk about DFS any students heard of
NFS
unfs
what is on FS you should know that
all right
working class
even myself
this Samurai
no
no network file system you you use
dropbox right
Dropbox is uh
very very later version of the NFS
Network file system right so hdfs Hadoop
distributed file system okay
what Hadoop let's see what Hadoop offers
is that
is offers a very reliable reliable this
is the keywords okay how do what Hadoop
offers is that reliable for torrent file
system reliable for torrents file system
to store a huge amount of Big Data huge
amount of big data so every file system
they have a system go into the
hdfs heat system goal is her system goal
is for tolerance for tolerance then as a
programmer you no longer need to worry
about where the file is located
how to handle failures and data loss how
to divide the computation how to program
for scaling
foreign
so this is a real word example that use
heart use Hadoop file systems Hadoop
file systems is the file system that
supports mapreduce okay so the goal the
make the entire
let's say we have okay we have this
articles we need to translate this into
the PDF we need to translate this into
the PDF so our solution our solution is
using the
Amazon ec2 servers and a simple storage
systems so it translates four terabytes
of images to PDF files okay okay so
how much time and how much cost
if if if it is owned by you you need to
do that think of that do it in your
laptop how much time it will take and
how much cost it will you will have
or if you we put the Amazon ec2 servers
in a simple storage system like S3
we only need 24 hours and of course is
240 dollars okay 240 dollars
seeing the other slides about that the
the original cost
star slide there's an original course
okay there's the original code so it's
super high
so we are happy okay
so this is a little story about Hadoop
so it's Hadoop is open source
implementation based on Google file
system and mapreduce from Google
I was created by
them in the related to
Apache in
2006 so this is a Hadoop slack Hadoop
slack uh
so had to this is the Hadoop hdfs okay
Hadoop this hdfs and then my producer is
working on top of it Peak hive
because
Central and Edge base you can think of
that they are just a
more beautiful libraries or interfaces
of mapreduce
they are more user-friendly they are
more user-friendly so in the map reduce
if you play with the software well we
need to we need to roll the map code and
the reduce code in Java right and then
we combine it and then run it it's not a
user friend frequently user
friendly because if you are not a system
programmer you do not load code you know
nothing about coding you may find out
it's very hard to use mapreduce that is
why this other software developed so for
using if you're using this software you
do not need to write a code you do not
need to write a mapreduce code you just
need to
familiar with their
their command you just need to familiar
with their comments then you can know
how to use it
so today we are going to discuss how the
hdfs is developed okay so so there are
some hdfs resources certain unless
starting around the motivation and then
I textual Concepts inside and user
interface okay
the first questions data is too big to
store on one version so what is solution
now you are you you are the designer of
the hdfs
data is too big to store on one machine
break it up and
so data is still is too big to store on
one version
yeah
store on multiple machines so we store
the data on multiple machines will break
the data up into many parts and restore
it into multiple machines
the next question yes
where how many drives you can hold in
one server how many drives you can have
it's
terabytes or petabytes of data
is it huge it's huge can you put one
like 10 000 of the drivers in one server
you do not have that power supply to
support it
how much space well you you you you have
you
how large is your this case one terabyte
we are looking at the data of this size
see this side all sides over there
you see
we are looking at this
yoga Wise It's not terabytes
you you your server cannot hold one
thousand ten thousand servers okay let's
continue
so store the data on multiple machines
actually many machines store the data on
many machines okay see but let's say the
motivation question two very high end
machines are too expensive then what is
our solution
so we store the data we divide the data
into many parts and we put them into
many machines and what if we cannot
afford
expensive machines
yes
so what what text is curling so
how
yes very good use more cheaper machines
use more cheaper machines right if let's
say the data can put that into three
machines for three super motions then we
can choose 13 cheaper versions
30 is cheaper machines so this is hdfs
solution
you are smart
that is how the how they these two
software engineering they designed the
hdfs they think of the same way okay the
community Hardware will fail or fail
what if the hardware fail so Hardware
emits the disk disk fail let's say disk
fail
the disk fails
the hardware fails the hardware fails
yeah it's very good we are good so data
redundancy reduce the replications with
the software approach to handle the
hardware failures that's a that's a key
concept so if Hardware is easy to fail
then we use some like redundancy
replication approach
that's the same as this what happens to
the data if the machine store the data
fails so the data fails we do the
replicate the data we do some redundancy
okay redundancy we use the software
approach to handle the hardware failures
how can distributed machines organize
the data in a coordinated way
accordingly or these questions let me
cross clarify this problem okay this
problem this problem asks you
how you going to disease you need to you
you have the input like when we talk
about system we will always talk about
before you for every system's design
okay when you are when you intend to
Design Systems you do not start from the
scratch do not start like calling it
think of that think of the input what
will be the input what will be the
output what will be the requirements
right so here the input is a bunch of
data a lot of data this is the inputs
and what I have what I have the hardware
I have is that the input is like many
many chip machines they are easy to fail
Okay so
what I have is some cheap motions what I
have is a lot of a lot a large amount of
data different data formats like
pictures images
documents PDFs movies
right so these are files so how can we
distribute the machines over like this
file in a coordinate way so how to do
that
how we're going to module
what are other architectures you have in
mind
that is my one my slides has
other architectures that you you have in
mind you basically ask you how you're
going to
how you're going to distribute the data
into many machines like the example I
gave to you is that I have many 10 100
thousands of documents that lead me to
help need you to help me
convert it into the PDF right I said
that I am the teacher so I assign this
work to you you guys each finish it for
me that is the master and the slave
architecture I'm the master you are a
slave okay no offense okay
that is the Master's life architecture
that's a muscle sleep architecture other
architectures you might think of that
you know other architectures yeah
what is exactly peer-to-peer anyone
heard of peer-to-peer
a lot of peer-to-peer yeah what is
peer-to-peer
yeah very good so it's not a permission
and access level it's like peer-to-peer
model means that I'm like you there's no
distinguish between the master and the
slaves okay
I'm like you you like me so we we
are the same peers that is the
peer-to-peer we have the same duties and
responsibilities so sometimes you make
you make the decision for me and I make
the decision for you and you also make
the decision for your labors so that is
appeal to peer peer-to-peer it's like
everyone can behave like a server
everyone and any like a master everyone
can also behave as a slave so you and
then the system can decide who will be
the slave who will be the master in
which circumstances but most of times
you guys have the same Duty and
responsibilities so the peer-to-peer
architecture has been commonly used in
many software like scalable software
like
um Skype Skype
Skype right you subscribe my many times
right the the phone
the underlying protocol is the
peer-to-peer protocol
BT tolerance
Beauty tolerance is also a very classic
software of the peer-to-peer system
season 2 and
um
YouTube is not YouTube is not okay
what are the architectures what other
architectures you might think of that
Master Slave
one master designed distributed work to
slaves and slaves to the same work then
combined Master combined results
peer-to-peer means that okay everyone
can be have the same duties and
responsibilities so you contribute one
contributes to all what contributes to
one like
is a famous saying about us like I
so you work for everyone and everyone is
working for you something like that so
that is peer-to-peer architecture any
other architectures
any other architecture
or single creatively
hierarchical architecture right
hierarchical architecture so it's not
just the Master Slave it's maybe half a
master
and then
it's actually have like master and then
maybe some small Master like
then a slave I don't know it has two
layers it may have many many layers that
is a hierarchical architecture what else
yes
the same it's the same client server
well here's the thing when we are
talking master and slave
you will think of the situation for one
master and a 10 slave something like
this but while you're talking about the
several clients it's maybe only one
server for one client
so the muscle slave is more
um
because it's a slave right many slaves a
master have many sleeves it's not like a
server has many clients and sometimes
the server can only have
several clients
okay so but it's one part is the same
it's actually very similar
where we have Master Slave architecture
oh I will post some some architecture to
you okay we have a Master Slave
architecture hierarchical architecture
peer-to-peer architecture what we can
have is a hybrid architecture hybrid
architecture means that it's a mix of
it's me let's say it's mix of the muscle
strength and peer-to-peer for example in
the peer-to-peer you can save some node
as a super low the super node has some
master attributes this is the system
architecture used in the Skype protocol
Sky protocol
um what else yeah there are many
different architectures but the takeaway
here is that hdfs use master and slave
architecture so what exactly must the
slave attention here in the master
here's the slaves okay the master is a
one note it's a one server so here in
the system we have seven servers seven
servers
now these seven servers together
constitute a file system record or
distributed file systems so
when we're talking about file systems
we're talking about an important
Concepts right
foreign
give you something okay when we're
talking about the file systems we we're
talking about an important abstraction
it's called the
I know the right I know we say that
every file has an inode right every
files has a i node every files has an
inode now the slaves
so where I should put I node in this
case
I have many files right
so each file profile has an inode I know
it's like a metadata of this file right
the metadata of this file so where I
should put the inode much
Master we as Master Guard all I know the
information or I know the information
then farewell we've put the files in
these slaves right they are the data
node they are the data node
so the master master
is called the
name node we call it a name node it's
it's saved information it's a safe
information name node okay save the
information of all I node I know the
information of the files files and
install it okay I know the shows to
block mappings right that I what I told
you right I noticed the blocking address
of each file that is the from the
virtual block number to the physical to
the physical address in the disk that is
the block mappings
so the I know the information all the
files I know the information is in the
master it's in the master
and then the data node data node
data node is responsible to saving the
to save in the files
and doing the replication why we need to
do the replication
what we need to do application because
at the beginning we're saying that we
are using chip machines and shipping
machines are easy to fail if the if the
node fails then we lost the data so we
do some replication
for failure recovery right
over here what is the secondary limb
node
Master is the name node right what is
the second rename node
foreign
useful for to do the Fatal recovery of
the master of the master that is the
secondary name node okay
okay so let's look at the
hdfs structure this is the Master Slave
structure okay
hmm
so we bought
the file system this is a architecture
of the distributed file system
um
so
let's say you come now you join your big
company like VMware VMware is actually
using this okay they have many servers
10 100 servers okay the servers rack do
you know what is rack Rack anyone heard
of rack
Magic
thing that they put on the servers yeah
the physical the server is low like your
desktop server like this the server is
is look like the shape of braid
it's like this
you see anyone see the real server yeah
yeah it and then we insert that into the
rack so a rack will have like 40 servers
usually you're the most times a record
have 40 servers
inside of the rack their communication
is very fast but between the racks
between the racks the communication is
slow why
because the Rocks rocks to rocks needs
to use the switch switch is slow
and then after the switch we have the oh
okay it is sometimes it's used
to actually use the top of rack servers
on top of rack router and then on top of
rack router to talk about the rock
launcher using the switch and it's
slower and slower that is the tree
structure of the data center
okay so we we have the machine we have
the servers okay this the data node data
node they are there they are in
different racks in different like their
data not in different racks okay the
data our data is there and then we have
the name node okay each rack have a name
node okay
foreign
mappings of this data nodes this data
and we have a secondary name node okay
secondary name node now here's the
question here's the question
we know that we are going to use the
replication approach to replicate the
data right
what is a replication Factor
replica replication Factor
how many
how many how many let's say
if this racks fails right all the data
belonging to disrupt or will be lost if
the replication factor in equals to one
then that means there's low replica
if it is equal to one then that means
there's no replica right sorry no no if
it equals to zero then that means
there's no replica so if there's no
replica then whatever the data here is
lost
there's no way to retrieve the data you
have to do the things all again you have
to ask your Masters give me the file
again so the master downloads the files
again and give it to you and needs to
check what you have and you can give the
file to you again
this is very incompicious right so we
use a replica replication but what is
the replication Factor like how many
copies that you need
for each machine and where do you save
these copies
let's say the copies we only need one
copy okay so we store for each machine
with each machine we store one copy of
their code their data where do we store
where do we store
where yes
very good I put you put it into this
difference rank difference reacts
but what if they what if you for
different racks you need to go through
this switch right so I already told you
the situation is slow
right then one replica may not in love
so let's say I choose two replicas
that is stored in one of the rocks
let's say this this for these files
replica I saw it on different drugs than
what else
where I should store this replica
another another replica
huh
and the original rack very good cause
original record like laboring node for
the laboring node is very fast right
you do not need to go through the
switches it's very fast right so you can
push it simply there simply there
then how about the
okay let's continue okay let's continue
so the name node knows all blocks and
replicas name node notes all the block
mappings and replicas yes
they they are using the uh
I think it's around the 10 gigabytes of
intro landscape
local area land work
yeah yeah yeah they're just the cables
this is what you should learn in the
light working class right they are
definitely not connected with Wi-Fi
yeah
so this is a data center yes
yes
we think the rack is always the fast
if I'm if we are in the
um so right now you may not that kind of
that impression because everyone is
using Wi-Fi so you have you do not
realize the speed differences between
the rats and then across the Rocks we
see the Rock and of course the Rock
um
think of the case I have a your I have a
I'm in the lab I have a file and I need
to transfer it to my to my another lab
makes Liam me so we both connected with
L in the cable cable right so very fast
it's it's between us is very fast but
how about another lab mate who is in
China
it's very slow it will be very slow
because he needs to go over a lot of
switches
yes
oh that's good that's a very good
question they are actually
so there are there's something the
picture does not draw everything okay
in the big data center like Amazon ec2
what they have is that they have the
concept of the songs away they first
have the concept of regions
how many regions do you know the Amazon
used to has they have seven different
data centers
the two invert why is it in Virginia why
is in Ohio
um
I do not think California has one but
yeah I may forget but Tokyo has one and
uh
Japan has another one they have uh I
think it's when I do the experiments I I
I you I think they have eight seven or
eight different data centers and that is
a data center concept and inside of each
data center there's a concept of the
um the Zone The Zone so what is the Zone
the zone is actually like the class the
the loom the loom concept because you
cannot hold order servers or together in
a place you need to save it in a
in different places the cooling is very
expensive cooling so they have the zones
they have many zones and inside of each
Zone then they have many racks
and some racks May in the same room some
rocks May in the different room yeah
yeah yeah the Rocks well well you you
think it's a hierarchical structure the
speed we think the rock is always the
fast always fast because they are in the
same Rock they are connected with the
multiple servers in your same physical
yeah
they are not as fast as within the same
rack because they all need to go stock
the top of rack router there's a there's
a
let me show you a picture okay this is
something that oh we should know that
okay let me see anything let me see if I
can find
this
yeah okay
can you see this
so this is the data centers
Factory cloud data center three tier
Factory topology
so here
if you are you are belonging to
different drugs
all the Motions are going to share the
same module here this is the router
it may have only eight
ports then here the rock each Rock have
40 servers so you have 100 hundreds of
um let's say 40 servers in each rack
then these are not a 40 servers is they
both need to communicate with the same
router it's slow because the bandwidth
is just that big
right the bandwidth is just that big so
that is why we're crossing the Rocks is
very slow the same thing as this if you
are you you want to go through this to
go to another Rack in another Zone that
is super slow why because many many
servers are concurrently used that they
are shared they are shared you see the
number is very limited every rack has
only one top of top of wrap server that
is why this is the factory structure at
the beginning of the data center they
use a tree structure
if you if you learn the if you take the
lateral cost they you will learn that
this is an important class about the
architecture okay of the data center so
here the what is the factory factory
means that I add more branches at the
top of the tree the tree itself is very
slim but for fat tree I add more routers
and more routers in each branches so
that's why I can increase this increase
the bandwidth
for this for for sharing it okay for
sharing that is a factory structure okay
okay
okay yes
if
if there's Not in Love
yes yes
that is the case go about the hardware
as there are developing very fast
so you should know it should not that
big problem
but if this is you ask actually very
good question you know the um my
otherwise are used to my PhD always used
to tell me he talked to a Google
um
Google senior engineering is almost like
top top top five Engineering in the
Google and the data engineering told him
that Google Google has many ways of
saving the data replicates the data and
make the best use of data but Google has
not developed a good policy for deleting
the data because Google has no idea like
why like
like whether you may need that data or
not so he will what Google did his touch
he several times set a time for everyone
for storing the data for a super long
time but actually everyone has many data
like 90 percentage that they do not need
that but Google will not delete that
because
he doesn't he has no idea whether you
will use it in the future that's what
they are challenging okay they're
challenging because they want to make
the best use of the storage space okay
so let's look keep looking at this okay
oh
okay
so what if the whole Rock got
failed then we need to replicate another
copy right in another rack
right
so what if the name node got down what
is the name sorry the muscle no get down
then we need a secondary name known
right the secondary lame node secondary
name node is doing the Master Copy how
about the network performance okay it
tells you the network performance okay
keep bounding communication with single
rack so we think the information is
always faster and efficient do not go
over that if you go over higher and
higher layers it will be slow and slower
Okay so
let's look at this okay
so if we have a file name the
replication factor is three and then the
block ID is one two three so we are
going to have
we're going to like file one so file one
this has three replication factors the
block ID is one two three so you can see
that one two three is replicated in
three different nodes right three
different nodes so what is what if the
file two has the replication factor of
two then the block ID is four five six
so you can see that four five six four
five six so you see there's only two
replicas right two replicas
two copies of this file tool right if
the file 3 has the replication factor of
1 the block ID 7 8 then we can see seven
and it's there's no replica there's no
replica okay there's no replica
and the default replica the application
number for the hdfs is
is how much anyone's any student no
default default replication factor of
azure DFS is three it's three it's
trying to save one copy locally and then
one copy across the rack across the Rock
and the
one copy in
like nearby in in the same note in the
same or same physical rack
Okay so
so why do we why do we leave abstraction
blocks in addition to file the reasons
the files can be larger than a single
disk it's still the same question with
the Unicode file system right blocks of
the fixed side easy to managing and
manipulate easy to replica case and do
more fire grade load balance more file
grade no balance
so the hdfs inside so let's skip that
this is Art building okay let's look at
this question why does hdfs choose such
a design for read okay
oh he's asking it's basically the read
and write performance of the hdfs it
basically asks you the design philosophy
of the read read and write
what's the difference between read and
write
read and write
but why it will infect your system
design of the file system why do
infected system design of the file
system
yes
no no not references
well here's the thing okay one one we
are both real file we can read it
together right can we write the file
together
no right that's the difference is
synchronization
overhead is the difference we cannot
write a file together right but we can
read a file together right if we do not
change the files the file will not be in
the critical section but if we need to
write a file write that make changes to
it we need to put it in a critical
section we need to settle
synchronization
whatever you want to use
yes Andrew
very good how do you upload the copies
there's two approaches one approach is
passive approach another approach is
active approach active approach you are
going to theoretically check
theoretically do check the fire if the
file got dirty if it is it's going to
change it to the replica so that is
active approach even it's not no one is
changed it it's still
it's still make the call like check it
periodically for every file so the
passive approach is that owning the file
is going to change then the name nodes
know that right at the beginning the
name node we know the name node
the name node knows Aries in the mapping
of The Blocking right the name node
knows that someone is changing that file
then
it's going to synchronize the copy in
different locations for that file for
the replica of the file okay
okay so this is basically what we have
learned so um in our last course we are
going to finish the file the distributed
file systems and we are going to talk
about another concept very important
concept called system virtualization
we're talking about virtual machines
then virtual machines VMware virtual
machines and uh containers
serverless you may heard of that service
is very popular concept
and then the next week we are going to
do the uh do the review okay we are
going to I'm planning to do two review
sessions the first review is that I'm
going to present this the second session
will be like you will ask me the
questions and I give you the answers
okay so that's the plan
foreign