Google has already capturing and
recorded that I will not do I will not
upload my own version but since today's
course I have already recorded okay
so any questions oh and one final thing
about a waiting list I I do not handle
waiting this uh link also does not
handle waiting lists so we already
discourse this class is already full we
have no seat available
but if you are in the waiting list and
if the other students they decide to a
job this course you can be automatically
got in but that is out of my control so
I cannot give
any one priority saying that you can get
this special code something like that
yeah
yeah so uh
I cannot help yeah unfortunately because
we have very limited ta and the tutor
and reader and the class is already full
um
okay so uh so let's start today's course
so before we start today's course I want
to get a quick review about what we have
learned in our last lecture so I'm going
to ask you questions then you can raise
your hands and uh answer the question
it's all that we have learned in our
last lecture okay so what is operating
systems in our last lecture
that we talk about operating systems and
uh
especially I gave two keywords to
describe the operating system rule yes
it has very good abstraction and
Resource Management so can anyone
describe to us what is exactly an
abstraction
you again
yes very good very good okay and uh
Resource Management resource manager you
can take say to resource manager
yes
what
yeah very good that's my next question
yes so resource manager what is resource
manager resource manager is managing
resource so what is the resource
resource is the hardware right the
hardware the system has okay right now
if you are working on your laptop you
may not have that feeling but
long long time ago long time ago the os1
OS is designed
the computer is very expensive and we
call that computer is like high
performance servers we call it a server
and not only one user is using that
server many users users they have their
own program on it that is why we need a
resource manager and even for now you
are the own owner of your laptop let's
say that but you are not using one
program not running one program on top
of it okay
um
while you use your word you also listen
to the music the NPC right the music or
watch the Youtube then that is all
concurrent running program and resource
manager means that
the OS operating system needs to design
who got what kind of resource
so there's two type of sharings one is
time sharing and one is space sharing so
for memory
memory one multiple programs
are concurrently using the memory is it
time sharing or space sharing
it's face sharing yeah
how about printer
printer if
yeah printer is time right because you
cannot print two PDF at the same time it
will be messy right only one user can
use the printer at one time that is time
sharing so same thing a CPU is also time
sharing okay that is what we have
learned in our last uh first lecture and
another questions
okay so this is OS if we can see that
the OS is between the sitting between
the um
so hardware and the software okay the
software so OS has two mode the user
mode and the kernel moves right so
what's the differences between these two
nodes two modes
what are the differences what are the
difference
so and yeah
it comes
up I'm more familiar with the
that's a good question why they name it
like that Colonel mode
but we first needs to know why we need
to Define two modes kernel mode and user
mode why we need to Define that why we
need to distinguish these two modes
I set up
very good very good thank you yeah very
good so why we need kernel modes because
there's some operations we know OS is
managing its abstraction and resource
manager right it's actually for resource
manager always needs to design
who it has some special resources like
CPU memory this is a very special
resources and Os needs to design do a
very fair distribution of these
resources to multiple programs
you do not want any normal user to
change or ask this decision
so for example if there's no user mode
and the kernel mode everything is in one
mode and we say it user mode then I when
I write a program I can easily managing
the memory
I can allocate a lot of memory and a lot
of CPU time to my program
and then the other programs will not
have enough time
so think of that think of that
your parents is using using the experts
computer science experts and using your
laptop and he changing your OS he
especially changed at the limits the
time that you can play the games
whenever you play the games the CPU just
do not run link that's not running or
memory that's not allocating enough
resources
so from many special special
instructions
it's easy to understand right you do not
want to the normal user the average user
to change it then you put that in the
kernel mode so many many operations and
what we will learn in this course
they're all in the Chronos they're all
in the chronomous what you have learned
in other courses for example if you
learned in programming languages or the
um
algorithms machine learnings AI courses
the operations you did
only stands in the user mode okay
so what we are going to learn now is
that what kind of os provides to
managing the resources in a kernel mode
or hidden when we are talking about this
we especially talk about the
um
if you still remember we talk about the
data
pass transfers between different
components in the computer hardware
right
so I'll show you a question if
let's say I'm I'm
I just program our
very simple program okay A plus b one
plus two plus three so
I finished that
I'm going to save that in the disk
and then run it okay
okay anyone tells me the data pass
between these different components
this is something we learned in our last
lecture okay I will start from this
so let's say I'm using keyboards right
I'm using keyboards
I'm using keyboards to write some
programs okay it shows up in the monitor
right and then and then before I save it
before I say for it the program is in
them well memory right memory after I
save it this goes to the
disk and then I designed to combine and
run it so it goes to memory again and
that and then
CPU going to run it right so if you get
it from memory not from disk okay
whatever
in this picture learn this this is very
important okay CPU whatever you run
anything you run anything is always
loaded into memory first it's loaded
into the memory first and memory in
memory we have
um memory let's say memory 664 gigabytes
6 1 16 1 6 Cube 16 gigabytes right no
matter how large they are
no matter how large they are
since many multiple programs needs to
share the memory
and so each programs or gather special
space in the memory and we call it a
dress space or the dress space
so after the program is loaded in his
address space
the CPU can get it and run okay let's
review that again
okay
foreign
code right
and then
let's say the path to run this Java
program okay
owning the code the code itself
we call it a program we call the program
however when we executed it when it is
in our execution State then it become a
process but right now it is still a
program okay this is still a program
so this is the code and the first thing
what I'm going to do is that
I'm going to combine into some SQL
execution ball files right
let's say this so we come I'm going to
combine it
okay to this file
and then what's next how to run that
program
what's next
something I didn't talk in our last
lecture I'll describe it now okay
this program may be very large right
so
you are going to
divide it into many pieces
OS will help you do that okay how else
will help you do that
and then loaded the active
active only the active
piece only the active piece
this is the active
active piece
is maybe the entry of your program if
your program is very large it will be
the entry of your program into where
memory
so this is a memory
is using
memory memory is using space sharing
right we just learned that so here's why
it's called space sharing
you have this active pieces
so many programs are share the memory
together with this program so this
program can only get us a science space
and we call it the drive space
memories of the draft space we are going
to learn that in memory chapter but you
first need to get a view about what will
happen
so we loaded that the active pieces into
the address space of the memory
so any students know why we only loaded
the active spaces in address memory
I will give you a real life example any
students play
League of Legends
foreign
okay so this is a joke okay so so uh so
um League of Legends we know I am
um
yeah I'm a very low rank I've been
playing for nine years but I'm still in
the I think it's Aaron or bros you can
see it's a loyal one yeah I'm not a good
player but oh well this is a very large
program
um I think it's
um you know it takes like two gigabytes
in memory but when you actually loaded
that loaded that there's
um
how many champions this game has I think
it's around 146.
but when we start to run that games
the OS will not load every champion
in the memory
it will not load every champion in the
memory it will only load the champion
that you select okay the same thing the
same thing is that another game okay
pubg I think many of you guys heard of
that
um why you play that game so the game is
very interesting it's like 100 person in
a airplane right then they jump and then
well only one can survive and they jump
on a one big big city uh I think a lot
of City yeah but they only jump on one
space
so in that case
every this 100 person they all have
their own OS right they are os or only
loaded
their vision of the map in the memory
they were not load the whole map in the
memory that is the active pieces that
means active physics the active means
pieces means that when you when the OS
when you also the OS help you load and
start running the program
only the programs that you are currently
using the pieces you are currently using
is going to blow it into the memory why
because we know memory is very expensive
and many programs are concurrent using
memory so that is why they have a
concept of address space
okay
and then when we talk about that we talk
about another new Concepts we call the
paging right page
Os or divide the large memory into many
small Pages pages and then the active
pieces of the program will choose
several pages okay it can be there it
can be there
it can be anywhere it does not need to
need to be connected together it can be
anywhere
that is the OS job OS which job is to
distinguish this to distribute that
distribute that
okay after it's loaded into the memory
one next one next
so CPU have
CPU will have loaded the code into
a register
you learn that in your actual courses if
you have taken architectural courses
before
um
right there's a program counter register
right
it will it will point to
where it is right and another
register there's several rules of the
register they were they were they were
catch though
Stars
Starship dress and they will gather
the distances the jumps okay the jumps
and then CPU loading that code the first
line of the code loading into its
register
let's say CPU has three components any
student remember that we use the Burger
King example to describe that
three components so CPU got the code the
first line of the code is loaded into
its three components
yeah yeah very good very good so I think
it's uh encode decode and excuse right
you need to need to you need to gather
and the CPU
when CPU is X searching the code and
executing it it does not activate
seriously does not do it
one by one because it's very slow so
even CPU is going to load just one line
but it's going to be put this put this
in the first components and then fetch
the next and the one the first is goes
to the next components the next can do
the can go to the first components so
that is how CPU
analyzing this code so after this will
finish that
what what it will be then it will goes
back
together the second lines of the code
now it comes to another sharing approach
called time sharing so why we need time
sharing
so CPU
as the resource manager
it is unfair for him to just working on
these pieces of code of your program you
may while you for example when you do
the writing something in the office you
may also
watch some video so CPU needs to give
the time to another to another program
in another
memory address space
that is the time sharing okay so next
time okay let's say CPUs already spent
10 nanoseconds in your program active
program now CPU designed to
execute another program another program
so it's going to a switch
before cpu2 did this switch
follow me guys before I did the switch
CPU going to memorize something any
students know what is going to memorize
yes every process has its own address
space
every process will have its own address
phase
you have like every one of you have your
own apartment your apartment number is
your address space the same thing as the
process whenever it is active it's
running in the Os Os will give him their
own address space
yes
very good memorize it where it was in
that program and put it into their
register because there's another
register for that CPU I think CPU have
a lot registers okay then but that comes
to our next uh next concept so let's go
over it for this one okay that so CPU
are going to memorize it where it was
mine writes where it was and then switch
to the next put start the new address in
his program counter register
and then start running that and we call
this process
we call it there's a name of this
process
you should heard of that in yes
well here's the thing okay let me I'm
for uh describe it in more detail
so this is a memory right this is your
memory
the memory let's say is 60 gigabytes
so
it's a dress
okay sure
memory right
so how you define memory address just
from let's say it's just 16 and the
sixth one 16 gigabytes
it's maybe a very large large number
then that is the
address
in the memory okay whenever a process
whenever a process is loaded into the
memory os are going to OS is going to
give give her some memory address let's
say it's from is this is one to 200 then
the one to two hundred this
is the P let's say this process is
called P1 then this 1 to 200 is p once
foreign
space
okay we are going to learn that in uh
our
um memory chapter but let's go over it
okay so if you are going to memorize it
is a memory address yes
then that is P2 okay this is P2
okay so every process has a individual
address space
any more questions
if not then wait let's switch back to
this okay so CPU decides to do a time
sharing to come to a second process so
it's jump to a second process or just
phase and we call this we call this this
has this has a very famous name
you've heard of it yeah
one
it is happening right now I do not get a
question
one I cannot hear you can use
yes yes but maybe there will be many
process they all have their active
pieces they are loaded into the memory
they are sharing the memory yes
they will have different addresses
any active program record process every
process when it is loaded into the
memory it will have its own address
space that is why when you write up your
programs it gives you the error of
segmentation for it
you'll hold over that right then that
means you
do not use your
correct address space you are using
someone else
okay
any more questions
so let's let's uh let me
my question is that okay I'll give you
this question the CPU is going to change
let's say this is from P1 this is from
P2 now CPU spends 10 nanoseconds in P1
under the memorize p1's address space
savor it in his register and then loaded
the next code next code in the P2
decide to run this P2 so this process
the process of
switching from P1 to P2 we have a name
of that
what
no
no I mean
what is RPC
the Discord will have 300 Concepts okay
new Concepts IPC is one of the concepts
but do not mix them together ipcs into
process communication right in the
process communication right but this
they are not communicated with each
other in the process communication is
process communicates with another
process that is inter process
communication but here
CPU is switching decide to switching is
scheduling order from P1 to P2 and
memorize the states
the context of P1
then switch to the context of P2
you heard over there is called Contact
switch contact switch holds many times
but you may not understand the reason
that is the contact switch
okay that is the contact switch
so we always say that when you
um I do not know how many of you are
decides to
go to a master or PhD degree but when
you do that then essentially if you are
pursuing a system research
You're Building let's say you're
building a system like for us my lab
building stream processing system like
one hour after we build a stream
processing systems we need to measuring
its overhead overhead means that how
much resources take to run this program
to run our system in the one specific
metric is contact switch like how how
much contact switches crosses because if
if my program costs a lot of contact
switch
that means it has a lot of overhead to
the CPU
write the system or not stable
well think of that that is called a
contact switch okay
okay so this is the concepts of time
sharing and this is the address one
different process they share in the
memory is the called the space sharing
foreign
okay so let's come to a little further
okay
when CPU is
concurrency running different programs
like doing the decoding code and high
skills we call it pipeline
pipeline right CPU pipeline
pipeline I need students
pipeline what is exactly pipeline
so pipeline you uh
here you have the search decode and the
SQL to write fetch
let me show you using an example okay
so CPU pipeline
CPU pipeline okay
foreign
decode
so we when we are talking about pipeline
we use the real life for example of the
Burger King when you order the Burger
King you you pay the money and then you
summarize helping you prepare the food
like this right and then you get the
food
so in the same thing happens here if in
the OS we have multiple process
concurrency coming they join the system
right if
without pipeline what will happen
when P1 one CPU is fetching P1 it's
called
P2 and P3 are waiting here
and then
P1 finished fetching we finished fetch
fetching p1's code and we come to p1s
come to the encode operation right P2 is
still waiting
and then we come to the P1 comes to the
decode operation where then P2 is still
waiting is it good this is not good why
because it hurts the throughputs of the
system
CPU can do much more things than just
processing P1
so we call the pipeline what is pipeline
one
after
P1 goes to the second phrase in code
phrase P2 can join P2 can CPU can
fetching p2's code concurrently working
on P1 okay and one
P1 goes to the decode version P2 can
come to the encode version and P3 can
join the system so at one time this
throughputs will become three operations
per second okay three operations
per second
instead of one operation per second
that is pipeline why we need pipeline
because
because we want to improve the
throughputs of the system
foreign
so memory
after we talk about CPU pipeline we
talked something about pipe the memory
hierarchical structure any student
remember that
what is the first lever
in the hierarchical yeah
registers very good the second one
cash where is cash
oil is cash
we do not talk that in the um
where is cash
any other sort
very good very good so cash happens in
two places okay some very expensive
caches come goes to the CPU and some
caches is in the memory
so in our last lecture I I have asked
you a question about what is tlb you
still remember
yes
translation look Hazard buffer that is a
cache cue that is you can think of that
is a cache where it is
translation look outside buffer
tlb is still it's in a memory okay and
then what the third level of the memory
hierarchical structure oh it's there is
already a memory okay and then we have
the access Theory the SSD and the
a disk
the reason why we do not why we have
this hierarchical structure is because
we do not have
um because of it is expensive to keep
everything in the register and register
is very expensive or in the cash
okay so um main memory
yes
pipeline yeah what
oh yeah yeah it's sorry it's a fetch
decoder excuse
um no no we do not care about what the
architecture causes
um no well since the thing we are more
architecture attack chokes connected you
more with the hardware
no no no different textbooks have
different explanations okay that is why
I tell do not do not mime or do not just
memorize it try to understand it every
different textbook I have used several
textbooks for now every book have
different picture for this they have
different pictures they have different
names and even if you look at the OS
what is the OS running now the modern OS
they have maybe have more con units than
this okay but you understand the that is
just the first to understand the CPU
pipeline
mm-hmm
so memory okay let's come to this
I am is I am is what is I am
Random Access Memory very good so what's
the differences between the IAM and ROM
what we are using yeah
no no it's not that different okay when
I while we are using now
is I am or om
yeah
yeah I am we're using I am we call it
Ram right we call it Ram right we are
using IM okay
so what is the key feature of I am
everything
so I am the the memory will not help you
destroy the scenes if you turn off the
my turn off the machine you if it is
power of everything in the memory will
just disappear it's not like this
it's not like this everything you put in
the disk it will be there forever
and then we call it caches okay disk
okay so let's start from this
device driver what is device driver
what is device driver we used to have a
project I do not know if my tier going
to design these projects in this course
but I use her to
um I used to design projects for my
previous students is I asked them to um
to write our own driver
um so what is a device driver
let's have an intuition
intuition understanding the device
driver
any student device driver
so if you read the things it's not that
easy to understand it's not good to
memorize in this okay guys you need to
understand it what is exactly driver
well one of the book
anywhere
yeah but what it is I know this this is
yeah or you need give us an intuition
like a racial line behind why we need a
driver
user needs to give commands to the OS
but then why you need a driver you just
call that right you just talk to the
yeah
very good very good is another
abstraction so device driver device
driver let's say why we need this device
driver okay let me show you a picture
why we need a device driver
okay I'm a company I design my USB
how to draw USB
this is my USB okay
foreign
company a I'm designing a USB
this is my USB
as USB
okay I claim it I claim it
very very fast I climate very very fast
why it is very fast let me yeah
huh
what
to me
it's better
did let's say I'm a company I designed a
USB and then I claim it very fast why I
claim it very fast because when I design
my USB let's say I just use one layer
but you do not need to care about what
layer it is right from right now okay I
just use one one layer I put everything
there and I put a special file special
act special data structure to organize
these things okay let's see let's say
that I'm using
I'm using a data structure like
double array
to store everything just in one layer
and then I claim it I am very fast
the way that I you if you use my USB you
can accessing this this data very fast
because I'm using only one layer and now
using a
this kind of data structure to store the
data okay then another another company
another company and this company is
called b b's USB and Bill uses saying
that okay and maybe not the first one
when you search it but maybe not the
first one when you search it but I'm
definitely the best one when you read it
why
so it's like the this is the fastest
search
this is the first reading this is just
an example you do not need to memorize
it just an example to help you design
understand what is driver why really the
driver and then why not decide this
piece USB I'm not using the double array
architecture data structure I'm using
I'm using a bitmap
please build map okay and put everything
together they are connected to each
other
so you understand the differences
between these two data structures right
if this this data structure is good for
searching
right of course it's all and you can you
do not need but you do not need to put
everything The Continuous contents
together but in the build map you can
put everything together it's not the
best for searching because whenever you
search your account let's say you want
you put a movie into the USB if you want
to go to the 30 seconds of the movie you
have to go from the very beginning and
find out the 30 seconds
okay that is the best USB then what is
driver
without a driver without driver OS
without a driver OS needs to understand
every company strategy about their how
they're organizing their data
without driver
with this is the driver without the
driver then OS need to understand
whenever a new company designs USB OS
needs to
pushing updates to its current version
about to understand how its reads or
read or write the data and then
adding that it's all in in its OS
Resource Management code but with the
driver driver is that the A's company
and these company are going to create a
new abstraction
this obstruction separates abstraction a
code and
just exports to the OS about the read
and write wise it gave the OS of the
interface of read and write
and the driver do all the dirty things
about how to read data how to write data
how to search data
the driver going to help the OS design
the order Generations happening in this
to be accomplished in these two USBS
the OS only needs to getting this
interface okay so driver is actually
just um
abstraction it's another obstruction but
that is why we need driver
driver is not part of the OS
Lo not here
give me one seconds
uh so device driver is just another
abstraction
and its users abstraction
so user
doing Rider driver and then combined and
just you can ask the OS to load it load
that then after that OS can read
and write your devices okay and there's
three mode of communication so
communication means data transfer
communication between
the OS operating system under your
driver there's three kind of Opera
Communications what are these three
operations
they are pulling interrupts and dma so
we talk about dma in our last selection
what is dma
yes
DMI
so let's start from the first one
pulling okay pulling all these pulling
three modes of communication
before we go to these three concepts I
need I need you guys to not just
memorize it understand it okay I'm
asking you a question
um
if you are going to if if you are
students you need to you need to create
um Wells Fargo Bank
West Park Wells Fargo student card so
you come to the bank then what you can
do
what you can do
you need to CR you need you need to
apply for a card and then
you need to apply for card and then
deposit some a lot of money into that
like 10 000 into that you bring their
money okay and then you bring that money
you come to the you are already in front
of the bank the West Fargo bank so
there's several options the several
options the first option is that
the first option is that you are going
to
you you are going to
just come in come in the bank and then
you find out the different registers
right
you find there's different registers and
there's many people maybe ahead of you
so you are waiting there
so this is me okay this is me
it's me okay I have
100K okay and I need to store it now I'm
in I might have several options now I
come come to the bank okay this is the
bank
the difference of registers they are
like agents they are right and many
people may be ahead of me
then I'm going to wait here wait here I
choose a line I choose a line I'm
waiting here
I'm waiting here and then until it's my
turn it's my turn so it's if it is my
turn then I'm going to ask the guy
saying that okay you need help me apply
for a credit card
you need to help me apply for a credit
card I need to apply for credit card and
then the men are going to import asking
my name and whatever what I have then
he's already serving me he's only
serving me
until I have successfully deposited this
100K into the new credit card this is
one option
this is one option another option is
that another option is that
I come into the bank and then I'm I'm
saying hey I have 100K anyone who wants
to serve me and then there will be a
manager comes out he's from Office
saying that okay I can serve you letting
come here come to my office then let's
do that together that is another option
right
and the third option the third option is
that
I come into the bank coming to the bank
the manager serves me by manager saying
that okay
you you go to my room and you're fill in
this form one
you feeling this form I'm going to serve
another guy who has 10 000 K so you
waiting here you finish your form after
you finish that you call me then I come
back so that's the three options so this
happens in our real life it comes to
same thing
not this one
it's come to the same thing into three
modes of communications polling
interrupts and dma okay let's look at
exactly it's maybe not the same but the
concept is the similar concept is
similar okay let's look at how they
communicate
so IO by pulling the device device
issued command to the controller you can
think of that is a
part of the driver and then driver ports
the device until it is ready
for the device until it is ready
or what that means
so it's see
this is the same thing
same theme of my first example you're
waiting in a queue until you see your
term now it is your term
so the right the agents who's serving
you is the CPU and tell the agents I
have this data I need and you need to I
need to transfer data to you
so the agent is going to serve me
only serve me that is why it's called
Big use of CPU because CPU only served
this device the device
the driver you should come also
Controller driver post device until it
is ready
the CPU are going to monitoring the data
transfer one Base by one bits is going
to be there do nothing it's going to be
there do nothing okay
now another another
see this is the first one pouring okay
pulling you see this
this is a big waste of CPU big waste of
CPU another method is that IO by
interacts IO by interrupt
so what is IO by interrupt
what is the io by interrupt this is
something like my second administered
example okay saying that okay you come
into the bank
then you do not lead the wage agents
waiting for you on like when you are one
manager waiting for you while you are
filling your forms
you can say that hey I'm going to create
a I'm going to transfer data to you
so it sends an interrupt operation we
are going to talk about later what is
exactly interrupts but right now it only
needs to know that this drive the drive
this controller is going to interrupt
the CPU interrupt CPU saying that
hey you need to stop the work come to
serve me and then CPU comes to serve you
and then find out okay you need to
transfer data there's people saying that
I'll give you on CPU are going to give
me an address for me to transfer the
data then CPU can leave and do something
else
after I finish the data transfer I send
an interrupt again to the CPU saying I
finish so you come back
that is the io by interrupt I over
interrupt
so what is exactly interrupt
what happens once I when the OS handle
the interrupt
okay
so interrupts this right now I'm talking
about what is interrupts you may follow
that many times
what is exactly interrupts
interrupts
who do you interrupt right when we are
saying interrupts
the object of the interrupts is always
or as the CPU okay CPU okay we are
interrupting CPU so CPU is the one we
are interrupting why we need to
interrupt CPU
because at one time see if you can only
do one operation can only serve one
program why you need to interrupt the
CPU because you want the CPU to help you
to do something to do something so you
send the interrupt single to them there
are many kind of singers but interrupts
is one single okay in your project you
you're going to practice many other
singles so I'm going to interrupt CPU so
what happens when I'm interrupts the CPU
so this is a thing
interrupts can happen in many operations
for example I'm great in this example
okay I need to transfer data from my
devices to the disk I need to transform
the data from my USB to disk so I need
to send the interrupt operation
interrupt the operation to the OS so
this interrupts is from
this is an operation Operation okay this
is from user mode
normal
foreign
to jump from the user mode to Kernel
mode because in remember what I need to
do I need to transfer data from my
driver my USB right this is in
in my devices you can think of this is
in your user mode right this is your
devices your user mode but the disk or
memory when you transfer data from the
something USB to the disk and go to the
memory right this is something that OS
is managing
so that is in the kernel mode yes
yeah well here's the thing okay try to
try
to answer your question what is the
controller okay controller is slightly
different with the driver controller is
part of the OS it helps the inter in
interrupt into prints the operations
okay
here when you read when you learn all as
this course when you learn OS discourse
even what I hope that you guys can
understand the concepts not memorizing
these keywords right whenever you
understand it then you read the textbook
it's very easy so for example for this
controller
different textbooks have different names
they even do not require the controller
right so you want to tell you this is
controller you learn that but then when
you read that different textbook you may
it's different smellings they give
different names the same thing as the
CPU pipeline you you just need to
understand why we need pipeline the
benefits of pipeline but you there's no
need to understand why it is just three
components not four comparison or five
components because different textbooks
they have different explanations okay so
for this let's come back to this
interrupt okay why we need interrupt
because we need asked all as we need to
ask OS to give us some control of the
CPU time to help us do some
priority operation priority operation so
we need go from the user mode to the
kernel mode and array interrupts will go
from the user mode to the kernel mode so
for example right now I need to transfer
data from the USB to the disk so I need
to transfer from from the memory first
the memory is put transfer to the disk
so what it will do is that here this is
the
this is the your current instruction
your currency instruction this is the
next instruction
okay so the for the current instruction
you saying that help me create a file
how many creates a buffer then let me
send your data to the buffer so this
kind of operation is uh it should runs
in the kernel mode you cannot control
that this OS will help you control
because you are creating a buffer in the
memory so it is something you cannot do
you cannot do then it's asked it has a
interrupt to the kernel modes okay so
whatever who will reach that interrupts
there will be uh interrupt Handler
no matter what kind of
OS that you are learning there always
interrupts Handler that is a special
code for every kind of interrupt for
example if this is a crazy buffer this
interrupt they have an interrupts
Handler they have an ID and the OS will
find out the ID corresponding to this
operation and find out the interrupts
Handler to handle that interrupts
foreign
this is the code let's say we run this
code okay after OS runs this code in the
Chrome mode so it will go back to the
next operation okay next operation so
this is um interrupt this is an
interrupt this is the key idea of
interrupts so key
interrupts are very important in OS
okay I I have a question for you what
can you make an example about the
interrupt operations in your real life
real life example of the interrupt
operation
yes
foreign
no I'm asking
that's that's cool okay I'm asking what
is the interrupts operation in the
happening in the OS when you are
interacting with OS what are the
examples of interrupts
yes
what
keyboard
very good
others how about others
yeah
yeah yeah yeah okay okay so so here
interrupts has two kind of interrupts
Hardware interrupts and software will
interrupts so um that students What's
Your Name by the way
Andrew Andrew just gave us a good
example of Hardware interrupts so
there's many software interrupts
software interrupt when one example is
just what I mentioned that when you're
trying to need to like create a buffer
in memory let's say like do some
memory operations like allocation memory
rights address space that is an
interrupt that you it will cause an
interrupt what else
are all Hardware but what are the
software I'm curious yes
very good yes that was one I'm waiting
for throwing an exception this is also
interrupt what else
a silverware interrupt
yes
shut down it's it's a hardware
interrupts
software
it will open a file right this is a
interrupt it will cause interrupts why
because when you open a file what os1
needs to do it needs to
create a buffer some buffer in the
memory right
the OS need to manage his memory
resources
yes
break of what
break stem or that is in your
um
yeah that is kind of interrupt too yeah
well I mean all the Trap operations are
also kind of software inter software
well interrupts we are going to talk
about that later okay but you need to
hear the takeaway here that
interrupts means
the control the control or goes from the
user mode to the kernel mode
interrupts always happens
interrupts means that the operation
needs to jump from the user mode to the
kernel modes you give your control
control of your programs to the OS so if
we come back to the textbook textbook
example we see this is example about the
interrupts is that
in the taxable if I still remember
correctly in the castbook the textbook
they they give you the example of the
file operations it's saying that okay
you call the file you call the crazy
file then when you
one when the OS is running the create
file this language jumps to directly to
here then create file operation because
you need to
use the library right the library the
library is actually you may familiar
with Java or C plus plus or C but
there's a library right you are using
the file crease or something library
right but what actually happens in the
library is that they are calling the OS
Handler to help you create a file so
that it jumps to the OS code
when you create a file this operation is
exactly code does not run in your
program it's running in the Chrome mode
in the OS program so you are actually
using the interfaces that OS providing
to you remember that the first course
we're talking about OS is an abstraction
OS translates the ugly operations of the
hardware into some beautiful interfaces
that is the interfaces OS give to you
right so example of textbook for example
of the file crease and the file delete
is actually running inside of the OS
it's not running even you are like
import the Java Library where the C plus
library is it's not they are underlying
this Library code they are still using
the OS code yes
about using the using the using the ram
in your program that depends okay that's
depends that depends on what kind of
operations you are using
we can talk about that in our memory
chapter
and then this is the interrupt so still
we are talking about the i o
Communications between different devices
under the OS right we have the i o by
pouring IO by interrupt and IO by dma
now it's come to dma direct memory
access direct memory access oh
I know this I know it's it's kind of
burning because we kind of learn a lot
of concept but that is Os Os course is
like this okay always because it's like
just to tell explain to you every
concept it has okay so what is the
direct memory access
so what's the difference is between IO
interrupt IO by interrupts okay anyone
see it from the picture
what is that
so you see you see it's a voice using
the i o as past a CPU as the part of the
transfer
so it does not need to interrupt the CPU
and then interrupts view when it begins
and interrupts if you want finished does
not need to do that yes
um we are talking about that yeah the
well what is dma so you can think of dma
is a special CPU it's a special CPU not
not all the Hardware can support you dma
but if it can support you DMI means that
you either get this device needs to
transfer a lot of data so it has that
because dma when you start dma it's very
expensive it's deals a lot of overhead
but dma is like you can think of it is a
device a special a special Hardware
device that can that can replace the
lower of the CPU
so you do not need to interrupt the CPU
against if you can do everything they
want when the dma is replacing that dma
is doing that
it helps connecting the devices to the
memory
okay
and that is the only exception when you
transfer data I do not need to interrupt
the CM CPU okay
so in real life it is like you I need to
deposit ten thousand dollars into my in
into my my credit card right I I do not
need for bordering the agents I do not
need to bothering the manager I do not
need to ask them to wait for me or
interrupt them and ask them to serve
anyone else I do not need to interact
with them I just do it online I create
um crazy accounts and deposits online I
do that I
just yeah that is like the amazing it's
very but it's very expensive okay it's
very expensive it's if you just have a
little part of data a few data you're
using the i o by pulling or using the io
by interrupt
this is very
very slow but it's very
it's very slow but it costs very little
overhead this is slightly fast but you
need and it's cost always ask the
pouring wall with us view to wait
interrupt CPU can do something else
dma CPU
do not need to be interrupted CPU can do
his own things okay that's uh that's a
differences between different these
three approaches
now we're talking about in the in our
last
in we also talk a little about the
process so today let's talk more about
that so you still remember process is a
running program right so a process is a
running program
so if you are you are the ois designer
now you need to code on OS what kind of
data structures you are going to provide
for process
let's say I create a object across a
class for the process right and what I'm
going to put into that
yesterday we mentioned that
yes
yeah very good you remember I just face
yes what else
person's name right process ID right
the owner of the process right decrease
time right
the group ID right so what is group
what is a group why the processor needs
to group so these come the concepts of
the process tree
process can create one or more other
processes we call it child process
okay and the process trees looks like
that
so how they process
communicates with each other
how they communicate with each other
there's a word
yeah
yeah that is the IPC yeah that is the
IPC so
um
the communication is called interprocess
communication
yeah what lights
okay another file we're talking about
fire a major function of the operating
system is to
um
it's to give the abstraction of the disk
and other i o devices and present the
programmer with a nice curling abstract
model of the device independent files
so so when I loaded that into the you
see you have a USB you plug in
they gave you a vision you can directly
click that right and then go to the USB
right same as your disk right your disk
is actually there are all files there
are files
right if you are familiar with Ubuntu so
um they are loot file or also loot file
and then there there is a I think it's
called Etc fire and then device file
right and then home user
this is all files so so the OS as long
as it is a storage devices or as going
to translate it into a file as long as
it is a storage devices remember that as
long as it is a storage devices it are
going to translate to the new
obstruction called file and then
files
are stored in the file folders right
this file folder is called a directory
directory is actually also a file it's a
special file but if you look at the OS
code the directory and the file they use
the same code they use the game same
code they are actually very similar this
is just a special file and the file
file
okay there's uh something is very
interesting I didn't put that in
mentioned we mentioned that the pipe
right so if if pipe is we can single
pipe is a special file it helps the
process to communicate with each other
but it's not IPC okay they're using
different they're using different
abstractions but five pipe pipe is a
file so it's using the file obstruction
to help process communicate with each
other
foreign
we come to the system course Okay so
so we have seen that
operating system have four are two main
functions providing abstraction to user
programs and managing the computer's
resources so for the most of the part
the interaction between user program and
operating system deal with the
abstraction like creating file reading
file deleting on fire
creating a buffer deleting a buffer so
the resource management part is
it's transparent to the user and then
automatically
so how they do it how they do it so
there's a
there's a few words here is called we
between the act with OS we need a core
and this is a system core okay system
code so making a system course like
making a special kind of procedure core
or in the system core enter into the
kernel okay Enter to the kernel so that
says very very similar to the interrupts
very very similar to the interrupt just
interrupts has two system core
interrupts has two kind right the
hardware Interruption software
interrupts right so system core is like
very similar to the software interrupts
it's called it's part of the software
interrupts so we clear about that is
part of the software interrupts so it
also needs to
jump from the username mode to the
kernel modes okay
so what happens in the system core
so the system core issues by the user
program we use a library called okay for
this is an example about the this is
just a software interrupt okay I'm like
I'm creating a file I'm creating a file
file creates this operation is issued by
my user program and then the library
routing puts them put into the kernel
modes by issuing a special instruction
and find the actual loading to the
system in a table there's a system
called handling table and then
run the system core then return the
program
so this is an example okay then let's
look at this so this is your users user
score right now
you see that
I'm creating let's say I'm read the file
right this um this is the
file descriptor right
this is what is that
yeah
yes very good very good so the amounts
of the bytes okay amount of guys you put
put in the buffer and so we read that
and this is the file descriptor okay so
read it then what you're going to do
when you actually run this operation
when you actually run this operation you
call the read right let's say this
letter form from this
we push we push what is push means
what does push means
see here
very good and then this
still push it in the stacker then push
it stack then what we do we call
recorder read operation right
put code for reading register and then
here this is very important trap to the
kernel right because this reader
operation this read operation will not
the user cannot handle that it is some
special operation user cannot handle
that so starting
starting from here
starting from here we trap to the CR to
the kernel
and then find out the system core
Handler
to handle it
that is you see this operation is very
similar to interrupts right that is why
I say system core is just a
special case of the software interrupt
so there's many see some cool examples
like for cooperation weight PID wait for
child
process to terminate
replace a process core images
open close read write files
so we are going to we are going to
practice that in your project or this
system course when you when we are
learning come to the process uh
chapter we are going to learn that I
think you very soon you will got your
first assignments so two I think it's a
write-on assignments and then the
projects assignment your first Project's
assignments will be help you familiar
with C uh warm up with C okay
so linking
okay let's let's skip that so operating
system structure
operating system structure
this is the history of operating system
um which costs like 10 pages in the in
the model brain system textbook I'm the
reviewer I review this book twice I mean
I was invited to review this book when
the books was designed so um because I I
use that book for many of my courses and
then uh I found out they changed they
may change it a little bit
um so
operating system history is it stands
for a very very long history
um
at the very beginning we
we do not have this big OS we we call it
Michael kernels this will be uh
before you were born yeah definitely
before you were born I think when I
learned that I think you are more most
about 20 right yeah it's when I come to
the college what I learned at that time
the osdf papers there there's a paper
about Michael kernel what they did is
that they tried to remove everything
from the kernel modes they asked the
user to do the resource management they
asked the user to do the abstraction
they just put very very tiny things in
the kernels so and we call it Michael
kernels
recording Michael kernels but it's it's
it's the good thing about that the good
thing about that
where if you put if you write a lot of
code
it was easy to have bugs right and
whenever you do a new operation you need
to change your noise so the reason why
they do Michael kernel is that they
found out that okay I just write this
this tiny tiny course just maybe
thousands of lines of code to to
managing the hardware resources and gave
a lot of
access to the hardware to users then I
find out that it's easy to minimizing
the uh to minimize the the Box
okay but then
then and then per day they found out
that it's like a printer it's like your
printer but it's only to the print since
you don't not do anything else and then
the operating system become larger and
larger and then right now the operating
system is more like um
trying to get everything inside try to
get everything inside so it's more like
a
printer machine where you can do the tax
faxing it can do a phone call you can do
it can save a lot of documents can go
through everything together
that is what we have now but
well
operating system now is come to a new
new age that we we are not focusing on
the old as itself so we are going to
talk during our hot topics at the end of
this course we have one week for Hot
Topic so I'm going to discuss with you
what happening very hard in the OS for
example virtual machines that you may
familiar with the virtual machines right
containers
right and the serverless serverless
functions
for example right now if you you you you
I don't know if you are familiar with
Amazon ec2 but everyone can using your
Amazon account to create a free tiny
virtual machine in the Amazon
um and you that is a little virtual
machine so when you log in you can feel
that it's the same as your the real
Merchant but they are virtual okay so
well that is what we are going to learn
in in the last of the course so well
here's the takeaways
and uh
um so my tier are going to
publish your assignments and your
projects soon you first um you know you
have uh
yeah you have I think you have one or
two weeks to finish that okay okay thank
you