to demonstrate that your call is the
same as the other students or from the
internet but it does not mean does not
mean you are safe some students who got
like
maybe problems a little bit like have
some similar code like 50 percentage 60
percentage or 30 percentage then these
students ta will Mark a warring around
the name but we will not tell you who
they are so we will check
at the
um when the class ends I'm going to take
a look at all together of everyone's
code
but in any case if you receive a zero
grade now that means you your code is
exactly the same as
another students or some students in the
class so that is unacceptable
okay
so do not try to do that you you you are
learning this course because you want to
learn something okay not just got a
great
okay so problem includes boring codes or
reports from someone
reading previous solution giving code or
reports to someone okay this is very
important
you may develop your call by yourself
you write your call by yourself however
you
you give your code to someone else in
the class you or automatically got zero
two and you fail
Okay so yeah protect your code okay
so give give codes or reports to someone
else
calling code reports from anyone
including from the internet helping
someone to write your code
or your reports submitting someone else
code or reports as your own and looking
at anyone else code or reports okay
so we are computer science students we
know that it's very real it's very real
that your code is the same as the other
scope well by the same I mean sometimes
you may just change the valuable name
but it's very easy to to to figure it
out right so um
so you can discuss with your classmates
you can discuss it with your with the
tutor with the TA you can ask for their
help but do not
give the code or copy the code from
anyone in in a class
okay so that's the honor code
so um if you have any questions for your
grades so feel free to
um
to ask my TA or my ta is Sean shun
so this is our RTA
okay
so this is about the honor code
um
and today as we discussed I'm going to
um we are going to have a review of our
midterm
our midterm and uh you will get your
grades very soon in the um
so for the first part of the class I'm
going to discuss the solutions with you
about our midterm okay then the next
part we are going to learn the file
system
too
what
that's
one problem
[Music]
uh okay so we are going to
um
have a review about our midterm and also
we can have a review about what we have
learned so far
let's start with the true false
questions okay
yeah
no
no no we are not going to release that
but you all got your grade
oh you're good
um
you you got I think they when they're
grading they will tell you
whether you are correct or not
but I cannot distribute stats in the
cameras because
they will give you the grading criteria
yeah something like that they will tell
you why you you didn't get a point
something like that okay so feel free to
ask me questions but I cannot distribute
stats on the canvas because it will be
or distributed to the next year or next
year okay
okay
it's larger
so it's starting from this the operating
system is not responsible for resource
allocation between computing
processes that's fourth right so we know
the
um
so there are two rules of operating
system means abstraction and resource
Management's rise on in the resource
management results or location it's an
important part of the resource
management
besides resource allocation resources
scheduling it means scheduling algorithm
page replacement algorithms swapping
algorithms
they all belonging to the resourcement
resource management okay
because of force
I interrupt table contains address of
the handlers for the for the various
interrupts
so we're talking about that right
in one of the slides we show that how
the OS handled interrupts right so um
for every interrupt Irene wrapped they
actually send a single to the CPU so the
for example the
um I think the many singles they have
many integers different integers and
each integer responds to a corresponding
interrupts table and it tells you how to
handle the handle difference single so
for example some single is just the
exception something else is like
are
um
drawing another process there are many
different singles okay and uh okay now
dma so dma is director memory access
right it's a mechanism for allowing
and IO devices to transfer data to and
from memory without involving CPU in the
transfer so we talk about that
in the in our introduction it's about
the three three type of food three type
of communication
for the data transfer so if you still
remember what are the three type of
communication there's IO by poding right
it's by after bytes very very slow bite
of the bytes very very slow and another
approach is
is IO by interrupts right so you send
the interrupt to the CPU say hey I need
to do the i o I need to do the transfer
and then the CPU say okay you do you do
your job it will give you back a Handler
and the handle help you to do the data
transfer after we finish you send
another interrupt to the CPU saying that
oh I'm finished that is IO by interrupt
it's faster it's much faster than i o by
pouring however it's still not quite
efficient if you transfer if you want to
transfer a large amount of data between
the CPU and IO resources so there's a
approach called dma directed memory
access it's going to build a channel
between the CPU and the disk so sorry
memory and the disk so without the inter
without the involving the CPU inner
control we can do a very fast transfer
from the memory to the disk so that is
dma so it's true
the next
each thread of a process has its own
and virtual address space so anyone know
why it's of what
oh what
I say again
I didn't get that yeah
so each each thread of a process so each
thread
if the Surah several threats belonging
to the same process they will not have
their own virtual address space they are
going to they're going to share in that
that is why we say that threats does not
need to do threads belonging to the same
process does not need to do compact
switch because they have the same
virtual address
right
so but if different threats belonging to
different process they will have their
own virtual address space
but if they belonging to the same
process they will not have their own
virtual address space
that's the difference so maybe in the in
the final I would say like
like a threads of two process have its
own virtual have their own virtual
address space then
that is true in that case it is true
okay and then another one
an advantage of implementing stress in
user space is that they do not incur
overhead of having the OS schedule their
execution
that's just three or the context the
differences between the differences
between stress and process right why we
say that contact switch between the our
threads is more is very lightweight
when the CPU is in kernel mode the CPU
is prevented from accessing areas of the
memory that are not owned by the current
process
why why is force
why is the force
yes very good very good if it is in user
mode then it is memory restricted you
you are not going to allow to access the
memory outside outside of your own
address
of your own process but if it's in
kernel mode that means os are going to
take the control of the resource
allocation so OS can gather get memory
anywhere
that is the why we need the two modes
the chronomous and the user mode because
we want to protect the protect the
restricted resources right
okay so here in round Robin's Gathering
it is advantageous to give each i o
bounce process along Quantum then each
of the CPU bounds process
wise Force
yeah
no oh sorry
no I'm sorry you raised the head
in round robin schedule yes
so what is the definition of the of the
wrong Robin what the definition of the
wrong Robin
definition
yes
this is not round robin with the
priority this is wrong Robin
if if it is that there's a priority with
the wrong Robin that may be a different
thought
think of that if it is wrong Robin we
remember that John Robin spew just sets
the same compound okay same content to
every process every process
right
now let's see let's see one is why it is
better to give IO bound process a longer
quarter than the CPU bound process
like which one should get if it is wrong
Robin with the priority queue if it is
the wrong Robin you remember like we
when we talking about the CPU scheduling
algorithm we're talking about several
algorithms right the
um
first thing in first out right
and the shortest job first the shorter
remaining job first round robin
priority queue with the round robin
and the lottery
right in so if it is wrong Robin if it's
only wrong Robin that means that
everyone got the same column everyone
got the same column but in the case if
it is the priority if it is a priority
queue with the wrong Robin and the
priority if the priority is is given the
i o bounce process then the i o bound
process can get more cotton
if it is given if the priority is given
to the CPU bound process then CPU bound
forces get more cotton
okay so the the the the
Trap here is the wrong Robin's Gathering
okay let's look at this
if unbatched jobs are scheduled use the
shortest job first schedule and shortage
job the total time it takes to execute
the end process is less than using any
other batch schedule assuming no two
jobs take the
take the same time
or is the force
well and you still remember the shortest
job first Gathering what is the shortest
job versus Gathering
shorten the job first should his job
versus Gathering that is that we
unbatched Jobs means that let's say the
batch jobs come arrive at the same time
right at the same time and then we find
out which one has the shortest
job which one is the shortest job so we
put this first we put the shorten the
job first
right
then the total time what is the total
time
so we have like say a yeah
the total time is not the total time is
the total I will ask you is in say is a
let's say a
B
C
so when we execute stats then what is
the total time to excuse them then we so
they'll if their job if their job
time is a smaller than b is more than C
smaller than D then what we are going to
executing is that a first isn't B then C
then D and then the total time is a
right so
but is the the widest Force white is
force
Force means that there's approach who
has
who has
smaller total time than this
we're talking about several algorithms
right
so which one may have smaller time
still the approach called one just
searches the job remaining
time right
that will be faster why because it will
keep keep tracking the other their
remaining time
this is the total term wrong time and
then if we might divide 4 into the
average term wrong card
no no no the total time it takes to
execute
to execute the end process the total
time it takes to execute the end process
so you want to actually let's say the
full process what is the total time to
excuse them
you'll need to actually a first right
while a is executing
then B needs to raise a to be finished
all right then so that's why
how much time to execute B is a plus b
right
yeah Andrew
it's actually the oh okay I will check
the take a look at the textbook but
there's another another approach called
the shortest job remaining time right
remaining
yeah it's preemptive yeah yeah
preemptive version okay
let's see this okay if a system has a
small turnaround time the time between
submission and combination then it
usually means that this system has a
larger throughput so we talk about that
we talk about that exactly the same
question in the class right
we talk about that
this is a force right this is force
right
this is force four circles
this this is fun
um so that's the text mode says that the
shortest job remaining
first
the preemptive portion of the shortest
job first so there's another algorithm
we talk about discuss the shortest job
first the algorithm and the shortest job
short to the remaining job first
yeah
and then this okay if a system has a
smaller we talk about that right that is
the that is same question as asking you
oh a small sentencing means a larger
throughputs that's the same question
right we using the example about the IL
Playing Airplane is very fast it's a
super small airplane but it's very fast
so it has a small town runtime but
throughput the L plane Can Only Hold one
person this throughput is very
it's very small or for a very big
airport very big airport it takes like
double of the time but it takes like 300
percent then the throughput is larger
so
it's actually asking the same question
as the latency and the throughputs
right the relationship between London
okay so let's say this dialogue can
never occur if no process is allowed to
hold the resource while requesting
another resource that's ask you the
definition of the deadlock right you
remember the definition uh sorry the um
for dialogue to happen there's four
conditions right you still remember any
students still remember not just you
want to find
what about
that conditions for a deadlock is mutual
uh exclusion yeah
exclusion can never occur because uh
because one process can take something
from another process while while it's
holding and at that point you lose
neutral exclusion which means no
deadlines
yeah uh
freedom
preemption
and mutual exclusion right full
condition so it's basically asking you
this is low process is allowed to hold
the resource while requesting another
request
it's asking like if one of those
circumstances it's not
satisfied then their look never occurred
as a true okay so let's look at this
okay a single choice questions okay
oh this is CMC
so that's the four conditions right so
it's a c right it should be long
preemption right it should be
non-preemption
so and which of the statements is true
which of the statement is true
but larger
statement is true
we talk about that right okay let's talk
about that a model switch processes with
process a contact switch
we talk about that as a sailor is not
here the Sailor specially we ask this
question twice in the class
in the yeah
so we talk about that why why why
are most which processor contact switch
so to do contact switch you need to go
into the kernel mode then you can do the
contact switch so both switch always
proceeds a contact switch
you cannot do contact switch in the user
mode like contact switch means the CPU
is going to scheduling from one process
to another process so it's involved for
a lot of
restricted operations that has to happen
in the kernel mode
so
then that means we need to go to the
kernel first to do a contact switch
okay let's do this oh
a computer has turned tape drives
which unprocesses Computing for them
each processor needs up to two drives we
discussed that right we discussed the
exactly same question okay so we are not
going to discuss it again
one needs to be saved and stored on a
contact switch between two threads in
the same process
we need to save all of this we talk
about that we talk about that in our
review session with data okay to do a
contact switch what we are going to do
you need to
save the status right the the program
counter means that the
it's a register right program counter is
a register
stack pointer is also a register it's
also saving a register process or
registers it's actually these two are
belonging to process registers so it's
actually everything everything
these two are two specific registers
there may be like some e like the
instruction register IR right there's
many registers
so when we do a contact switch
we need to save that but why connect
switch in the threads are more
lightweight because in the if we do
contact switch for the stress we don't
need to the same process
they share the same virtual address
space
so that is much easier okay
which of foreign is true of a blocking
system
Co-op
broken system called let's see
the application continue to execute this
code One Core is issued
a blocking system console is asking you
the definition of the system core
so the application continue to execute
the code when the code is issued it is
forced right
you remember the other workflow is um
in some slides in our in our
introduction
I forgot the size that slice number but
it's it's in some page nine ten so like
it shows you how to do the system core
we also review that in our midterm
review session so when we handle our
system core
the application gives the control
to the OS then OS
got a trap operation to the kernel
hundred handled system course the
application will not continue to execute
the application continue executes after
the call is issued and returned back
remember that they also there is a trap
there's a trap operation you look at the
slides we have the picture about that
the second the core returns immediately
without waiting for Io to complete
that's that's false right
you need to wait in the core okay you
need to wait in the i o to complete then
return it the accusation of the
application is suspended when the call
is issued that's true right the
application
we we for example we open a file we open
a file
before we open a file the application is
run the process is run then when we say
the program counter points to the open
the file the open operation then it's
going to have a trap operation to the
kernel from the user to the kernel modes
and the kernel find out the Handler
corresponding to that
like to that Library System core and
using uh
the system called Handler to handle that
so after it handle finish the code open
operation open the file it may issues a
page Force get a page from the disk and
put it to the memory Creator memory
are creates a memory space for that
application and then return the control
to the application in the user mode so
the execution of the application is
suspended when the call is issued
blocking application code is harder to
understand
the long broken
application code is harder to understand
the noun
okay that's that's false
so let's do this oh this is something a
little tricky how many of you guys see
how many of you guys see if you follow
the formula you are gonna see right if
you follow the formula it's gonna see by
the crush on the is
great great then Andrew can you explain
why it is the
for the formula is asking the CPU
utilization right it asks you the CPU
utilization then here the question
answer question asks you
what fraction of the CPU time is wasted
it asks you what fraction of the CPU
time is wasted it does not ask you the
CPU utilization so you need to
distinguish between CPU visualization
and the CPU idle time so if the CPU
utilization is 19 percentage then that
means the CPU
10 percentage of the CPU time is wasted
so do not hardly memorize the formula
try to understand that then you can get
a correct answer okay the formula is
asking you
the CPU utilization means like which
fraction the CPU is used but here it
asks you what fraction of the CPU is
wasted is idle
right
all right okay so this this one we we
discussed that right we
so the event is not that difficult
because we discussed so many
questions already in the lecture so how
many philosophies may eat simultaneously
in the dining philosophy program with
seven philosophies
um
we have like so so it's you can write a
picture and then it can give you okay
okay this one this one this one is
tricky this one is tricky
so onion students know how to do this
one this one is tricky this is maybe the
hardest step
part in this
so you want to spend some time to do
that
you don't remember remember
yes
yeah yeah it's very good very good he
gives us an intuition how to solve this
problem you need to you well we we take
a look at this and see whether it is the
first thing first serve what is shortage
job what is around Robin and what is so
we can use some
the removing the solution removing the
incorrect solution first then the last
one is the correct solution yeah
yes yes very good so why just run around
Robin we can see that it's not running
the same time right it's not running the
same time so it's definitely not round
robin right so round robin would say the
same column the same column always the
same pattern now we see oh
whether it is uh first thing versus
first serve it's not service first thing
first serve or what is first thing for
service not right because you see this
is God
this is not finished all right it's not
finished it's not finished
right
now weather is the shortest job first
why it is not the shortest job first
then we need to look at this okay assume
a process P0 needs five Circle to
terminate and uh requests on iO three
circles P0 okay and there's another
process py in the same radical in the
same radical so they are arriving you
can see they are arriving almost at the
same time they are in the same radical
so if they are in the same graphic queue
then the CPU needs to figure out okay
who got it first and it's only requires
five CPU Cycles to terminate so if we
can see this timeline for p what P0 and
P1 you know if P0 and P1 so if it is
first circum versus serve then we
definitely need to finish P0 P0
um P0 first and then P1 right and
let's say if the shortest job so why why
it has not shot his job first let's see
about more Cycles than that and it's
switching to that
yes yes yes yes very good so it's
already uh very tricky here okay so for
this question we need to why we just
look at this we look at this through to
removing the incorrect answers okay so
let's
which of the following is most likely to
be a system call
the implementation of a while loop in C
that is not a system core right that is
a user user in the user in the user mode
parser token from a stream is just uh
it's it's not a system core right gather
this is this is a mass Library this is a
tax
processing library right the
implementation of all right Loop in C so
you can see this if you can see why when
it when it become a system core that
means you need to have those kernel
modes to process there then that is the
system core so if you look at this
gather time of the day
we actually discussed that like but I'm
not using the same term I'm saying like
can we change the clock in our laptop we
cannot change that so that's the same
thing as The Gather time of the day you
cannot
since you cannot change the clock of the
timing right in the computer you cannot
change that same thing the time the
timer the timer the uh of your computer
is is controlled by the by this by the
OS but OS it's a resource it's a
resource it's controlled by the OS
discussion in a review session I ask you
like can we change the
clock of the of the of your laptop we
sell node right that's the
so this is a system so regarding the
differences between preemptive and
non-preemptive schedule which is true
pre and pre preemptive non-line
preemptive Gathering which one is true
of the buff right
of the buff right so it's actually the
playing preemption scheduling preemption
allows the process to be interrupt in
the Middle East of its execution
non-preemptive scheduling shoulder
process
give the control
of the CPU only minds finished with its
current CPU first
there's another short answer she answers
were very
easy it's come from your homework so if
you do your homework you should be good
or from your homework
so name three ways in the process can
transition from user mode to Kernel mode
I will be very nice for this question so
if you
if you just make three examples it
should be fine you should get a grades
okay
but here this is the example solution
let's see so this one this one what's
the differences between dialogue and the
starvation
actually mentioned that in a client of
the lectures that are the dialogue and
starvation in a dialogue situation
nonflow involved process can possibly
make progress in a starvation situation
process is ready to ask you but it's not
being allowed to execute so dialogue in
the dialogue situation it means that
it's going to be
um
you need to you need to you need also to
answer this question correctly you need
to give the definition about what is the
dialog and what is starvation and the
difference is that that in the
starvation situation process is ready to
ask you it's ready to execute
so it's ready to argue but insteadlock
situation it's not because it does not
have the resources that it wants it's
not in the ready it's not in the very
status
okay and then what is the contact switch
what is the contact switch
well I will give you a hint okay
the midterm questions May repeat in the
final so in the final we are going to be
cumulative we are going to be cumulative
so
um
so try to pay attention to that okay
what is contact switch transforming
control from one process to other
process so if if you if I want you if
I'm not going to
um if I feel difficult to answer this
what is context video I can actually
find a solution in this
right you can find some Solutions in a
in in enough true force or the multiple
choice questions there are there are
some definition about the context switch
okay so it's transferring control from
one process to another request same in
the state of the pro our process and
loading the safer States from new
process so we are going to save all the
process registers from the old process
and load the saved States saved projects
process registers value
what is the meal tax your taxes are
locked it's a program object that allows
multiple
programs right to share the same
resource such as file sets but not
simultaneously so someone is an integer
a valuable data apart from
initialization
is to standard atomic operations down
and up
we have that solution in the uh in the
slides right okay so let's look at this
oh I should not give you this okay
is true or false this one
true or first
what where's my out there most operating
systems are designed for general purpose
computation a proposal has been put
forth for OS that is optimized for
running Mass intensive programs in Mass
OS so someone is proposing Mass OS it's
like your
Apple OS
the kernel includes the system core from
many useful mathematical operations such
as metrics
like this audience like Eed or maybe
that's all functions this system called
writing in highly optimized assembling
language for maximum performance is this
concept for mass or I think it's a good
idea
is it a good idea Andrew
this is a for
um easy right
what's your name
Madre who is easy
it's very good so yeah let's combined to
students are answers so you think of the
OS why we need the OS the OS the common
parts of the OS is in the kernel modes
right so basically It'll ask you that we
put the mass operations in the kernel we
put some math operations in the kernel
that's not a good idea because you're
going well what the kernel the job of
the kernel is to do the
obstruction and the resource management
especially to protect the important
Hardware resources so that's why when we
say kernel operation is almost relating
to
resource like the memory resource like
paging right page Replacements or the
process process scheduling almost every
kernel operation is relating to an
important resource of the or of the
system like the hardware like the uh
when we learn file system we will select
open Creator file this relating to the
disk a disk obstruction the block
address
so almost every kernel operation is
relating to a hardware the mathematics
does not relating to any hardware right
so it's very inefficient okay well not
bad if it's running they do not need a
privileged instructions or special
facilities you can say the special
Hardwares okay
it does not need privileged instructions
it also does not need any special
facilities like special Hardware you can
do around anything with just using
the common resource
okay so the answer is no okay the answer
is no let's look at this oh okay at the
beginning of it I downloaded so I think
there's a type of
so at the beginning of calling the
lockdown I download 100 megabytes of
large directory of high resolution Zoom
background image from the University
website and add it to the zoom clients
on my computer computer now whenever I
open the settings tab in the zoom and
try to go to the virtual background tab
where approval of the old image will be
shown my zoom clients appear to
store hunts there and the UI becomes
unresponsible for almost half minutes
before the image finally appear in the
UI this very alarming situation
situation be thinking about
make me thinking of making me makes me
that's a typo thinking about the process
States so while the zoom clients is long
unresponsible word process States is
most likely
justify your high persist so it's very
important you need to justify that
any student think they're running
so it's like the client the zoom client
so basically it's asking okay
I open a zoom clients but I couldn't
open this like in a lot it's like hands
there hunts there forever
non-responsible so what process this is
the zoom most likely in
running ready or blocked
and you need to justify your answer
yes
you think it's blocked okay so how to
justify that why it's blocked
it's not it's not any of this is working
then a system caller you have to go to
IO to get that file and
that that I O call will put like we'll
put that we'll put the process into
velocity so how to justify your
hypothesis hypothesis so sync is a block
but it's all from your assumption right
how you justify that how can you find
out whether it's blocked state or not
yeah
while I haven't heard a better answer
for this I wrote that it's task manager
just or just use task manager it should
tell you
very good use pasta manager in the task
manager you can see what the CPU
utilization right in the task manager
you can see ccpu utilization so if it is
a running stage you are going to see a
CPU utilize anyone thinks it's a running
state
if it's a block stage we will see a CPU
utilization of
Magic
very good if in the block States then
that means the zoom is waiting for your
i o input so we say that we download a
very big image right it may needs to
gather image it's doing some IO job and
then so to prove that I'm correct using
block stage I click I open the task
manager and to see check that if I see a
loan supervisation then that means it's
block sticks but it may can it can also
in a
running space right now also in running
States
right it's so it's most likely in the
running stage in learning stage I would
rarely find that by just looking at the
superiorization if in the running state
so I would check the answers like this
if you say running stage you say the CPU
utilization is 100 percentage you check
the CPU utilization you do not need to
say you open the task manager there's
many tools that can help you look at the
CPU utilization but you need to mention
that that is how you justify your answer
okay if it's in the block States if in
the block States then that is trying to
get some you waiting on UI inputs right
contact the remote server with a very
low process time response time okay so
that is how we uh how we how we um
how we justify that okay
let's look at this next another
oh we got this right
so we do not need to repeat that right
we already discarded in our class right
we we do not need to repeat that so
okay the coding versions okay coding
questions
okay for sample solution so you take a
look at that
um
well the thing is that for the midterm
if we look at the tips what you can
learn from midterm if you do not perform
well in the midterm that's okay no need
to vary we are going to curve the grades
if you do not perform well
others may not perform well too so we
are going to curve that and but I'm I'm
going to after I got all the grades I'm
going to tell you what's the average
um it's medium what the medium what's
the standard deviation
um yeah I'm not allowed to to tell you
the uh the worst grades but I can tell
you the best grades in class that sounds
fair so you can have a
understanding about where you may stand
in class
okay
and uh
um what else yeah in the final we are
going to have
accumulative so it's going to cover
everything cover everything it will be
the same style same the true false
questions
single choice questions and there are
short answers with some
short answers so it should answers it
should be very easy to prepare or you
just need to go over your homework
because our homework will have many uh
ask you many definitions of the OS so
your short answers
so is that I kind of wish that before
the before the midterm you gave us the
like I guess it might have been
stressful but it was stressful but it
might have helped if you gave us some of
these uh and I guess some some people
response might hate me for this but I
feel like if you gave us the if you
assigned the homeworks or like made the
view before the midterm then we can kind
of have an understanding of what we did
right and wrong so then we could oh yeah
yeah
so can you
can you make um the next two assignments
are due or like at least assigned before
the finals yeah yeah that's my yeah
that's my bad yeah because um my tea um
yeah the ti got delayed on that so I'm
going to release the homework
assignments soon like the file systems a
memory I'm going to release it this week
all the all the homework the file
systems the memory and the
virtualization we have three chapters
left system virtualization file system
and memory our going to release that in
one day but you have the uh you have
each of them you have like two weeks to
finish okay so um
so but I will release that earlier I
will definitely release the lower levels
thank you for the suggestion that's a
very good comment
uh
okay so um
do you feel the time is in love for
midterm
the time is in love
okay okay then that's good that's good
because in the final we'll have more
time
it will be still act nice and it's very
unfortunate for that
no no no we just discussed yeah we
already finished it yeah
so but the the the TA will have the
criteria so if you are not unsure about
any of the
answers cross answers so you can ask it
okay final system okay
um
also so tolerant file systems actually
file system you can think about if you
still remember the memory hierarchical
structure we have the register we have
the cache we have the memory then we
have the file we have the disk correct
so the file system actually has a very
similar structure abstraction of the
memory it's very similar no but the file
the only big issue with the file system
is that
file system is a abstraction of our disk
right disk file system is the
abstraction of the disk
the memory memory chapter in the memory
is the abstraction of the ram IEM right
file system is abstraction of disk so
the differences between the hardware of
the disk the disk hardware and the
memory Hardware what is difference
between this hardware and memory
Hardware
what are the difference
um
internal memory hierarchy what is the
difference between memory and disk what
is the difference yeah Andrew
the memory is a volunteer in this case
uh number very good and any else
the difference is yeah Andrew
memory is smaller and more extensive so
Memories We have very limited memory but
we have a lot of disk right we love this
so in that case if we have a page as an
obstruction of the memory that is 4kb
corresponds B we need we also have a
same obstruction in the disk and then we
call that block we call it a block and
block is larger than the page so we are
going to discuss that later
so first why we need file system
so the many important applications leads
to store more information than that in
Virtual address space of a process the
information must survive so that is the
first thing is that okay we need more
more spaces we need more Hardware spaces
second we need we need to save the
information right we need long volunteer
resource
third multiple process must be able to
access the information
concurrently concurrently
so we need to have multiple processors
able to access the information so what
kind of information
for example you have you have a
directory you have a directory saying
that the graders of the class
many students may be interested in the
graders of of him or her so they need to
concurrently access the same file
then you need to have a schedule to
enable that multiple process success
so how do how do we find the information
with safety into the disk how do how do
you keep one user from reading and
another user's data another user's data
so how do you keep one user from Reading
another user's data
we use the
it's
or in the file if you look at the
property of the file it can have some
read opening right right holding it can
how you can set it to be hide from
special users
for example in in the computer we can
set a special User Group
and the administrative group in the
administrative group we can see all the
files but in the user group you may only
see part of the file that is how can we
how can we keep one user from Reading
another usage data okay
okay
so the motivation the motivation is that
we need to use file system as an
obstruction to deal with accessing the
information capture in blocks on a disk
block the block here the block you
single the block is same as the page in
the memory the block the block is the
abstraction of the file system
files are created by a process there
might be thousands of them on the disk
or I structure them name them and
protect them
so there's two ways of looking at one we
are learning file system we are going to
look at it learn it from two perspective
one perspective is from the user point
of view
another perspective is from the
implementation point of view
the user point of view is how do we
label file protect it and organize these
files and the implementations of how can
how are they organized on your disk
so file systems the user point of view
lay means structural directories so that
is how we see a file system right how is
your file system so you can look at your
your laptop
click that into the disk what you are
going to see click it into the disk you
are going to see a lot of folders right
file folders
right and that is the file system so go
to the city it's called the disk you see
a lot of file folders and you click into
the file folders what you are going to
see you're going to see another file
folders right and then you click there
you see another file folders that is the
file system that is the structure of the
file system so what is the structure
it's a tree structure right it's a tree
structure you click the folders in the
into the disk any of the disk you click
it and then it shows another folder you
click again it shows another folder so
how the OS organize these folders a user
tree structure that is structure and
what's the limit so while you are naming
a folder naming a file you can
you can name it using any of the words
right you can name it with any of the
words that you like you can use some
special parameters right special
character characters you can use that
and the directories one thing to take
away is that from the OS point of view
the osc's directory is also same as a
file so if you look at the code in the
OS the directory has the same code as
the file they just have only one
difference it's like one bit shows that
it's a directory or file it's just like
it's a file or it's a directory
so let's look at the learning
or current operating system allows
streams of one to eight letters as a
legal file names
so for example you can say it's like
Blues Cassie Andrew a possible file
names and frequently digits and special
characters are also permitted so for
example you can say like two
like Cassie
something like that so windows
oh that is from the old um
in order to file a system format I'll
say something from we happen to file
system format
um
yes
file name
okay because for file name
counter example by saying that the the
um the name of this of this presentation
is actually more than eight characters
so
or eight letters it's eight letters
okay okay oh okay okay yeah yeah okay
I'm reading the content from the
textbook textbook is is written
five years ago that is
of os Advance okay OS Advanced yeah
okay so it's like this animal however
that
this is the old
all the
um file system format so we have the
file system format okay
so you have Windows 9 Windows 1980s it's
from Windows 1980s and another file
formatted file
the file system format is FAT32
and now we have the n
FS right the file name file names in the
Unicode
so Unix does not always enforce a
meaning for the suffix Stars the space
is very old you may not heard of that MS
DOS you how do anyone heard of that it's
it's more it's you heard of that Andrew
no it's it's it's older than you
it's older than you it's it's at my age
when I was borrowing it we use the math
dots it's very there's no UI so you need
to type everything is need to type we
just have a black screen and you type
everything there is a muscle up
always a surface example so it's oh this
surface examples we are see as computer
science major so we need to know that
okay we need to know that
so this is easy right
JFC Java and peace
MP3
PDF my PS text right text
Zip Zip is the compressed archive
these any students know that Bak
Ed so
that's not backup files
um in many logs in the system logs you
can see a lot of backup files I would
suggest to you after you come back home
you can open the hidden files in the OS
if you go to the file a property in the
in your in a Windows systems it can ask
you to
ask you whether you want to hide the
suffix then you're saying that okay I
will see the whole names and then you
expose the other hidden files then you
can see a lot of back files there
okay the file structure file structure
so um to learn that the file structure
let's see what we did at the early age
at the early age we use the biased
sequences by sequences file structure
means that
this is the disk
so this is a disk right it sucks you
have the sectors and the
the the the the
pointers to each sector this is pointer
to that so this is the disk each part of
the sectors right
then the fire structure means that if I
have a file like this
so when the osc file is just to see many
one zero one zero bytes or range right
then we have many files let's say many
bytes or range so how are we going to
structure this file save these files
into the disk that means file structure
so the old years we use the buy
sequences by sequences and then we use
some fixed lens records then we use the
tree of the records so let's look at the
differences of the age
so this is the byte sequences so when we
do buy sequences we just
see the file or the bytes see the files
device and put them one after another
that is a very old Year all the year
like the mess stores even the mess
stores we do not use that button this is
all the year file system and then and
then we
the OS the color of events are a little
bit then trying to see how it's not
efficient to save just the buys of the
buys for each file so what we are going
to do is that we segments around Robin
we we divided the disk into many same
columns the same spaces and we put a
file in each space but it's also not
inefficient it's not all not efficient
because it will waste a lot of space
then
developed we we are using the
tree structure we are using a tree
structure
that is what the um
most modern operating system did so Auto
operating systems use the tree structure
to organize the files the tree structure
signature structure we have the root
folder right the loot folder
and then we have different folders like
in the uh like a user
rice
Etc
device of many folders
that is the tree structure
the tree structures
okay and then file types
regular file we have the US
the regular file we have the regular
file the directories the character
special files and the block special
files there's four types of
files four types of files the regular
file are the ones that contain user
information
directories are system files for
maintain the structure of the file
systems so we are going to study the
directory later
chemical special files are related to
the i o and used to model serials i o
devices such as terminals printers and
networks
so any students familiar with that
when you insert your USB USB
into the into the laptop when you insert
that you can see that it's actually
Os or creates a folder for that USB and
loaded that folder into the OS tree
structure that is why if you insert a
USB into let's say your Ubuntu right
then you can see a
special or in separate folder for that
that is a special character special file
that is you use to represent all the i o
resources same as monitor motor is also
have a going to have a i o character
used to represent
a monitor okay a monitor when we insert
a monitor to connect the monitor to the
uh to the OS it's going to also create a
file relates to that and use the pipe
operation to transfer data between the
memory and the monitor
so well there's there's a very
interesting book I think it's the the
first sentence of that book this tells
you everything in the OS is a fire
everything in the OS is a file it's very
classical Iceberg I forgot the name
um it's it's it's written by a professor
you know Canadian Island it's very old
classic book and the first sentence of
the book is that everything in the OS in
operating system is a file so everything
you see the monitor the USB the folders
the file the and the just the regular
files they are all file so this the io
devices the i o devices
a character special files and block
special files block special files used
to model disk like the disk C disk D
disk e there are also files they are
just above the folder right they also in
the loot we are maybe in the root folder
and then this disk okay this disk
different disk
so um
so that in a regular file we have the
ASCO and binary code binary okay and ask
her this is the unscore code in the
Oscar so this is the article code that's
different formats different formats
it's Oscar called American Standard code
for information interchange they can be
displayed and printed as it is and they
can be added by with any text editor
yeah this is the user point of view
the way we learn is that how we use the
file system in here this part may be
very boring and easy to understand
because we are using file system every
day
yeah
yeah let's look at this better than that
binary file types
binary file types that is the already
over let's skip that
the file access this is this something
it's something that needs to have
retention so five percent is very
important because we are using file
access to prevent the user to write or
read another user's files for file
access
so in the early operating system they
provide only one kind of file access
called sequential access so in this
system a process could read all the
bytes and Records in a file in order
starting at the beginning but I couldn't
skip around and read them out of the
order so that's the secretion access and
random access files are essential for
many applications for example the
database systems so if
we want to we want to just look at a
special file not starting from the
beginning to the end then we need a
random access to the files right
so if in IO plan customers cross up want
to reserve seats for airplane for
particular flight the reservation
program might be able to access the
records for that that flight without
having to read the records for thousands
of the art of fights the other flights
that's a random access so file access so
how to do file access we use the file
attributes file attributes
every file has a names and its data
so the for example production
yes Andrew
or what's your name the name of RAM
oh yeah for this yeah
what are you accessing the file system
is rather more accessible access means
that I showed uh so this is the compared
to the old excess patterns in the old OS
in the old OS they can not search the
files that they want they need to if
they need to you remember that in the
Odyssey or old OS operating systems
there's no UI remember I told you
there's no UI so everything you need to
command when I learn computer science
when I know I I'm much older than you
when I learn a computer science I didn't
learn the UI I learned a lot of commands
first lesson is like different command
like
um many Ms doors come on like the CMD
and the CD is the same as what you do in
Ubuntu number at my age there's no UI
everything is you need to search and for
the files to win if I want to search a
file I need to type of commands and then
OS search for me from the beginning to
the end that is called sequential access
but not
Oscar developed right we have the
right now the windows 11 right it gives
you the UI so basically we just you just
go into the disk and find out the file
you want that is the random access
okay let's look at this this
the file attributes
um
the password creator owner there's no
questions right read only flag okay this
is this
you're familiar with this Command right
c-h-o-md
is is
you can change you you you if I type in
the 777 then I can give the
file to all the access right 777 means
All Access
let's see that this is the uh this give
you is actually help you set the what is
read out in Right audience excuse only
and the group will need something like
that
you need to remember some of the batch
scripts there's very they are very good
textbooks about the batch scripts
there's very heavy book but you do not
need to buy that you just play with the
Ubuntu it's very important after your
graduates you are going to go join any
company software accomplished
they require you to
um familiar with this batch scripts code
so this command and many commands is
reading to changing the file attributes
changing the file attributes
I see some chords for files so this is a
system code for files
that's very easy to understand so I'm
skip that see some quotes for files
append append seek
put so far importance specific place in
file read and write from that position
on get attributes make needs most recent
modification types or running for group
completion set attributes protection
attributes and relaim it
okay and then how can system code be
used this is some code
so we read that code it's going to copy
the file
so copy the file to ABC to XYZ
this is the system core code
this is a
this is a system core code okay that's
how we
how we make a system okay let's quickly
end us directory okay what is the
directory directly files which are used
to organize a collection of files
collection also called folders
so directory
I like to call it a folders or just a
full directory that they're directly
you'll still organize a collection of
files this is the single Library
directory right it has a root directory
and then some files under that so
remember that right now all OS use the
tree direct choose three structure three
structure to organize the files and the
directories hierarchical tree structure
so this is the loot directory right the
rule directory and under root directory
you have many other user directories and
other users directories so to the Past
names so we have the absolute past name
the relative past names
are you familiar with Star Trek you're
familiar with that right so the
operative relative so we
the absolute means starting from the
starting from here this is the loot this
is means loot right this means lose
so absolute means that you locate a file
from the beginning the loot directory to
the end relatively means that we just
look starting from the current directory
and then we find out the
um the the files under the current
directory that is the relevant relevance
path
of the past names okay and this is the
um this is your new systems directory
file system directory this is still from
the user's point of view this is how we
see how we see our file system looks
like
and then later in our next class we are
going to learn how we develop that so
you see right now you just see the
how it appeals to you how the file
systems used are used by Earth do you
this is like the um
if it is a project then this is a
project requirements okay okay this is
the project requirements you need to
specify or three three structural to
organize the files you need to implement
that you need to implement the file
attributes you need to implement the
access control for the files you need to
overlapse these files into a tree and
save the files
in the disk that can
preserve maintain the tree structure how
are you going to do that
when you implement the system think of
that question
of hidden directory operations we have
many directory operations like craze
list open open DIY means open the
directory right close the IR Link and
Link
they also there's a there's difference
between the software link and Hardware
link any students know that
link there's a software link and a
hardware link so I can make a very
shortcut to a file I just copy the
shortcut of the file to the to another
folder then when I click that shortcut I
can
I can see the same files that is a
software link but there's another link
called Hardware link that I call
actually copy the file from two
different places and when I want to
access the one copy of the file the
other copy will not change that is the
hardware disk Hardware link so there's
two differences
okay so this is today's class
um
starting next class we are going to
learn from the implementation view of
the file system okay
so thank you
foreign