uh okay so this class will be our last
class it's just a QA session because
we've already finished the final review
so here's what I plan
um
so you can come here on board to ask me
questions or you can raise your hands to
ask me questions so
um
anyways you want and I can provide the
answers
so any questions you can ask
um
page replacement algorithms okay so page
replacement algorithms
um
so here's the thing you have your
lecture notes right the natural notes in
the it is in your um
in the natural notes in the um
um in a memory memory page after the
page represents algorithms we have an
example and in your homework we have
another example the homework review
so um if you're not a sure of that I can
later so by the end of this week I'm
going to sub
um release all the homework solutions
okay
so including the file system and for the
page replacement algorithms any specific
question about page replacement
algorithms
the graph which graph
working Circle as a function oh okay
okay you mean the formula the Volcan
says formula oh okay so this part is out
of our
oh it's out of the lecture so because we
have not discussed in the lecture Zone
we are not going to this uh test it out
but for you to understand the key idea
about the working set is that
um
when we talk about the page within the
algorithms we use an example about the
reference streams right so in the
reference streams we're thinking of the
the way that you access the pages is one
page after one page after one page
so for example is the a b c d b
c d f
e f like this right
so we give you the example
about what we're saying like Okay this
is the this is your
this is this three let's say this is
your physical memory you only have three
slots to handle these streams
um memory access streams and then we ask
you the calculating uh the number of
page fours right
so this is the page replacement
algorithms after we discussed are we
talking about a working search so the
reason why we set working search is that
most of times most of times we
the streams coming not one and one not
one by one the streams like the access
streams
let's say we are looking for a page a
specific page we are not we are not
going to find the page one by one
so for example are you loading your OS
you're not going to loading the page the
missing pages one by one right we are
noting a lot of pages together and this
page required a batch of pages
and so working set is help you design
what is the best size the optimal size
of the number of page references
so that is the key idea of the working
sets and then there's a formula about
determining the best size of the working
cells we have the formula intellectual
nodes okay
[Music]
um
yeah
okay so today is the QA session
the last time I put the QA session in
the zoom uh
um but I'm afraid it may not recorded
very well so I'm going to do that in
person so any other questions
yes
practical problems
yeah yeah I'm
definitely so um
you may notice that in your midterm
right I'm asking you questions in
not just exactly the same way as I ask
you in the homework so that is the way
if you understand the concept in my
um
um you can easily to um
answer it for example I'm just it may
not be in the exam okay just some
examples okay for example
if I'm asking you like saying okay you
are the system designer now
um
now can you um can you
design a new page replacement algorithms
right I can show this design a new page
of resistant algorithms that is let's
say
after
another different system go
I mean in the first server first to come
firstly serve to succumb what is the
system goal
season go
remember
we have the optimal algorithm optimal
page replacement algorithms right the
least recently used the page replacement
algorithms right and we have the worst
page replacement algorithms we have the
um
like the first thing first out the first
come first serve replacement algorithm
right
so they have different system goals what
if I'm asking you like here's the new
system go can you design that this is an
example okay another example okay after
you design this page of his algorithms I
want to ask you okay
um
how the algorithms Works can you specify
the negative page size okay the page
size like what will be the best optimal
page size and how about a bigger page
side what is the benefits and this
disadvantages how about a smaller big
size a smaller page size the world will
be the benefits and limitations
and then come to the after page size now
I may ask you okay
um how about a page table
right
um are you going to design a one level
page table
with multi-level page tables what will
be the disadvantages and disadvantages
of that
remember that when we're talking about
page tables right page tables we
there are maybe multi-levels of page
tables right and how it influence to
your
the how you influence the
yeah it's not good to say that
in see this is a memory hierarchical
structure right
we have register
we have a register a cache
a memory
what memory we have the
uh this color this
show you first you first go to you look
at the law the
you look at the tlb to find the page
right and then if this means you look at
them where
the page table right the page table and
if still meets then you go to the disk
so in exam it may not are
straightforwards like that
I may ask you as for example I tell you
uh okay hey here this is 10 milliseconds
or 10 nanoseconds to or to
to find our entry in the tlb 100 minutes
level seconds to find the entry in the
page table and the 100 1000 nanoseconds
to find that the files in the in the
disk
so then I tell you okay you have 10
percentage to have a tlb tlb hits you
have
around 20 percentage for the page table
hits
you have then what will be the average
what will be the average
response time together
got her paid to successfully got a page
well it may not appear to an example
because I'm just making an example
because I have a lot of questions in my
mind I have not designed my exam
questions
it's just an example yeah yeah
well here's the thing if you have 20
percentage hits the page table then that
means the other 80 percentage you have
to go to
where so
the exam the problem if I'm making an
exam question like this it will be very
specific you tell you like 10 percentage
in the tlb whenever you touch tlb it
will be 10 percentage and you miss your
tlb you go to the page table
the circumstances probability that the
page is in the page table is 20
percentage so that means another 80
percentage you need to go through this I
cannot tell you exactly what it looks
like but this will be the way that I I
can test you about the page Force
handling the page Force right
this is off flexible questions they are
not exactly the same as your homework
Solution that's that's right down those
write down the short answer
right
okay so this is all about like
um
memory memory chapter but there are many
Post Falls
exam questions
it's not it's not limited to just
calculating the
feeling the memory
there are many there may be many other
questions right like what I
um introduce to you guys like how to
how to calculate how to do the
um
address translation
from the virtual
virtual address to a physical address
right
like how to do that what is the concept
of offset
can you calculate the page size based on
this
all right
okay okay we'll continue our QA sessions
okay
you can ask me any questions you yeah
we it will be the same
um
yeah not exactly the same number as your
midterm but will be very similar
um yeah
um I expect to take
um
well maybe one and a half one and a half
should be oh it's I cannot say that
because different students have
different style
like when I was doing my my my final
midterm even I finished studying while
I'm still sitting there waiting for
another two hours I'm just checking
whether if I'm I was wrong in
yeah I'm that that kind of person
laughs
yeah so we have three hours it will be
in love for everyone
yes
yes we will first have true false
questions then we will have we will have
the um
multiple choice question
so they give you a multiple choice right
but you owning a circular one okay ABCD
only one solution is correct
then we have some short answers and then
we have some um
yeah a lot of short answers and then
like long answers
um design questions
coding questions
yeah you can bring your
um
you cannot bring your cell phone
but you can bring the calculator
because I'm I'm yeah
yeah you can bring your calculator okay
well I'll ask my th will send an
announcement
so you can bring your calculators and no
need to afraid that it's maybe too much
to to do the calculation
yes
no you you are not allowed to bring any
cheat sheets
and uh
I'm going to I'm going to have the exam
of exam exam version version a and the
exam version B so even students sits
likes to each other or receive different
versions
um
because we have no
many more students than I expected yeah
um
yeah I have not designed that um I'll
look at it I'm trying to give you many
solutions so
for example the coding question maybe
just some actual points
because
um I do not want you guys to worry too
much about your final it's not that
difficult okay but if you if you want to
finish challenging questions there will
be challenging questions it will be in
the actual actual credits it will be
very very very challenging okay
yes
um yeah I can give you an example but I
can I cannot
um go do the exactly one give you
example okay
um
[Music]
here's the thing okay
um
if I'm telling you if I'm telling you
the offset
those sets has four bits
okay this is the this is one of the
dress officers and then
so this is the let's say
so this is a virtual um
someone what's your address right some
virtual address then I'm telling you
this for example the offset has four
bits
so what do you think the size of the
page
what do you think the size of the page
yet
thing right 16 White 16.
this is this can be a
we I gave you the offsets right so this
is the wishing one page so this is
exactly one page
right there's one page I have different
uh the pay the page officer
so the number of the entries right the
number of entries is the size of the
page right size of the page so you need
to know how to
how to do the calculation
right so that is uh for the this is one
tricky part
um
another tricky part is if in the obvious
way if I tell you
the page size is 16.
the page size is 16 byte then how do you
think the
which part of the code is the offset
then you should know this is the from
the end to the last four is the offset
right
so you you yeah Andrew
page size of 10
no I do not think so
the page size right the pages that you
need to so what is the page size
page this is like a page right each page
we have many entries
right and then the pros the code can
can be in any of these entries
okay
so that is for the translation and we we
do the trans translation
it's like we have the you only need to
find out okay this is the virtual page
number right then you look at the
the page table so this is the page table
you look at the page table and you find
out
so this is this page number what are the
exactly this virtual page number refers
to let's say it's reference to two
zero zero one zero then the virtual page
then the virtual the virtual sorry the
physical address is zero zero one zero
and zero one zero one right that is the
so you're looking at what exactly this
is the virtual page you find out what
exactly the physical pages and then
replace it with this and then add in the
offset then that is the physical address
that is physical address
of the code
okay
so you need to to be able to do this
calculation
and uh
so we already know how to find out the
we already know how to find out the
you are able to filling in this right
you're unable to finish in this what if
I gave you this are you able to tell
whether it is a first in first house or
optimal Replacements or list the reason
I use replacement algorithms are you
able to do the office
all right let's continue yes Andrew
what what what what what do you want uh
say again
so water execution of stress
how to determine that
is you need to give the Assumption about
what how to determine that
right in which case are they sharing the
same variables
I I do not know the question
uh what's the question related yes
yeah it's like uh implementation
it's the true first question let's say
again
because I kind of forget
it's true Force
no
come kind of
BE Implement them and internally user
space you don't need
for stress oh okay
kind of forget okay for stress and the
process
where we want to test to you is about so
so here's the thing context switch
between Surat can also be painful even
thrust but only two different process
but contacts between the process are
always painful
so if I'm testing the
this this resin process or maybe the
differences between threats and process
but uh the things that they actually
have the same data structure
like maintain the same input output
status register values
but the the difference is that if the
threads are created by the same process
then at the back end when OS managing
distress
they save them the same they mean the
same on the dry space that is why it's
cheaper
so industrializing process chapter
um the most important takeaway here is
to understand or some foreign
we may also test that again because it's
very important
um
like we may ask you to use this to
implement a synchronization problem
you heard of the the
so for example there are many there are
many real life examples that are like
like the car
like in the cross streets right
in different ways like different car
they they are sharing the
they're looking at the green the green
lights red lights and the yellow lights
right
then can you using this to some woman
text to implement a
synchronization system that's that's one
example and there are many other
examples it's like a producer customer
a different kind of producer and
customer
stress and process
you need to know how to calculate the
average turnaround time
the um
you need to know what is the wait time
right the wait time
for each person what is the wait time
what is the execution time then what is
the turnaround time that's that's quite
different
wait time
execution time
internal runtime
that is a
threading process
yes
for what
oh you're asking this can be
like oh it will be binary
[Music]
potassium binary
I will not make it complex
if there if I do not say it will show
you show it in the exam right it may may
or may not I have not finished my
final final exam questions
may or may not okay
danock
do you have any questions for dialogue
so you know that we know that uh we have
the
um example questions like
um
remember we say that we have
different process right each process
needs two
we have different process each process
needs two drives like a disk drives to
process right and I'm giving you the num
write the number of the total resources
so each process needs two resources to
get through I'll give you the number of
resources that asks you what is the
maximum number of the process that
ensure dialog free right remember the
question right
so what if the what if not not if what
if it is not two resources each process
needs three resources one will be the
max number
of the process that ensure it is dialog
free have you think of that sort of that
question so it's a extended version
right
you understand my question right
so
this is the six resources six identical
resources in the each process needs two
resources
to finish so what is the maximum number
that you ensure number of process to
ensure if the system is dialog free
is five right
it's five right
so what if what if the question is
slightly changed I'm saying still six
resources but each process needs three
resources
each process needs three resources
to finish so what will be the maximum
number of the earn I will not check I
will not discuss that but I'm just
erasing this okay I'm just erasing this
this is maybe an extended version of the
dialog chapter have you thought of that
yeah
advantages and disadvantage of
multi-level page table
what do you think is the advantage of
what do you think
where is the page table we put the page
table
why we need multi-level page table
yes
very very good very good here's the
thing right so page table so um
why we need a page table page level save
the
save the entries save the entries
between the
save the entries
between the a virtual page to the
physical page right physical page
so in
if if if we have we have
small page size if we have small page
size and large memory large physical
memory then that means the page table
entries will be very very large right
will be very very large so to save the
memory spaces We cannot put the whole
page table in the memory that is why we
designed a multi-level page tables so
you can store some part of the page
table in the memory which you mostly
like the most frequently use the page
table entries then put the rest of the
levers okay one level to level in the
disk that is why we need
that is why we need a multi-level page
tables right
the number of page the number of the
size
the total size of the page table
page table what do you determine the
page table the page table is just the
mapping right a mapping from one address
to another address right so
so if there's a lot of mappings then the
page table will be huge right it'll be
huge
if it is huge
then you cannot store or waiting memory
because there will be significantly used
of memory
then multi-level page table may help you
may help you and and even you can post
that in memory you do not want to
Pursuit all together in a continual
display it's not much multi-level is
what is multi-level page table is just
adding a link like a Linker list right
link list so it can help you make the
best use of the resource to managing the
whole page table so it's an open
question guys do not try to memorize my
solution my answer is an open question
so you think of you you try to make it
sense okay this is an open question yeah
so the same thing like the page size
and the same thing like the I know table
remember why lastly in our last class we
have a question I'm asking you a design
question
why we need I know the table can we just
store the I know the information in
memory instead of inode table and why or
why not we do that
right this is an all open question
yes
in which situation you think of that in
which situation
if you do not have that much entries
right
the max number of
the max number of what
how big the physical memory is
how many page frames in the memory
how many page frames that's the term
that is determined by how large is the
memory that you have and then the size
of your page side
right because the page frame size is the
same as the page size
friends
yeah yeah yes yes yes yes of course that
is one-to-one mapping right one to one
mapping
any questions about the file system Io
Io
what is a reference count
of the I node what is the concept of
reference currently in the inode
or the reference counts of the I node
what is used for what is useful for
it's not how many is not how many users
are using this is how many directories
are concurrently
points to that specific it's not how
many users okay
right and then what is that used for
I can become three
and what is that used for
yes
yeah that's good but
you need to mention that's like holding
white becomes zero then that means
no directory is using
that specific files right that I know
then that file that can be
deleted right this can be a file Cameo
directory so the reference or the
reference count right this is
the differences between the hard link
and the
yes
you can be an insane it's access okay
access
the camera reading camera writing it can
be on it can be excess okay
reference count is a Concepts we or like
what is I node right what is inode
or is it I not
a lot of the information about the notes
the name name
where like address of the file uh how
big the file is
yeah very good
yeah yeah very good and we
um in file system we we first
before we're talking about I know so
this is all about I know the right we um
we've also spent a lot of time to
to discuss other like
other algorithms to managing the free
blocks right
for example
there's an approach called continually
allocation
right continuity allocation
and we have
in a continual allocation we using two
algorithms to implement two data
structures to implement the continually
allocation algorithm so first what is
the continually
location
allocation
continuous allocation
right we are we implement we use two
data structures right
be map right
and the link release right
so continually allocation then we say
that this is not good so why it is not
good why it is not good
so we say continue allocation it's not
that good why it is not that good and
the bin map is just or LinkedIn is just
two approach to implement the continuing
allocation approach right so be in the B
map
we we are using
what you think
a lot of bits to to represent whether
this block is taken or not right if it's
not taken then with zero if taken we use
one
so we use we use this so in the link
list we use the P to represent its
occupied
we use H to represent this or how it's
not occupied I mean we can also Define
the size of each
blocks right so
um what is the advantage of beam map
what is the advantage of linked list
that is what we have learned in the file
system right
and in which circumstances you you may
choose these algorithms in May it this
up implementations in which
circumstances you choose linked lists
the implementation
right and then we're talking about
an improved version of the link list
that is called linked list with the
table
is the table Index right table index
with linked list and then we're talking
about inode with we will introduce inode
and we're also talking about I know the
table
so we are also talking about if I'm
giving you the absolute pass yes
yeah actually actually this these are
quite similar these are crazy in the
lecture in the lecture is the
continually allocation with the swapping
is called swapping technology right in
memory equals swapping technology
it's not this notice okay okay my force
my fault so
all in this Linker list all in this okay
only this yeah
so
yeah beach map in a bit when we're
talking about bitmap approach we are
actually talking about it with the
swapping technology in the in the memory
the memory chapter is actually this this
is just the one solution in the textbook
about how you can
um how you can
um keep track of
the available the free blocks so there's
many solutions bitmap is just a solution
in the page in the in the paging but it
you can also be used here it's just I'm
not putting that in the slide okay
yeah my badly okay I'm trying to not
make it confused just a link list so
linked list we're talking about
different algorithms right so the first
feeds
pass the feeds
versus the feet
quick Fades okay quick feeds so what is
a quick fix Quick Fix yes
all the um the most common sites oh yeah
yeah it's very good so so quick face is
that we
um it says it's like we we just keep
track of the like the comma size is like
two four eight sixteen something like
this then
when we have this the this is our empty
spaces empty spaces now when we have new
files we we find out we find out this
a continual location and then we're
talking about the um I node
I node
I know the table
so if I'm giving you a address
um
it's an absolute trust in
you are able to
find out the file okay the file
should be able to find out the file you
should be able to write down the path to
locate that file that is what we learn
in the file system okay file system
um
so here in file system we have actually
many open questions that I can think of
that so in file system we're talking
about centralized the file system we
will also talk about the centralized of
an example of decentralized file system
right so centralized the file system is
is what it's the what we learned a lot
the Linux file system
is a centralized then we learn hdfs
which is a decentralized right sorry
it's a distributed it's a distributed
file system so the difference is that
there are blocks
their blocks are replicated by three
times
and puts
so in hdfs the the difference is that
they put the blocks they replicate the
blocks into three times and put the
difference three blocks in different
places like one is within the same node
one is within the same rack and another
one is across the rack right the reason
is that we want to ensure the best for
tolerance so whenever a rack is fails we
can always find another blocks in
another
in another rock whatever
but if only the file is missing but the
machine is there we can copy it from our
laboring nodes something like that so
three blocks you need to understand why
we using three uh why are we using three
and where we put these three replica
replica blocks into understand the good
way
the good approach to ensure the failure
recovery for tolerance is redundancy so
which means the replication approach
there's another approach
is another approach is called
checkpointing Head model if you think of
that when when we learn this what is the
checkpointing checkpointing means that
whenever I do something I
I take down what I have
I take down my logs and then put the
logs in some safe spaces so for example
um
you know the white one drive right
use that you're using it right
OneDrive for Dropbox or Google Drive you
are using it so what they did Is that
real you are working or you are let's
say you are working on documents in the
in your desk in in a desktop you're
working on it and then you
you forget to
yes like auto save but auto save is like
checkpoint is it has a name more
professional names is checkpointing
that's the key that's the key idea of
checkpointing so it's going to
periodically checkpointing what you have
done maybe 10 minutes 10 seconds sorry
10 minutes or half a minute or 30
minutes so they they're going to push
them and then upload that into some safe
space safe place like in a OneDrive what
they did is that they put this uploaded
that to a Google drive right so
checkpoint is another approach to ensure
failure recovery
um
in this case if we are if we are using
checkpointing to implement the hdfs then
there will be no hdfs anymore then that
will be the same as NFS like Network
file system so we have we still have a
new nucleus FS system whenever we have a
new files comes in your local node then
we are going to upload that into some
Central cloud
right that is checkpoint into a cloud we
can still ensure that it has
a failure recovery right then if I'm
asking you to design a system like that
can you design it what would be the new
name node looks like what will be the
new
data node looks like what will be the
challenging problems what will be the
challenging problems that means students
can think of that why hdfs using
reputation to do the failure recovery
not using the checkpointing to do the
failure recovery
think of that
why
because many times you do not have the
disconnection to the cloud right
if it's just a local server local server
you have 10 servers you just have La in
contacts connects you do not have won
you cannot go to the cloud
send the data to the cloud then the
local replication may be the best
approach so so single creatively about
that so file system has a lot of
interesting scenes to to think of that
okay so
when we're talking about the new nucleus
file system watch DFS file systems they
are using Master Slave architecture we
work oh sorry no more we're using this
okay column server clients
server clients
architecture is like a Master Slave okay
so the I know the name node is like a
master
the data node is like a slave so Master
Slave what if I'm asking you can you
design a new architecture like
peer-to-peer architecture
so this is more like a design
challenging design questions can you
can you think of a solution
this is this will be so this kind of
work is what you are going to to
pursue in your in your graduate study
okay if you have that interest to to
take a mass or take a PhD degree then
that is the
um
some research topics
what else
there are actually not too much about IO
they are not too much about IO
I owe by Pauline
I hope I interrupt
I hope I
direct memory access so the differences
of this so what is Io Io it means import
output right so input output status is
another abstraction
um
you might find out that for
so an operating system is an abstraction
between the hardware and the software
the users software that is operating
system so if IO is one part of the
operating system so which part of it so
I always just translates
so you have for example you have a USB
either from a SanDisk
sentence this is a SanDisk right this is
a very good brand SanDisk and there's
another
King King song right there are many
different brands they may have different
ways to design the USC they may use
different material I know some material
is water resistance some material is
like heat resistant some material can
can be more safe like adding the
encoding some have encoding algorithm
into that so there's different Hardware
but the thing is that the operating
system you OS like the Microsoft your
nucleus they are not going to understand
every Hardware language they will not
they will not get an idea about the
language the the material that each of
the different brands are using then the
then the key idea of the io is that
operating system are going to give the
interfaces to different brands
so each each company then they can have
using the this interface is to implement
their own device controller so in device
control what is device control device
controller is to managing the input and
outputs the bytes okay like the speed of
the bytes the translation of the bytes
into some languages that all us can't
understand
so always only give you the interface
but how you implement search is by
different company
so that is IO then but OS inside of the
OS they are going to use the difference
different technology to manage the speed
to manage enough data transfer speed
between the
um between our device
to memory
okay
so this these are three device these are
three approaches the OS managing the
speed the data transfer speed between
the device to the memory but how to do
the um
translation of the from different
material to the OS as you can understand
this
that is belonging to the driver's job
okay each driver's job so that's the
difference
um
that is for Io
well I think I have
um any any more questions
what else
see some core right you understand see
some call you understand the interrupt
you can understand the contact switch
you understand what is the kernel what
is the user mode what is the kernel mode
um
what is the main job of os you
understand the time sharing space
sharing you understand the CPU pipeline
you understand the interrupts
oh you understand interrupt Handler you
understand
see some core system Library
right you understand contact switch
um
many new Concepts like thread process
process values what is the ready State
what is block state
what is the
running stage
can
running stage directory go to the blog
states can block States go directly to
the running States in which
circumstances a process can run from a
running state
to the block States
what is a iobz
what is iobz process what is a
computational intensive
process what's the difference is between
the i o intensive and the completion
intensive process how can you tell which
process is a i o intensive
or computation intensive
if I'm giving you several process I tell
you they are IO weight percentage can
you tell me the average CPU utilization
of the system
can we can you tell me the idle time of
the system
what is the critical section
what is the barrier what is
synchronization
what is shell valuable
differences between busy waiting and the
starvation
what is the alternative clock right of
the latest block right
sorry Auto
what is the software approach to to
avoid a
race condition what is the hardware
approach to avoid race condition
how to use the mutex and some phone to
avoid the race condition what is exactly
a race condition
why race condition happens
yes
has not been neither of them are work
properly
but why it messes why because contact
switch happens right when they try to
access the same resources and then the
then the accessing order
is not determined by the process
determined by the CPU scheduling and is
unexpected that his Wireless condition
happened right and then after this we're
talking about
some form you text
why what is the what is some form what
is mutex can some form become elective
can mute tags become lactive
how many values can mutex have has how
many values can some form has
when some form becomes zero what will
happen
will come when some form becomes
like positive what will happen it will
like
make which process of sleep which will
wake wake up which process oh that's a
new order New Concept okay in the
process
or else producer customer problems
dialing philosophy problems
right and then we're talking about
dialogue four conditions for that log to
happen what are these four conditions
then how to avoid these four conditions
we have four Solutions right we can
completely avoid the problem we can use
or dynamic avoidance we can use
active prevention and then we can use
leak remove any of the conditions right
avoid any of the conditions to happen
easy
no you are not there no you were not
there yeah because I missed a lecture it
were not there
okay so
Let's Help Me review then so how to
what's the differences between
non-preemption preemption what resources
are preemptive resources what resources
are long preemptive resources
is that is the printer preemptive or
non-preemptive
okay
yeah
let's bring her the printer in normal in
most cases is non-preemptive right
because
yeah that is the solution that how you
avoid the
um this situation right avoid the four
conditions right we have four conditions
we can support everything that is the
approach we can order in the num the
resources what are the resources we can
ensure that different we can we can
avoid the mutual exclusion we can show a
different process we can share the
results right
um
why else then yo you need to know how to
write the resource or location graph for
example I'm using
we are using
we're using the array the arrow to
to represent rice I have I have the I
have some resource and I want another
resource right so you if I'm I'm giving
you the number is like okay the resource
the user a has the result of R but once
the results of
Z you you should be able to draw the
resource allocation graph that is the
because that is the only way that you
can find out the you can find out
whether there's a potentially secure
change in the system right but it does
not mean that the system will be that
locked why does not mean the system will
be deadlocked because the there are
other four conditions you need to
consider so the so the exam material
give you the hints about the other four
conditions then you you holding
four conditions are there then that
means it it is there's a dialogue then
we long after we learn the dialogue we
learned the memory chapter right we say
why we need um what is the memory
hierarchical structure why there's a
memory hierarchical structure and we
learn about the
different algorithms to
to manage the memories swapping
technology right we use bitmap and the
linked list to locate the free available
memory resources then we have the
virtual memory right when we introduce
virtual memory why we need virtual
memory
because yeah
or if there's enough space for a
positive
shot making the short why we need a
virtual memory because yes
why why we need a virtual memory
no why we need virtual memory
even for in the memory why we need
virtual memory
so that is that because we have shortage
of memory that is the physical memory so
in our world we have a shortage of
physical memory
okay
um
uh okay and version after virtual memory
we will learn about the
um
so it's virtual memory so virtual memory
every process has a virtual memory they
are independent so virtual memory right
they have their independence virtual
memory address every process has that
okay every process has that
so a page table refers to
the mapping between the
between the virtual pages to the
physical pages right physical pages so
that is the page table and then you need
to know the page table in the page table
there's many entries right some some
represents this is 30 or not what it
means by Dirty
dirty right some a bit rough if one
means it's 30 what is 30 means right and
some bits reference is the access model
what is read or write or executes right
and some um
some rubber one reference one bit
represents its if if it's in a physical
memory one notch
then that is the page table architecture
so you need to know that where is Page
table
um right it's what is mmu what is the
tlb what is Page table entry
what is the um
why we need a tlb well we already have
page table why we need tlb
um so if it is a hit in the tlb does it
means there's no page fourth if it's a
Miss in the tlb doesn't mean there are
definitely no page Force well there's a
page Force if it's a Miss in the tlb
then I would say there's a page for
these are true Force
true or false fourth first yeah because
you need to later you need to see the
page table right you need this is how
you um how you see the how to handle in
the page Force how to handle page four
we first look at tlb we then look at
page table we go to the disk we fetch
the disk we fetch the file from this
proceeding number in the physical memory
then updates One updates the page table
then updates the TL video sequences you
cannot update the trb and then update
the page table you need to go like a
circle and then finish the job right and
then um
after that we learn about the address
translation
we also learn about the um
like the other Concepts like the page
frames right working search we also
learn about the
offsets right so that's a very a lot of
concept you know as the the course is
full of Concepts we have hundreds of new
Concepts and then we after we talk about
the
then talk about the files this Samurai
so file see some key Concepts is the
we first review it from a
personal
um user's point of view so you need to
think about that oh
what is a directory what is a file right
that
um what is the directory what is file so
what is the tree hierarchical structure
three hierarchical structure one is the
absolute pass what is relative path
what is the um
what is block
um what is block address what is inode
what is continually allocation approach
in the continual allocation approach you
use the linked list to implement the
continually allocation approach right I
think in the linked list we have
different algorithms to look at locate
the different blocks like we have first
feeds next feeds best feeds versus the
feeds quick feeds
second feeds we have many algorithms so
um
then we learn about the
here after that we learned about the
I know it right I know this is a key
concept I note so what is that exactly I
node and I know there's a special
contents called reference counts what is
reference counts means
what is the um
a symbolic share link and a hard link
right
um
what is the I know the table
so I know you need to understand I know
it contains the order of addresses right
the block of address about the about the
this file so each file has an inode
right by the way and I know table will
save the locations of
what I node
then we learned IO
so we learned three approaches to doing
the i o these three approaches what are
their differences in which circumstances
you may choose IO by interrupt
in which circumstances you choose IO by
dma
so
you don't understand in which
circumstances you use each approach okay
so this is mostly the
what we learned in this semester are
you any more questions
yeah
what exactly optimal page replace when
the algorithms looks like so the optimal
so well here's the scene we
the optimal page replacement algorithm
says that you
you always know so
if this is a reference count a b c d e a
c d f g so if if there's a reference
count streams like that so the optimal
page replacement algorithm is that you
assume that you order you already know
which orbital most frequent which will
be the
um
use which will be used in the next
Circle in the next time
okay so it assumes that you know what
will happen in the future and you always
make the best choice
so that's it that is not that he's not
going to implement that in in in
the real world because it's it's just a
test method
it's just a customer okay
um
okay so uh I think it should be fine
because I I see you on me drama see
everyone's midterm I think you performs
really great
um
yeah and it's even before I cover the
grade I didn't curve your grade for
midterm I would craft or everyone's
great after I got all the great together
okay like your homework your projects
um you have
you have one project so it's pending
right final product the project five
after I got all the grade then I
calculate the final grades then I will
calculate that
um
uh do the curve to the curve so my curve
is very
um
strange forward okay I will try to cut
it a half okay so as long as you stand
in the middle of the class it should be
good okay so um
okay I I want to thank you guys for uh
for well come for choose my lecture and
I hope that you can learn something from
this and uh okay so good luck with your
final
okay oh one thing one more thing I
appreciate if you guys can um can review
this class so I will give the actual one
points to for for the students who
submits the review okay so there will be
uh yeah after the after the final week
there will be a link for you to send the
review
okay okay thank you
thank you