oh
so today we are going to uh so today we
are going to first
um do a review of all the introduction
then we are going to finish our the
first chapter the process and threat
okay so let's look at the video
what
song
hello I'm going to explain the basics of
an operating system so that you have an
understanding of its desired purpose
we will be covering key Concepts and
definitions whilst briefly touching upon
the essentials of operating systems so
what is an operating system
in simple terms it is the chief program
that manages all of the hardware and
software it has control of every process
file section of memory and device it is
very important as it works as a
middleman making sure both hardware and
software interact correctly Windows Mac
OS Linux and Unix are the big operating
system contenders and all have their own
advantages and or disadvantages but they
are all based off the same concept
there are four essential managers of
every operating system and they all work
together like a team to get jobs
completed the operating system works as
their boss and makes sure they are all
working in harmony
the memory manager is in charge of the
main memory it scans every request for
memories in charge of their boss
so look at that
this is the OS router we have the
process process rat so this is chapter
one
memory this will be our chapter 2 file
system will be our chapter 3 and device
management will be our chapter four so
in this course we are going to cover
these four chapters okay in the
and to make sure they are all working in
harmony
the memory manager is in charge of the
main memory it scans every request for
memory space and checks if it is valid
it allows allocation of memory spaces
that are not taken up already
memory spaces may need to be
de-allocated to free up space for other
requests
the process map to free up space so look
at that look at that what is the job
this job is a running program a process
right so you see that this is the ram
space Ram is our memory right see these
jobs are they are sharing the memory and
they have their each own address space
for other requests so if you look at
them
memory spaces may need to be
de-allocated what is mean deallocation
means the
yeah man's daughter dropped when the job
is finished we need to free the space
right so there's there's a page
replacement algorithm because you need
to design
which job to go to next
so what we're going to learn the
requests
the process manager decides how to
allocate the brain of the computer known
as the central processing unit
it is necessary that the process manager
keeps track of the status of each
process it has to handle jobs as they
enter the system and manage each process
that is associated with those jobs the
device manager monitors every device
Channel and control unit it has to
choose the most efficient way to
allocate all of the system devices that
are connected to the computer USB sticks
printers and external hard drives are
examples of this
the file manager checks every type of
file that is on the system this means
data files program files compilers and
installed applications it sets
permissions so that certain users can
only see certain files so when you log
into your guest account you cannot
browse through the administrator's files
as you do not have the permission to do
so
another manager worth mentioning is the
network manager this provides a way for
users to share hardware and software
resources while also controlling the
user's access to them
so we now understand how it works under
the hood so how do we the user interact
with the operating system we rely on the
use of a user interface this gives us a
visual understanding of what we are
trying to do when we interact with the
system so when you click and hold the
file to move it into a folder you're
making the managers work to carry out
the request
in the next few tutorials we will be
digging deeper into manage
um
also at the beginning of this class we
are going to have a short review about
the introduction section so this is the
forgetting curve that I mentioned to you
in our last class it means that if you
want to remember something you need to
uh
so the the forgetting curve hypersides
the decline of memory in time so so this
curve shows that how the information is
lost over time when there is low attempt
to retain it so we need to keep learning
that time and time again to help us
remember everything okay the the
stronger the memory the longer period of
time the person is able to record so
that is why we have this review session
because if you look at this when we
first learned that at the first name we
remember everything button at the second
day you see we will almost only remember
80 percentage of it and when the time
passage at the certainly you if you do
if you do not record refresh it you're
going to forget everything
but if you if you review it
if you review it
if you review it you're going to uh
mostly learn it for a long time
okay so um
so you you may have already do the
homework so just to quickly go over it
okay what the main purpose of our
protein system
so it's an abstraction right the
operating system's job is to provide
users with the abstractions such as
process or just based files which are
more more convenient to use than actual
hardware and as a resource manager the
operating system's job is to manage a
different part of the system efficiently
so it's an obstruction and resource
manager
so what is the time sharing of os what
is the space sharing of os is there any
examples so time sharing means that we
share the executing power such as CPU
logic processor GPU by many users
at the same time
for space sharing we share for example
we shared memory space the hard disk Ram
database by many different users
at the same size
or what is a trap instruction what is a
trap instruction
so trapping construction will also call
it a software interrupt right the
interrupt has Hardware Interruption of
software interrupts so how do I
interrupt for example if you a power of
the machines that that is a hard that is
a hard interrupt the traffic instruction
is a softly well interrupt
okay it's a software interrupt it's it's
such to have occurred once some
exceptions or um occurs like a process
accessor memory address space outside
its address space so it will result a
trap like you catch the exceptions right
this is a example of the travel
instruction
so a trap instruction usually resulting
a switch from the user mode to color
modes the wireless operating system
performs some actions before running
control to the original process
returning the control to the original
process
what is the user mode use amount means
that our original process they have the
they are managing that mode they are
um
you can work flexibility in this mode
but for the kernels you need to give the
control to the OS so OS can use some
libraries to handle that at least the
kernel mode so I users alone uh
very uh so I'll authorize the user
process cannot change anything in the OS
code this is not permitted for the OS
that is why OS set a user mode and
kernel mode
so what I interrupts so interrupts is
sometimes generated by the hardware so
Hardware interrupts actually have the
software interrupt and the hardware
interrupts okay so when we it's it's
very easy to to confuse between the
interrupt and the trap so trap
interrupts you can think of that chop is
just a special case in the interrupt
okay
so interrupts something generated by the
hardware
um like IO uh hard disk graphic card IO
Port they are asynchronized they do not
happen at pretty well places in user
mode or passive since the interrupt
Handler has to wait for them to happen
eventually
well do not use no need to memorize the
exactly words of trying to trying to
understand the highlighted the
highlighted Parts okay
try to understand a highlighted part so
and what is a CPU pipeline it's a
technical that implements as a form of
power rhythms called instruction level
power rhythms okay what is the
instruction level remember that we have
the um
oh sorry my my voice kind of uh changed
uh it is we have several like tiny
components right when we talk about the
pipeline components we have the um that
is the in structure level in structure
level power isms okay in the code
execution components right and uh so
it's therefore allows faster CPU
throughputs so why we use pipeline
because if you use pipeline
if we do not have a pipeline
eventually at one time at one time you
we can just run one instructions that's
one instruction for one program is it's
not efficient so since CPU have
multiple coins and each core have
multiple tiny components to do the
instruction level parallelism so that we
use the pipeline
what is virtual memory and virtual
memorial address okay these parts I
didn't I didn't talk about that in the
introduction we talk about a little bit
okay
so virtual memory is a feature of
operating system that allows a computer
to compensate for the shortage of the
physical memory what that means
virtual memory is not a physical memory
a physical memory is like you have 60
16 gigabytes of let's say we have 16
gigabytes of physical memory right but
for virtual memory
we can we can extend that like a
virtualize this physical memory 16
gigabytes to a very large number to a
very large member so
um
is actually is actually for example if
it's let's say it's 16 just the physical
memory right but I virtualized it to be
1600.
gigabytes of the memory another quite a
virtual memory but it is actually not
that much because the physical memory is
just this large right so the virtual
memory what what the system data it
would give a user that illusion people
use an illusion that you think that you
have this larger virtual memory but
actually it's not part of this the part
of this is actually in the disk right
they just virtualize the disk to pretend
that you have the whole memory whole
1600 gigabytes of memory this technical
we are going to talk about that in our
memory chapter okay memory chapter
so uh it's for the because we have the
shortage of physical memory so we
temporary transferring the pieces of
program data from the main memory to the
disk storage to the disk storage
so it's a matter of a memory address
used by a program called virtual address
into the physical address so any
students know that how we map the
virtual address to the physical address
we have a very famous technology
yes
page table is very good what's your name
thank you much yeah a page table so we
use a page table data structure to do
the page mapping right we do the page
mapping from mapping the physical
address sorry virtual address to a
process virtual address to the physical
address which is the actual address the
actual position in the memory
what is the I know this is also
something that we didn't talk about that
in the introduction but I posted in the
in your homework your homework should
have that too so what is inode I know
this is a very important concept or data
structure in the file system chapter
so sometimes we call it I know sometimes
we call it name node in many systems
file system if you if you
um if you are also taking the data
science courses or the like the big data
causes you might heard of map reduce
hdfs in hdfs architecture they do not
call it I know they call it a name node
but it's the same as I node okay it's
one profile data structure used to
represent a file object so it's sort of
telling who owned the fire where the
disk blocks aren't so on so it's like
the I noticed like we saved the metadata
about the file so what is matter data is
about the important thing about this
file like
a movie can be two gigabytes right
so we saw that moving your disk
another I node
will tell you where exactly this movie
is like in the disk CEO in the disk D
and where is exactly physical location
of that because in in the compute in the
OS from the oi subtraction where you
save a file a large file in a disk you
see that this this entire like the
entire file I mean let's say in the disk
C right in the C disk you see the whole
movie is there is continuous right
however
if we go from the view of the operating
system they are actually the movie two
gigabytes of movie is actually divided
into many small parts and they are they
are approached into different place of
the disk different actual place of the
disk so the
OS just give you an abstraction an
illusion that using all the whole file
is in this place
okay that is why we see the OS is a good
obstruction to transfer the ugly
Hardware into some beautiful software
okay so this let's continue about our
last Tuesday's course okay
uh so we talked about different
scattering algorithms right uh we have
we have discussed the first account
versus surf algorithms showed his job
first algorithm showed his remaining
time next though so what's the
differences between the shortest job
first and the shortest remaining time
next
what's the difference
Eric
preemptive yeah oh so which one is
preemptive which one is not
non-preemptive
uh yes
Shorty's job first is long preemptive
then what is preemptive
yes
shot his remain calm next turn uh how
they how how they work how they Works in
detail
if you have like someone who has like an
initial job that's of like 100 seconds
and then after that
99 seconds
and then you have another person
now has current it still has the current
lowest time it's like it's like
important
okay uh so let's uh rephrase it a little
bit okay if we have let's say we have
um
so for the short is the job first
um let's say we have
five jobs five jobs concurrent coming at
the same time they are arriving at the
same time so for the shortest job first
algorithm so the first thing we are
going to do is to
to to see their
to estimate their processing time right
and then we rank them in a water
or from the shortest longest right
let's say if the one two three four five
comes and then one then we see which one
is the shortest which one is the
shortest
Lifetime right
so since we do not know that they have
we have not yet running it we do not
know their processing time we just have
an estimation about their time right
so one two three four five to ensure the
job first means that we are going to
process them in a water that is the
shortest job first and then the
next one and then the next one until the
longest drop and the long preemptive
means that when we process them
we cannot change their order
so no matter how exactly the time
time they actually use
once they are submitted to the system we
are not going to take them away
right that is the shortest job first
then what's the shortest remaining time
next so short is the remaining time next
algorithm is uh
preemptive algorithms right so
we have to say still we have five jobs
comes in the system and we know who is
the shortest who is the longest we just
estimate that then we put them in the we
put them in the system but then then we
may
we may at any we may we can do like
periodically modifying it or we can do
whatever new jobs comes in we check the
remaining time of these five jobs if
there's any jobs that's longer than my
current new job then I'm going to put
the longer drops out and put my new jobs
in that is the shortest remaining time
next
okay
so we need to know how to calculate the
turnaround time
of this then let's continue with then we
talk about the round robin scheduling so
what is wrong with scheduling
we need to set a column right we need to
settle cotton
right guys we've talked Autumn what is a
cotton
yeah magician
s
like the amount of times
yes very good so it's right it's the
units that we switch between different
process right we give so the quantum is
too short then we have a lot of process
switches if it's too long then we waste
still CPU time all right for example if
if I started like one hour but I'm also
process just
finish it in 30 minutes
we set the quantum okay let me
so on the key idea of the round robin
instead like we have this right of this
so this is a quarter all right what is
it
oh
okay
so so let's okay what kind for example
is better
so we have five process okay five
process five process
this is P1 P2 P3 P4 P5
um so this these five numbers are there
processing times they are processing
times so
so here's the thing okay I'm setting
let's say I'm setting the code home
I'm setting the bottom to be one so what
we are going to do
we say P1 first right
then P1
then P2 P3 P4 P5 so after after they
each process one Quantum of Time how
much left this one left nine right this
one
so there's nothing right should already
finish right it's 0.1 right things
that's four it has 98.
right
right so this is the round one
round one
right
then what about round two
round two what we can do is the
age right
times zero so there's no this right
because it's already finished
397. so this is the round robin
algorithms so the disadvantage of the
round of sorry not this one so if I set
a column to be very large
if a surgery to be very large let's say
I said to be 15.
what will happen if I set it to be 50.
it's more like this
if I started to be 50
what is a disadvantage if I start with
right now I set it to be one okay a
reasonable value so if I set it to be 50
foreign
yes
yes so wait for 1p1 when we run P1
we spend 50 units on P1 right so we
wasted how much
40 right
we wasted 40 40 times on P1
right and if and the same as P2 P3 P4
okay but P5 will not get infected record
P5 is larger it's much larger than 50.
so our question is that a question is
that so some students ask me this
question so my question is that how
about you just keep monitoring it like
whenever it's finished let's say it's
finished let's say P1 is finished then
we immediately switch to P2 so we can
avoid the 40 minutes of the time can we
do that
to understand my question
we can do that yes then why why why OS
not doing that
why now of the OS is doing that
because it's a very very straightforward
approach right we said I can set a
I can just set a value a large value and
then and then I set it like say 50 right
I've set it as 50. then when P1 finish
that I just monitoring that of P1
finishes then I immediately shared with
P2 so I do not need to waste 40 minutes
of time so Source P2 when P2 is finished
I do not need to wait 48 minutes of time
okay
so why we not do that why now the OS is
doing that
why any students know that
why we are not doing that
yes
wasted Hardware what kind of hardware
where's the CPU why is wasting CPU
because you need to continually tracking
it right it is what kind of operation if
you're writing your code
you are going to write a
while loop to continually checking that
right it's not inefficient so it's not
an efficient to waste a lot of CPU
resources
you can see that right you're going to
continually checking that because you
want to see finish or not so you you
need to keep keep monitoring that yeah
yeah well that's that's a very good
question
but still okay still still wrong Robin
when we say round robin it's
it's it's actually the quarter is very
small the quarter in the OS is very
small it's in the narrow second scale
level seconds it may be even smaller
than that
so you are what you are saying is that
okay initially initially when we say
interrupts is happening for the io
operations right when we finish IO we
send the interrupt Health CPU finish IO
so the interrupts happens it's not that
frequencies maybe this kind of this kind
of distance this kind of distance but if
I set in the here if I start in the
quarter the round robin algorithm to be
interrupted what will happen it will be
like this
a lot of interrupts in level second
stats too much overhead too much
overhead okay so um so this is why we
not settle to very large Quantum if we
sell very large Quantum we are going to
waste a lot
CPU resources right how about we set the
column to be small
if we set it to be small
it will have a lot of process
switches right process which is conduct
switches
so priority is gathering we talk about
that priority scheduling and priorities
together means that we are going to run
the jobs according to their priority it
can be static and can do it dynamically
so we typically run when we are talking
priority we typically combine the round
robin with priority so any students know
why
why we need to combine the um
round robin with priority
Magic
why is it easier
yeah if because if we do not combine
with round Robin's think of that we have
thousands of process right thousands
hundred thousand process you are not
going to search each one a priority
number from like one to ten thousand
it's it's not reasonable right so if we
can combine with the wrong Robin we just
need to set several priority numbers and
then divide them into categories and
evenly process with process each
categories process
so another algorithms the shortest
process next shortest process next so
show this process next cool idea if we
know the shortest the the remaining
times okay
lotteries scheduling what is the long
tourist Gathering approach can anyone
make a guess what is a lottery
scheduling approach
randomized it but why we call it a
lottery no don't worry
yeah so we are going to we have the
lottery let's say tickets right we have
many winning winning tickets right then
we send it to the process then who get
it then who
who who is going to scattering first
okay okay that is the lottery approach
we can enforce priorities by allowing
more tickets for the more important
processes so what that means
what that means yeah Andrew
yeah
we can give it more tickets so how are
we going to implement study for software
engineering how are you going to
implement that algorithm
yes
yes also if we look at this picture so
what we are what we are going to do is
that
if I have one if I have 100 tickets
lottery so
um for what we can do is that if if we
just do it randomly like evenly every
process can gather tickets then what I'm
going to do is like put 25 to each to
each category right to each to each of
them then each categories process can
get the lottery
like if they are lucky and doesn't run
but if if we want to ensure the priority
Lottery approach we can do is like we
give 50 to this categories we give 30 to
these categories we give 20 to this
correct oh sorry
50 to this and then 50 to this
that is the
um how we combine the lottery approach
with the priority scattering
okay so uh next we are going to do one
thing I'm going to give you a real word
example so you um you give me one second
foreign
what's this
um
so we are going to do it in the class
okay so here's the table can you see it
you can see it right
so here's a table process and they
associate arrive times and running times
arrive times in the running times
so show the scheduling order for this
process under three policies first the
conferences serve show to the job first
round robin with the time slice Quantum
equals to one
so let's do the question one first okay
so do you guys have paper
try that try that try try it and then uh
I'll ask you to show the answer okay
so yeah so you see that shortens the job
first like we have an alarm preemption
preemption right the preemption of the
shortest job first means is the shortest
remain any job first algorithms so they
different papers have different names
for that so to avoid the confusion
especially Market that as preemption
which is preemption which is long
preemption so
oh
I'll give some hint about the first
circumference surf Okay so
so we see when we say first to come
first serve
what I need we need to do we need to see
who is first come who is first off now
who is first coming right then look at
the what I need to
to not arriving time or CPU remaining
time smooth running time
why we need to see
the arrived arrival time means like when
they arrive like I arrive at 1 pm I
arrive at 2PM time first right then if
another person arrive at 2PM then she's
next
so when first to come first the serve
what we need to take a load is that they
are arriving time right
right
so this is the CPU right at Time Zero
any process arrive
any process arrived
P1 right P1 right
P1 right
so we need to run
which process P1 right
records there's only one process arrive
right
so first to come firstly serve first to
come first to serve is long preemptive
right
so we need to run P1
until P1 finish
so what we should do how much time P1
needs
how much time P1 needs
four five right five right so we'll run
P1
now what time it is now
what time it is now
five right
atom 5 which process is running or which
process have arrived at 5.
which process have arrived
at Time 5 which process have arrived
P2 and P3 right the who is the first
first conference serve who is the first
PS3 is the first right because his his
right Horizon arriving time is 2. right
so then what do we look at what do we
look at it
how much time p31 needs to finish
how much time is it needs to finish one
so
PS3 right
and then what is time now time six
and in process coming
six
only mp2 right
right
P2 arrive at four so it's already six
six o'clock so p2o already arrived and
she's has been waiting here she has been
waiting here
right
so how much time P2 needs to process
five so it will be 2p2 right
P2
P2 one two three four five P2 right
right and then what time it is now
11.
Atomic eleven
what what we have well we have
time 11.
P4 P5
and at that this time P1 p2p3 they
already finished then who is who is
first
before is first of all he's learning at
the seven p5s arriving at eight
right and P4 how much time takes two
right
then we run p
and then the rest of I don't have paper
okay
okay so so you know how to do that right
so to do the shortest job first
non-preemption let's do the shortest job
first non-preemption I'll give you
another uh several minutes
shortage drop first
so the key idea of the shortest job
first is what
that's right
on me
I've got it back
I'm gonna put this on so
um yeah so can you assume that
um that um if that if one person ends up
at time four then another problem
darts at time four or would that process
start at time five
so you see one day it arrived then they
can be processed when they arrived then
they can be processed
so let's do let's do the shortest job
first Lamprey I'm Shara
so still at Time Zero at times zero
who is there who is there
at Time Zero
who is there
only P1
so who is the shortest since we only
have P1 so who is the shortest
P1 P1 is the shortest right so it's long
preemption long preemption means that so
since P1 is the shortest I put P1 in the
radical to be processed it's
non-preemptive so I have to process it
until it finished right
so so let's just finish it
P1 P1 P1 P1 P1 now what time it is
here five right
after we finish P1 now the time is five
at the time five
what we have what we have
P2 and P3 right they are waiting they
are waiting the radical they're waiting
there
how about P1 we do not have P1 anymore
right P1 is gone it's already finished
right so we have P2 and P3 now P2 and P3
showed his job first who is shortest
P3 is the shortest alright
okay further please raise the shortest
right so we run hope first history right
PS3 needs how much time one
right CPU remaining time is runs to be
running time is one so we run P3 right
and then what time it is now
after we finish piece three what time it
is now
six
right times six
why we have times six what the process
we have
pitura we only have P2
so we need to finish P2 right
so p2p2 we need a five right so it's B2
P2 P2 P2 P2 now what is time is now
11 right 11 at time eleven
we have P4 and P5 right at time 11 we
have two P four one P5 P4 and P5
so
so what goes first
before I because P4 is
some short shorter
than P5
right so we have P4
P4 and then
P5 P5 P5 okay
now let's go to the shortest
this this is the most challenging one
okay shooting time first preemption
approach so show this to the remaining
timing left first algorithms let's do
that
let's do that I'll give two minutes I'll
give you two minutes
okay
you guys try that first
any student want to try yeah
we could make yeah we could like if we
knew that that office one and say called
on i o and top
third second or something then you can
actually yeah then there will be natural
difference right I mean a lot of times
first to come first server was short to
the job first
because in order for shortest time
remaining to work um
you need to understand when we check
shorted time is preemptive approach
right so whenever you think of that one
other new whenever a new process arrives
we need to check think of that whenever
a new process arrives we need to check
who is the shortest left who is the
shortest
whatever a new process comes that is the
time you check who is the shortest that
is the hints for for the solution
any student want to try this
yes
yeah you want to try
you want to go first
P1 so at time 0 we run P1
and then
a time one we run what
we want P1 as well
at the time 2 what we run
okay guys you
catch that catch that you catch that
right well we need to run P3 why we need
to run P3 because at time two P3 arrives
so we need to come we need to compare
between what
p1's remaining job with P3 we see who is
shortest now who is shortest P3 is one
right
how about P1 P1 how much P1 left
three like why is this more than three
so we need to run P3 first and then
at time three one with one
times three
still be one right because at that time
no one is arriving rewinds arriving so
we will just run P1 only P1 is there
then at time four what we run
P1
at time five what we run
0p1 right
because no job is coming
no you need here let's we need to check
here we need to have a check here I'm
sorry
P2 arrive at Time 4 right so when we
when we are running here
other four we need to combine P1 with P2
right we need to compile P1 with P2
see
right because P2 arrived at 4.
2 arrive at time four
and that at that time we have P1 and the
P2 so P1 have two left right two
remaining time left P2 will have five
remaining time left so we need to finish
P1
because P1 has shortest remaining time
right
so we finish P1
and then at times six one which two
times six
times six we do
we do P2 right
we do P2 okay we do P2 a time now it's
time seven This Time It's Time seven how
much P2 left
four or four people left and at the P at
the time seven what is coming
P4 is coming how much of the p4's
running time left
true so which we should process first
before we need to we need to run P4
right because P4 P4 is
smaller than the remaining time of P2 so
we run P4
then at the time at a time H we check
the timer is any new process is coming
any new process at time eight
P5 is coming right so water remaining
time of P5
three right threes now what the
remaining time of P4
one right so we still needs to run what
P4
after we finish P4 after we finish P4
then we come combine compare
right at this any these moments and in
this moments look seven is we need to
compare the radical water radical here
is like we have P2 P2 not finished right
P4 P5 We compare these three to C which
is shorty shorter
now that at time nine atom nine what we
have in the radical
we have P5 and P2 right but since P5
P what how much time left for P2
4 because we already use the P2 here so
we have four of P2 and we have three of
P5 so we need to run
P5 first right
thank you P2 P2 P2
okay any questions
any question
is it the same as your answer
yes
it's just a rather Mutual start I will
not design a question that confusing at
this moment but in real life you just
randomly choose it
okay
there's many deals many policy of adults
but if for the shortest job first if we
have this we have two jobs they have the
same shortest remaining time left
the most of system is just a rather many
pick one
okay
because that's when we build the systems
we want to build it in a most efficient
way so let them pick one
it's better than we adding a line of the
code to check like check their ID or
check whatever priorities since then if
it's not license written we do not do
that so okay so let's do the wrong
robbing approach okay round robin
approach
any student want to try
I'll give you two minutes for that
the quarter equals to one quarter equals
to one
I
um
I think it's mentioned that right you
see
adding to the tail of the cube
chaos
okay so here the new process added to
the head of the queue and the new sorry
it is a round robin for round robin is
adding a hat sorry a hat
yeah I didn't know how of the queue I
didn't the height of the queue
we're adding it to the height of the
queue
for round rubbing we're adding the to
the height of the cube
so it's adding to the head of the QR
code new process is adding to the head
of the queue
so any student want to try
and you still don't want to try
foreign
[Music]
we start with P1
we still have P1 because at time one no
one is coming right
so we do P3 first of course
P1 is used up with quarter mode and P3
is at the height of the queue so we go
start from the P3
we still switch to P1 it has two
two items in the queue right P3 and P1
and then at the time four
P2 P2 arriving right so P2 arriving at
and we're adding to the head of the
cute right so we do
P2
right
now watch the water of that
in the in the queue it's P2 right
it's P2 and then
peace P series already finished okay and
then P1
so what we do
P1
okay so how much of the P1 left one
right we still have one about how much
for the P2
P2 of four right so right now we have P1
P2 right now at the time six any items
left coming
seven
people comes in right so we need adding
P4 to the head of the queue so we need
to run
P4
and then P5 comes in right
so what the items in the queue in in the
in the wrong Robin queue
we have
P5 added P4 added
it was already finished
pick one right
okay so after P5 what we do
P1
right because we have P1 P4 P5 they are
all in the queue right
and then
P2
P1 already finished that right now that
P1 will rather finish
that then we have
P4 right
before
and then
we have five P5 okay now note that we
already finished P4 right
we also finish P1 right
right and we finished P2
right
no no we did that we didn't finish P2 we
finished P3
P3 already finished now we have what P5
and P2 right so we have P5 and P2 right
so we are going to P5 P2 P5 P2 right
one two three four five three right
right
okay
okay then the next question is that uh
so calculating so calculating the Q wait
time QA time for each process the Q wait
time for each process
Q wait time for each four sets of each
approach the QA time
Q wait time
Q weight time
of each calculates the Q wait time
of each process for each approach so
let's let's just use f first
circumference the surface example okay
so the Q wait time okay the QA time is
the total time spending in the queue
okay all the time in which the task is
not running so if it is not running if
it is waiting then that's the QA time
because so let's take a look at
first circumfers the self approach
so how water QA time of the P1
what's the QA time of the P1
0 0 1 P1 arriving at a time of zero
and it starts running it's all
the moment it arrives the moment we push
it in the queue to scheduling it so we
have been running P1 so the QA time of
P1 is zero
write it zero
no way there's no wait time right how
then how about P2 P2 arrive at time four
let's arrive at the time four right
time four
when do you start P4 a P2 in the first
Conference of approach
six right six
so what the QA time so QA time is for P1
means that zero right so how about P2
P2 is starting at the sixth is arriving
at four so what the QA time
what a QA time
it T2 arrive at six oh sorry arrive at
four the arriving time is four P two is
scheduled to play to run at time six
then the wait time of P2 is
two yeah six minus four equals to two
right so it's two
but you know how to calculate that right
P2
is arriving at the four it's starting
running see you start running at a
time six
this is time six we start running P2
how about P3 P3
water P series wait time
why is P3 arrived
two why is P3 got scheduled
five so P series waiting time is
three five minus two equals to three
right the how about P4 what is the QA
time of P4
why is P4 got scheduled
11 right
why is arriving seven right so what the
time
four right
so how about five P five it's arrived at
eight
it's we start running after searching
so the time Gap is 13 minus a is equals
to five right
right that is the Q a time there each QA
time so
the same as the shortest job first of
algorithm Rises because we have this
exactly the same scattering order
right so they have the same QA time then
how about the shortest job first shorten
the job first the short is the job first
what is the QA time of P1
for the shortest job first so what is
the what's the QA time of P1
is one right because it's waiting here
right P3 guide is water so P1 needs to
wait PS3 finish so it's how much time it
wait one right it's weight One units so
the total time is
one right so let's let's take out to P2
P2
P2 arriving at arriving at four right
four
so here
so P P2 P2 arrive at what time
are 4 right out of four so one is got
scheduled at six
right
P2 schedule and six so first before it's
start running its weights two two slots
right where it's two slots and then
and then
it's a little tricky okay and then you
see
this much of the space one two three
four five
one two three four five
six
after p p two start running
we have to push it in the way waiting
queue in the radical back right then we
schedule P4 P5 first so P2 has been
waiting for another five slots right
then it's finished so it's two plus five
is a seven
that is for the shortest shortest drop
first show you the job first the QA time
of P2
it's a seven
P2 is 7. now let's look at the P3
what is the P series waiting time
in the shortest job first so what is the
PS3 is waiting time
zero right zero because it's arrived at
two survival 2 is finished at the three
is it is immediately in process it so
there's no waiting P3 the waiting time
means waiting on its total times and
waiting in the queue total times for all
the time in which the task is not
running
so P3 0 right P3 is zero
P3 is zero this is P2 P3 P30 the how
about P4
P4
is also zero right
right because it's arriving at seven
it's arriving at a seven
it's short it's the shortest so it will
finish at a middle process it unfinished
so P4 is also zero how about P5
P5
P5 is one right because it's we it's
arrived at Ace we schedule it end up at
9 and we have been scheduled no waiting
in the middle no waiting in the middle
so we need to calculate your time
before it is scheduled and also the time
in the middle how much time in the
middle is for example like P2 it has
been waiting for another five units then
until the rest of the P2 is scheduled
that is why we need to two plus five but
for the P5 is just one okay but that is
the
all right
this is the minimum maximum I can guard
okay
um so um for the rest of that you you
guys calculate by yourself okay the
round robin okay it is it's not that
difficult okay so for example let's
let's take a look at that
the round robin for for the P1 how much
time to wait how much time to wait
everyone is waiting I did here it's got
interrupted so it's this and then this
and then this right so one two three
four five waiting for five right the
same as the others you can just
calculate that
foreign
okay so let me see if I can
help you get that
what
oh sorry
uh so you guys can can take a photo
about the approach if you have not done
that then you can calculate that uh
after the class okay
oh wait
and this is the second
okay
so uh
the last thing about this chapter is the
uh philosophy
philosophy problem okay
where is it
dining philosophy problem okay so let's
look at what it is
uh okay it's a it's a very classic
problem it's very classic problem and uh
so um
so here's the thing okay we have five
pastas see we have five pastas and we
have five we have five uh
folks we have five folks all right so um
here we have five philosophies
philosophies so at
one time one one each froze fee take the
lunch
it needs to get the right and the left
Focus together then it can take to eat
the pasta
okay so it's for example
um
so one is here one is here one's here a
person is here person is here so
it needs to take
it needs to it needs to get
left and right folks then you can start
taking the parts that saw uh at what is
the maximum number of fields if you that
can
eat the past time at the same time
so well
so you need to write a system to ensure
this happens properly you need to ensure
that happens properly which means like
uh
one each philosophy is the pasta it can
get the right
and left folks together then you start
to eat after you finish they need to
release the left fork and the Right Fork
and then the others can take that can
take that you want you do not want to
have the situation like everyone get the
right folks the noun can start it right
you do not want that happen right so
um the writer write a code to ensure
that so you you can use some form mutex
to do that
so uh think of that how how are we going
so this is a long solution called means
that this solution is it's just it's not
good it's because uh the race condition
but it can give you the flow of that
right we have
um philosophies right and then we have a
while loop they think right they think
right sink
you take the left take the left take the
right and then eat that and then release
put back to the to the table okay pull
back to the table
and then
you see this is the uh
okay
you understand the problem right you
understand problem
now how are we going to use some formula
text to solve that
okay I'll quickly go over the solution
because I think your project two should
have a similar problem okay
so where were you what we are going to
do is that we and why eating when you
eating that you eating that you actually
see we have the mutex see how they
settle mutex enter the critical region
right under the critical region exists
in a critical region so whenever
whenever you take the forks you need to
enter the critical region because
what is the sharing between philosophies
the Fox right the foxes sharing
between philosophies take a look at that
the picture
what is the sharing between different
different
why is power Stars why is fast as let's
say we just have five philosophies right
each day have their own Pasta Pasta is
not sharing
Fox is what is sharing right
this fox is shared by these two right
same as these foxes share by these two
these two so while you are sharing when
you touch one different process once you
touch the same share the valuables it
means it's entered into the critical
region so that is why when we see the
solution
say that right you you enter you you
enter the you another click see see this
see this right we see the test code okay
you release
see you Saturday eating you release this
okay you release let's say what we
release you release the meal tax okay
you enter the you enter Dash take try to
acquire see this test or 12 2 Fox right
it's not what you are a girl the pasta
pasta is something not sharing the
sister
resource that is sharing between
philosophies philosophy is a process
right so whenever you try to Accra to
Fox you need to end the critical region
take that take that and then after you
finish the food you release it all right
see that see that and then see how they
set them some form okay
okay so this is today's class
um
thank you