released this week last week we will
also have one assignments
released I believe today or tomorrow so
for for the first projection of first
assignments
um you have one week to finish and you
need to do it individually so do not
copy
your classmates or others answers if for
the especially for the homework
assignments I hope that you can you you
are free to use any resources
like in the website Google it but you
need to you need to mention that where
you got this answer and write down your
own understanding okay if we find out
that
um you write down the exactly the same
answers
with your classmates or with some open
source answers that we know then you you
may you may be risk at receiving no
points for that answer so I hope we are
clear about that
um
and for the projects that we store are
same lure you you cannot
collaborate with anyone in the classroom
to finish their projects it needs to be
done individually
and my greater I ask my graders to use
some progress on software well to check
so if I found out that
um
I I will talk to you and so for my
previous experiments like every class
that I have
almost every class there are around like
10 more with more students who actually
didn't pass and it's not because they
are
not smart oh it's not because they are
not hard working and the most of them
didn't pass because they
they cheat okay so you are supposed to
finish it individually even you didn't
do it grades we have many ways to help
you improve your grade
okay but it's it's not good to copy the
answers from anywhere else okay
so starting from this week we are going
to move to the our
uh each chapter of the textbook I have
the textbook Solutions but I cannot
unfortunately I cannot upload it in the
canvas and then I'll share it with you
because there's some copyright problem
you have to buy the book to get a
solution menu so I give I give the
solution menu to my ta so if you have
any for example when you read the
textbook and you have you will not know
some uh questions answers so feel free
to uh ping my ta will come to the TA
hours and then we we can share that with
you okay
okay so uh so starting this week we are
going to learn process and threat
so the most Central Concept in any
operating system is process a process is
an abstraction of a running program
everything everything else is just a
strong this concept
well you can think of that
um process is
so everything
in the OS if they needs to run then they
have to run it with the process okay so
it's an abstraction of a running program
so um
so for example if you're writing some
code let's say it's like a plus b plus C
you give a value and then be a value and
see a value and you find out the answer
of a plus b plus C this is just a
program only when you loaded that in
memory and start running that then that
programs become
process okay so let's take a look at
what exactly is a process
so process is an instance of program
it has registers variables and a program
counter
it has a program inputs output and the
states
okay so and
so first is an instance of a program so
let's go through that together okay so
what is a program program is just your
code you write in some code so this is
the code and then with registers
variables and program counters so what's
that
what is that
registers valuables or program counters
so uh so here's the concept of process
okay process
so firstly you need to understand the
process it's not just code it is a
running program it's a running program
but to to make a program run in your
computer
you first need to load that into the
memory right you need to load that into
the memory
so let's see this is a memory this is
memory and we discussed starting our
introduction memory for every process
for every program when it's when we load
that into the memory we allocate
each program uh
independent or just space to them so
Independence
are just paste you can think of that
this is the location of where they
should be where they should reside in
the memory so this is memory
we have memory memory is divided into
many pieces and we call this is pages
okay let's say we give these pages to
this process so we loaded that the
program into the memory right into the
memory and then who are going to access
to it who are going to access it our
computational components of the
operating system right who are the
computational components CPU is the
computational components
recipe with our compilation components
so it has several
several a very small tiny computation
units like we decodes the we decode the
code right we executed that right and
then we talk about pipeline in our
introduction so CPU is going to load
that going to
going to run it then when you when CPU
is running the process if you CPU has
some less ACP CPU is a computational
components right it has some this is the
computational components and also CPU
has some
caches like we call it a register
register so it has the register
program counter program counter is
actually a special register so when CPU
is running this program will load that
into the memory right it's still that it
is still there we have a lot of years
executed so to excuse the program if you
if you take the compiler course or you
might be familiar with that so we need
to load that right they have some code
like junk right the jump
all right they loaded that taken that
and read that into the register and also
the program counter going to read this
code
so a process will include a process or
includes
is everything okay this everything
everything so this together we call it a
process that's why process
includes the
program with the registers with the
program counters and with its valuables
so it has some valuables
and also it has
inputs
and outputs
do not eat things in the class okay
okay
let's uh
so let's continue so we have the inputs
and outputs okay
so what else what else
state
so what is state
any student know what is state
uh is actually different this is what we
are going to learn we are going to learn
it's actually different but it's it is
slightly closed okay so States
you can think of that
um
so this is a running running process
right this is running process but it
cannot always run
it cannot always runs why because
we we know that CPU is let's say let's
say CPU has only one coin so CPU can
only run one program at a time right so
you cannot always run
then the state is relating to whether it
is running or whether it is not running
that is what we are going to learn later
so here you need to take away here is
that process so what anyone else we will
interview questions wanted to ask you
what is the process do not think that
process is just your program think of
that Pro you you have a program right
your program has input outputs valuables
in your code that all together with the
program and when it is running the CPU
needs to load that the memory needs we
need to load that into memory and then
CPU needs to use some registers to read
this code so everything together
we quite up we quite a
process okay
so the second thing is about
multi-programming this is very easy to
understand so multi-programming means
that
we have we have at one time we have
many importers running in on top of OS
if if you look at this picture this
picture
this is the first picture is the
um
how we how we see uh the pro the four
programs in memory so we can see that
here the memory is large right
the memory is very large right
then we can see that each you can see
each program they have there
Independence address phase right you can
see that so and then
and then how the pro how the context
switch happens
so we have the program counter program
program countries of register inside of
the CPU so CPU using the program counter
to design
which line of the code to read which
line of the code to read so they switch
for this program process and then the
second one the third one then the first
one and then they switch there's there's
many scheduling algorithms relating to
that we are going to learn that in later
slides but here the takeaway here is
that you see if you see this
we can see that
this is a space sharing approach
difference process they are concurrent
running on top of the OS and they are
inside of the memory at the same time at
the same time now let's talk let's take
a look at C okay the slice C
so how the CPU is gathering
between these four program how
distributes scheduling before between
this so this is why I say that
if we just for the rest of the this book
okay we only seen CPU with just one coin
CPU we do not think it's a like multiple
coins CPU we do not think of that it
also consists of GPU now it's just a CPU
with one coin okay
so you see this view what I did as the
time goes as time goes by you see he
kept owning around one program at a time
right one program one process at a time
at this time it runs a and then switch
to another time it runs B and runs C and
run stick
so and you still don't know like
CPU is using this kind of sequence to
run different program why we have a
feeling why we do not why
we can still when we are using
when we are using our laptop we we still
have the feeling that they are
concurrent running like we I can easily
open up 10 office right and 10
of what office documents right I can
easily open 10 and when I open this turn
I can easily write them together and I
can listen to music I can watch video
I'm gonna run many I do not have the
feeling that the CPU is switching
between this do you know why
why why we have no feeling that that CPU
is switching is running one program at
one time yes
yes
each each of the time slides is in the
order of level seconds it's not many
seconds it's not it's not many seconds
it's not seconds it's the nanoseconds
it's in the nanoseconds so it happens
very very fast so um we remember that
when we purchase when you are going to I
do not know who have experiments with
building a game PC when you're building
a game PC you always think of okay I
want a very high speed CPU right so that
is the speed this high speed is really
into this relating to this how they can
do the contact switch okay
so this is the concept of the
multi-programming
uh
so
so operating system needs some way to
create process in very simple system or
in system design for running only one
single application it may be possible to
have one all the processes that were
ever leaded to present one system comes
up so what happens for the process
creation
um
when we when we here
when we create a process one will put
the system right when you boost the
system
so what is the process
that is the first loaded in memory when
you put OS
there's a boot process right there's a
boot process
you may have data experiments like you
know when it happens for the blue screen
right so you always find out so where is
the how it is loaded
right you can you can brush some
interrupts interrupts single to the
hardware the hardware pick it up it lets
you to choose how to load this OS
so that is the one system initialization
or process will be created
and what else
a process can be also created by a
running process okay by a running
process
for example a parent process can create
a child process during trans you are
going to use that in your in your
projects
a user request to create a new process a
user request to create support for new
process that is an interactive command
an initialization or batch job
so there are many examples of a process
creation
um
so how to terminate a process so process
can be terminated here the takeaway is
that process can be terminated in our
volunteer way or land voluntary in
warranty array so Loma exists or Arrow
exists they are all volunteer
you you catch up by exception this is
still a volunteer
right but if it is something like
segmentation forward and then it is
existed then there is in warranty okay
it's or it's killed by another process
for example we found out the system is
stuck so we just brush some
um commands to interrupt it right then
that is the key by another process
okay so now it comes to a first key
Concept in the process chapter is the
process States
so um
so process has in this different
textbooks have differences so
um explanations for these process States
I I see that one textbook saying that
there's five states another textbook
saying that the four states uh this type
of textbooks saying that there's only
three states
and for modern operating systems May uh
have I believe is five states but these
three states are the
um most important states of a process
the other the other two actual States
they are just the new added States but
they are related to these three states
so you need what you need to remember is
this three states so let's take a look
at what these three stages and how they
transfer between each other so here this
concept this picture I hope everyone can
memorize it
even you cannot understand it for now
but you need to memorize it we are going
to test that in the exam this is very
important okay so the process States
we have three states running blocked and
ready so let's look at this the first
one running what is the running States
when our processes
run in the it is in the running stage
right
so the challenging here is that the
differences between block States and the
ready States and the ready States
so what is the ready stage
ready stage ready stage is
is some process that is runable is ready
to run it's ready to run
however however it is not his turn to
run yet
CPU has not yet scheduling it later I
will draw a picture to show that okay so
that is the ready States ready States
means that this process
okay to discuss that let's first uh
let's re remember again what is the
what is the process process is a running
program right and it has
input outputs the code and it also has
the register value the variables
and it says right so
what is this means that the process has
everything available it has its inputs
available it has its code available
everything is already loaded at in the
memory
what he's missing what he's missing the
process just do not yes has the CPU turn
Okay so that is means it's in the ready
stage
what is the block space what is the
block States
block States means that this process is
not really as it has it needs to wait
it is unable to run these two weights
until some external events happens which
is usually a for example example of that
when we are um
example is that while a process is
waiting for Io input IO inputs let's say
it's waiting for users interactive
operation of input sum operation like
brush the keyboard so the process can
run then it is in a block state
so um
let's take a look at this okay
okay this is a CPU this is your
computational components okay there's a
queue inside of CPU there's a queue
okay the queue will actually saying the
queue the queue is the process process
are in the queue okay and then
there's a process running okay
so the row means that CPU is switching
switching the water order between this
process let's say this is P1 P2 P3 P4 P5
p
there's some four
okay
okay let's look at this
here we have let's say we have six
this is your CPU okay this is your CPU
okay we have one two three four five six
we have six programs are conclude
running and we call it a process right
we call it a process now they are in the
running stage right there in the running
stage they can come running now CPU is
doing the part multi-programming
multi-programming tool do some time
sharing between this process like each
process can get some level seconds to
run
the CPU is switching because if you can
only run one process at one time so it's
let's say switch to this is switch to
that the next time switch to this next
time but they'll still
they are all in the running state so
that is the running stage
now here p7 joins the system p7 joins
systems unfortunately unfortunately
CPU can only can only hold
six process at one time counts can hold
six process so what about p7 will do p7
will go Will Wait into the queue okay it
will comes to here it will wait to the
queue it will wait here
p7
p8 P9 P10
they are waiting here
but they have their inputs
data
outputs they have everything available
they just need CPU scheduling order then
they can start to run and so they are in
which states they are in ready States
right there in the ready States
can they come can they switch from the
ready states to running States
yes they can right they can why why they
can because why we know CPU is doing a
fair sharing Fair sharing so like if
let's say CPU is doing some short is the
remaining time left scattering algorithm
and the CPU is find out okay P1
P1 still has a lot of time left but the
p7 needs to needs to be quickly finished
so it will start scheduling p7 to
replace p1's slots
so there's many algorithms can do that
okay like for example first circumfers
in right
let's say P1 finish P1 already finished
now it's turned to p7 so ready states
can go to the running space ready states
can easily go to the running stage when
it is history Reddit states can go to
the running stage but it's running stage
able to go to the ready stage
yes it it is right
one for example one any of this running
process they use up their available
slots once CPU already spends a lot of
time on them and it's not their turn
anymore so what happens
they are going to be put back they are
going to be put back into the weight
into the queue into the queue until
anything happens okay and then the what
so it's easy it's very easy to
understand the running stage and the
ready States we can just say right
CPU can hold just a six program at one
time so far if we have 10 programs at
least four programs will be in the right
States sixth program will be in the
running status so always like that then
what about block States
and what about block States
block state
so I hope you can single it for a while
block State okay block state
block the states okay block state
so why we still need block States
by why we didn't suppose this it's like
I'm a driver I'm a driver I like drive
my car I'm always driving the road and
then
one eye one when I see a green light I
drive when I see a red light then I stop
but I'm ready to drive for like I'm
always ready to drive
but why why is those block stays single
of that example right I'm driving the
car in the road yeah
yes the car broke you use up your oil
the car broke the car has some problems
you cannot you are not ready you cannot
run
so you are in the block States that's
the same thing happens in this in in
here process white process has a block
State why process has proxies because
for example a very easy example is that
they are waiting for some inputs they
are waiting for some inputs the impulse
is from is not in the memory the input
needs to come from a let's say a USB a
new inserted USB
from a user user needs to input that the
user is waiting for that the program is
waiting for that so
what will happen we cannot put it
let's say
P2 is this one is this process it's
needs to
after it runs on five minutes in the
program the program says that okay you
need to wait to use those inputs until
the users inputs give the inputs like if
the inputs over the a then you can start
running again so we are going to put P2
if that happens it's like the car use up
all the oil
you have some problems so you can't have
some problems then we put that into the
blog post okay there's a pool there's
port in this review there's Pro there we
put that process in this blocked state
what
here
this is not working you cannot hear me
I I I'll make it closer
is that is that better
okay
it's okay okay so it is in a block state
so we see that it is in the block today
we put that into some block four
okay we put that bro poor
so the running stays can
come to the block States
but is it is it okay to directly put the
block states to the running States
no okay no it's it's it is impossible so
why it is impossible because every
single of that this is not that easy to
understand right
um
it's like your car have some problem
your car you can't use up all the oil so
you need to get some gas and then return
back to the road so same thing comes
into here if the if the process is
pushed into block States
even the process is ready to run it
needs to we need to insert that into the
queue first so it's the ending if after
the block stays if it's ready to run it
needs to go to the
ready States it needs to go to the ready
States now my question is that why so we
know that the running State can go to
the block State block State cannot go
directly to the running State block
States needs to go to the United States
first and go to the
run uh running States right it goes to
block ready running so why we cannot
switch between the ready States tool
boxes
yes
yes yes the the not exactly I'm sorry
the process okay why what we think of
that what is a block State block space
means that I am got blocked I need to I
need to
I'm interrupt right I'm interrupt I need
to get some single to bring me back to
bring me back so
does Os or owning take a look up
the the process running here the running
here the process running here to see if
anyone needs to go to the block States
but the process will not check
will not check the process in the queue
because there will be too much
the queue the program in the queue they
are not running they're not running so
the OS will not check them
think of that so why so that is why we
cannot go from United States to the
block stays okay
so let's take a look at this pic
um
let's take a look at this picture again
see we have three that states right
so running States and ready States
can easily switch between each other
but for running States needs to when it
is blocked this needs to go to the ready
stage first and then goes back to the uh
to the running state
so trans transition one so from ready
states to work states happens when the
operating system discovered that a
process cannot continue right now for
example it needs an input however
there's no input
so that is why running can come from the
Block States
transition 2 and 3 2 scene 2 and 3 are
caused by the process scheduler CPU
scheduler
a CPU scheduler is a part of low
printing systems
so it's it designs some Gathering
algorithms for Earth to best use the CPU
resources so it's all the time sharing
algorithms
um so let's take a look at the
implementation of the process so process
um
the lowest level of the process
structural operating system handled the
interruptions Gathering so above the the
layer are the sequential sequential
process so this is the implementation of
the this is you can think of this is the
architecture of the your CPU okay CPU
scheduling mechanisms so we have a
scheduler and we have many process
running on top of it so the lowest level
means something under the scheduler they
are handling the interrupts and they are
handling the interrupts
how we handle the interrupts we learned
that in our introduction section
how we handle the interrupt when
interrupt happens
um
foreign
so interrupt interrupt we need to we
need to
we need to go from the uh use some of
the kernel mode right and then all as
the CPU has an interrupt Handler right
Handler they are in they are around I
believe it's one more than 100 different
interrupted singles in the OS and there
will be 100 different interrupts
handlers
to catch up this single and then handle
that
now uh
so to implement the process so
implementation the process means that
how we going to if you are the of
software engineering how you're going to
design the OS design the OS so to
implement that implements the process
you need to Define this differential
variables and data structures different
variables and data structures
so let's start from some easy one okay
foreign
we need to have the register program
counter program States word this word
means like it's running stage ready
state rock States right the program
program counter the program counter
means it's a right it's it's another
register it's just saying
how many lines of the code we have run
so far right saved this word like this
and the stack pointer process States
priority what is the priority of the
process process ID parents what is the
parent process ID process group ID the
singles
two-time use chosen CPU time time of the
next alarm
okay so my question is that why we need
to save that CPU time chosen CPU time
time of the next why we need the CPU
time used why we need that why we need
that
why we need to to have that
yes
we want to know how much time the CPU
used
to
to ensure
to run the process in a
so this is used for multi-programming
right
multi-programming because CPU needs to
support multiple process to run so it's
this needs to save the information about
how much time each of the process uses
so far of the my CPUs my CPU resources
but then why CPU needs to save these
resources
if we cannot if if there's no data
structure to save these resources what
will happen
what will happen yeah
yeah you can you cannot make it fair so
the fair here's the thing this is a
tricky word so we have we have many
process let's say we have 10 process I I
have 100 CPU slots it does not mean
everyone needs to get a 10 it does not
mean everyone needs to get 10.
like because some process are not very
high priority process remember when you
run your um you have the experiments
when you open the world uh you you type
something right there's always a demon
process that just runs the back the rest
of the back they are going to doing what
they are going to do checkpointing
they're going to save but it's not safe
every minute you can find out it saves
almost like it depends on how you set it
up if you do not set anything more about
like 5 to 10 minutes right this is save
the current copy your copy you so while
you mistakenly close that you can still
restore that but for that process the
demon process they are actually in a
very low priority
place so they may not get in love CPU
time
here's the example means that is why we
need the CPU time used we also need a
priority right this is easy see this
these two these two are actually working
together
they are ensuring that the process which
is the most important critical one to
get the most of the resource
that is how we implement the process
there
every data structure is designed for a
reason they are not they are not
they are not just simply designed it
okay they are for a reason okay
I will look at this
what is that
the process also needs to maintain the
data structure to save the space of
memory management the pointer to the tax
segments info the pointer to the data
segments import the pointer to the stack
segments info
what is the tax data and the stack
healing it is
here this is a process right when you
loaded that process into the memory into
memory
you put the order variables inputs
outputs the states everything and the
registered program countries everything
and
the priority CPU use you have all these
data structures they are all loaded into
the memory
is why you need a very large memory for
that they're all loaded in your memory
but they are not mixed together they are
not mixed texts together OS is not that
stupid what OS did is that Os or divide
the process data
here
the OS
are going to also did
this is not good
and I say this is your code right this
is your code we're writing a lot of code
so when osc from the O has point of view
we will so I saw a push all the data
together
all the data together
or the texts together
like I wouldn't say that just the code
right your code will command data means
when you're writing a program you set
the valuables the global valuables the
local valuables you write you you give
you have a lot of variables this is like
your inputs you set all all the
variables so the data is there tax code
is there and you have the stack stack is
like during the process is running you
may allocate some memory resources or
delocate some memory resources there all
happens in the stack so what will happen
is that
one process are loaded into the memory
one process is loaded into the memory
we are going to get some
spaces for each of the segments and we
call the segmentation okay we'll call
the segmentation that is why this
process needs to maintain the pointer
for all this
for all these
contacts otherwise the process will
never know
will never know
where it is
there's something tricky here but why
I'm asking questions why the process
needs to save this information
why the process needs to save this
information
why the process data structure needs to
save this information
because the process needs to do the
context switch later so in these two
store this information otherwise the OS
will never know where you were you are
right you are talking to someone
in the morning while you're talking to
the same one at the night you are not
going to talking to to to her start from
the very beginning you are going to pick
up where it is that the same thing
happens in the process process needs to
the OS needs to enable the process to
memorize where they are where they what
is your current state
before the before
scheduling and after the scattering
so this is exactly exactly what happens
when OS processor interrupts okay on OS
process interrupts
so the hardware Stacks the program
counter the hardware loads the new
program counter from the interrupt
Vector the summary number language for
procedure save the registered submarine
language procedure set up the new stack
C interrupts the service runs a schedule
decide which process to run next see
procedure return to the summary code and
summary language procedure startup the
new current process
so to memorize it that is not easy to
understand this is from your textbook
there's a picture there's a picture
together with this in the textbook in
the in the chapter one and also the
chapter the chapter two they all have
the very similar picture uh so are you
trying to understand that I suggest you
to take a look out of this picture
there's no need to
to hard memorize this okay what is that
means
so it's actually very very very easy
just uh we have
so what happens for the process right
for the interrupt what happens for the
interrupt there's two modes lines in the
user mode one is in the current normals
right so let's say I'm running here
this is in memory okay in memory in
memory this is the memory
so my code my process
I'm loading my process here my program
is here
there is in the user mode and then
they also interrupts happen they also
interrupts are happening happening one
interrupts happening
the CPU going to memorize where it is is
if it's the 9 100 so it's memorizing
okay this is the 9 100. we have these
states okay the process the variables
everything everything we say feed in the
process the data structure of the
process right priority the CPU time use
they have everything available and then
and then
we gave the scheduler we gave the
schedule to the CPU so CPU is going to
find out where the interrupts Handler is
so how to find out it is it goes from
user mode to Kernel mode and to find out
to find out the process
the interrupts Handler let's say the
interrupt Handler is running here
is running here so it's going to find
out the Handler after it's and then
handled code run this code run this code
run the handle code I've already
finished so it goes back so this is how
the interruption interrupts works
so this is in the memory this is
actually what happens exactly in the
memory inside of the memory there's
always a special address space
we do not allow anyone to goes into that
is the kernel kernels the OS code okay
that is where we put the active OS code
in that part of the address space this
is in the kernel modes in the kernel so
you interrupt Handler is there interrupt
handle is here
okay okay
okay
okay so let's take a look at this this
yeah yes
we did we didn't discuss that to use
some of the kernel modes we discussed
that in the uh our introduction section
yeah it's still I've already upload my
slides I will also upload the lecture
notes later okay uh so let's look at
this this is a
so how do multi-program performs
um is ask you is asking so it asks you
how to calculate the CPU utilization is
how to calculate the CPU utilization
when multiple programs runs in the
memory multiple program
let's say okay
um
so degrees of multiple programming means
that how many how many processes that
there are many processes that there
let's look at let's just look at one
okay before we're looking at the meaning
we look at we start from the very
beginning let's see there's only one
process if there's only one process
running in our OS and it has
80 percentage of the i o weights I what
is IO weight what is ioh
what is it I always
yes
very good very good so I always means
that uh
the CPU is the CPU is
the process is in the block stays the
speed the process is waiting for some IO
inputs like inputs and it's it's not
using the CPU
it's not using the CPU remember that in
the when we are in the block States it's
not in the running state so it's it is
not using the CPU so one a process has
80 percentage of the i o weights means
that the process has all most of the
time is waiting for the io for example
the printer is not working the printer
is waiting for the PDF to be ready okay
it's like it's same thing like this the
process is is waiting it's just hands
there waiting for this waiting for Io
waiting for some users inputs
so the superior utilization
Superior utilization
in that case
is 13 percentage why because 80
percentage of time you are waiting you
do nothing you do not need you are in
the blog State you do nothing
and now if it is the 50 percentage then
that is one
minus 15 percentage times with the
recipient is 50 percentage okay if it is
20 of your IO makes I always means that
the CPU is always running so the CPU
utilization is 80 percentage now this is
this is
um this is easy to understand let's look
at this
let's look as wonders if there are two
programs there are two programs there
are two programs okay two problems then
if we we are using this formula okay we
are using this formula with one minus
this and this is twenty eighty
percentage of I always right so it's 0.8
Square okay Square
so it will be
36 percentage right
so why why because why why does a CPU
utilization is increasing
um
because one person we have two process
one process each of them has 80
percentage of time of I always when one
CPU is one process a is waiting for his
i o the process 2 may need the CPU so
CPU can help process too same thing one
process two is waiting on the iOS CPU
can also process
a so CPU kind of become more busy busier
than than the first situation okay
so my question is that the same thing
like this if in the in the extreme case
in the extreme case if we have
if you have 10 process if we have 10
process
10 process then the CPU utilization will
increase a lot right even even in the 10
process each of them just
slightly runs like this pens or 80
percentage time of I always but what if
a process
um or if I have two process okay my
question is that if I have two process
the first process have 80 percentage of
I always
um
foreign
calculate that
my question is that I have two process
process one has 80 percentage of IO
waste process 2 has 50 percentage of I
always one will be the CPU utilization
in that case average Super utilization
in that case
how much
you have
80 percentage another is 50 percentage
so a
is
CPU utilization is 100 a choice B CPU
reset engine is 50 percentage
choices CPU utilization is 20 percentage
okay 20 distribute is
60 percentage
e is 40 percentage
f is zero
what will be the answer okay
I will wait
this is the
what's the spiritualization
we still use this we still just use this
formula right we still use this formula
right
okay so this comes to the uh
surround okay Suraj
so go this
foreign
structure as the process but however
there's
um one key difference is that there's
one key difference is that
um
is more lightweight however from the
data structure point of view there's
very important differences between the
thread and the process the stressing
process
so any student knows that
so if we
anyone want to try
but you heard of thread right
you heard of that right but what is the
difference
process
that's right
it's very it's very lightweight right
and we we have the feeling that it is
lightweight it's easy to create easy to
delete
it's very lightweight but what the key
difference is that
they actually thread has a very similar
data structures process if we look at
the OS code they have very similar but
what's the differences
the key difference is is that the key
difference is with starch
if the thrust is a process
is strong if these slots several threads
they are belonging to the same process
then they they are going to share the
address space of that process
and then
what will happen if they share the
process the address space what will
happen
that is why we say process is very
lightweighted then the contact switch is
very easy the contact switch is very
easy it costs very less overhead and
let's see why it is okay
I like the process they have the same
space like running stage ready stage
block stays have this have their own
Stacks same as process okay they have
their own Stacks they have their own
data
they have their own inputs they have
their own tax they are called
the same as process
so if
if this is your memory okay
so uh
a key a differences of my course from
other uh professors course for the OS is
that this is also the same as like the
um
so in this textbook they actually
emphasizes a lot on the CPU and memory
and especially memory because
everything actually happens in the
library
everything that happens happening in the
memory
if you understand the memory understand
the memory data structure and the CPU
data structure you almost understand the
whole OS why we when we talking about
memory you are going to learn a lot of
algorithms data structures and the
design decisions then when you're going
to learn the file system you you can you
can you you can feel like very surprised
they are almost exactly the same they
are almost exactly the same
they're slightly different they're
slightly different because these are
much larger the memory but one day when
OS designed the memory data structures
very similar to file system so what are
most important in the OS Crossing this
OS course this process and memory they
are the ultimate ultimates
importance then memory is the
abstraction for the hardware of the ram
right RAM and the process is the
abstraction forward for CPU okay for CPU
and for the process when we are talking
about process we say in the process
and stress okay stress stress are very
much lighter weights they are very
lightweight but you need to understand
why we say it's lightweight
why you say this lightweight when we add
one process when we are creating process
we allocate the address space for the
process right but if the process if
process creates multiple strengths these
threads are going to share they are not
going to be in anyone else they are
there they are they are inside of the
process the same they are going to share
the same address space together so when
you switch when you switch from one
process one stress to another thread if
they are belonging to the same process
only if they belonging to the same
process
you do not lead to ask the CPU register
to do the very complicated scenes like
take down the numbers take down the
program counter take on the Knights of
the code take down your data take down
the states because everything is the
same you just need to
to a easy switch is happening there this
is why we call stress is lightweight
so they have their owns that they have
all their own Stacks oh what's the
difference between stack and a hip
what's the difference between a stack
and a hip
yes
I couldn't hear you very clearly
um
why why they are or why why is this okay
let's look at this yeah
this is a memory right this is your
memory
this is your memory let's say we have
two process P1 and P2
so what happens what are going to happen
if you switch from P1 to P2
what happens you remember the process we
learned at the very beginning of this
class the process what is the processor
running program what is process include
contains
variable register problem counters right
and the inputs outputs States code right
everything data is in there right when
you are switching from process one to
process two
so who is doing the switching
CPU is doing that CPU is doing that
right so CPU how CPU doing that
what's inside of the CPU in architecture
course we learned that it was inside of
CPU yes
[Music]
what's inside of a CPU CPU has what's
inside so you just have two things to
come
computational computational components
right there's a lot of decoding code
components execute components they're
running together doing some pipeline
using some pipeline to run this
they are they are taking the Beats like
right you learn that in your company
course you take they taking the Beats
doing some xor
computation rise or and write different
computations right and xor
or
this is a computational component and
what else register right CPU has a lot
of registers hundreds of registers
so when you do this contact switching
who do who did the contact switch CPU
did the contact switch right so how CPU
this contact switch it needs to memorize
everything inside of
P1 why you might need to memorize that
right
so how should people memorize that
most of you memorize that it needs to it
needs to load the information here load
the information here in the
help save it save for it save it into
its registers right registers and then
some information needs to load needs to
save in the memory some information
needs to save in the register and then
and then it's not loaded the new
information about P2
then do the contact switch right
after P2 finishes it needs to read the
information in the previous register and
then goes back to P1 so it can finish
this switch but if if it is happens in
this
in the process in the stress if this if
stress let's say a process
he she creates many
threats she creates many threads then
they are going to share the same address
space
space the one we are doing the contact
switch when we are doing the contact
switch CPU does not need to memorize
everything
about this because they shared address
space they have many things in common
so when CPU do this contact switch is
easier
you think of that you you flying from
the California to Florida how much
distance is if you're flying from the
San Jose to Santa Claus how much
difference is
that's the same thing here
okay
say again
how
E4 difference were
different process have different data
right they are still stored in different
places in the memory
so CPU has the registers to take down
this and you process have the data
structure to store this information
so let's let's continue okay so what's
the difference between stack and hip
stuck on the hip
here we say the stack
and the Heap
so in in the C plus plus course for c c
cos you
um
there is still C chords right
you still learn zero so he understacked
so what is the hip
what difference between hip and stuck so
stack is used for static memory
allocation and the hip is for dynamic
memory allocation right
so if I'm creating an array now I know
the size of the array then that will be
the inner step but if I I didn't know
the size of the array in
I have no writing calls for many years
but I still remember when I write the
code right there's some um
vectors or hash tables that are you they
can dynamically
allocated that you do not need to
specify how large it is
especially in the Java code you do not
need to specify how large it is right
you can dynamically allocate the memory
so that is you how they are used they're
using the hip and the hip and the stack
their indifference
Memorial address
so how Strat works so if you look at
this this comment they are very similar
to
very similar to the process okay
so as Grace wrong exists just join the
yield okay
we are not going to talk too much about
that because I'm asking my ITI to to to
to release the projects about this so
you are going to practice that in your
projects like
um
almost every on the first of all second
project about the um textbook about the
OS textbook they are using the piece
rats okay
um we are going to do that too so we are
going to practice that
um
different commands another day
so to understand the differences between
joy and a year okay the crazy existing
these are easy I understand right but
what is the drawing what is the yield
okay what is draw on the year is this is
not that easy but you need to know how
to do that okay
then how the process communicates with
each other is we're using the IPC in the
process communication
in the process communication why we need
to do that why we need process
communicates why we need forces
communicates
why we need IPC
because we want to make sure that each
other do not get in
two or more process do not get in each
other's way we want to for example put
two process in
let's say two people in you are trying
to get the airplane tickets at the same
time
what will happen
only one can get it the other cannot get
it right if there's only one seat
available
right but how how this happens in the OS
how OS
guarantees that
always guarantees that
this is a very important concept about
that we need to ensure that if there's
many forces they are trying to get some
same share some share variable they want
to change some shared variables we need
to ensure that
there's no misunderstanding between them
so why there's a misunderstanding why
there is a misunderstanding let's take a
look at a real life example
when you're in the team
this cookie represents
Disco
these cookies
uh well
I think there's a projector
issues
there's actually a very very interesting
example in of the race condition is a
real world example it's in my slides so
it's in the YouTube
um
using a YouTube or
unfortunately there's no way to see that
oh
it's like it's it's there you you can
take a look at it I think it's very
interesting so I'm going to use another
example of the of the race Condition
it's still real life example
it's still a real life example
um
so um we have we have a bank account
we have a bank account
we have a bank wait let's say a
um
husband and wife are sharing account oh
husband and wife they are sharing
accounts they are sharing our bank
accounts uh
this is they are sharing bank accounts
this is their their sharing these bank
accounts okay they are this is shared
um so the wife is always earning the
money
so I'm going to
this is a wife
what's up so she's earning the money so
she's always
food surmounting into them into it into
this shell accounts so every time it's
like 100 200 100
so husband is taking the money out
okay so what he's doing is that he's
taking 100 200.
100 whatever there's some money they
were going to take it out
so this is how it happens okay they are
sharing the accounts
so
so if if no re what is race condition
I'll tell you this is the example this
is just a very uh simple example why the
they also raise condition okay
let's say the first time
the wife earns some money or the a the
shadow comes is the a okay a equals to
zero then a becomes like 100 right come
100 and then if the husband's Deport
restore the money after the wife
then the a becomes zero again right same
thing is here a comma 200.
and then husbands
get the money out which become zero
so
if they are doing this one by one if
they are doing this one by one they are
agree some order
they algorithm order the accounts will
be fine the accounts will be fine the
console will not be broken they will not
get some penalty from the bank
but the real reality the
reality is that we know that what
husbands knows that the wife is always
our money and puts the money into the
bank and so he's
he just assumed that he she will she
will do that let's say
every day sure did that every day so
sure and the husbands will
get the money out or get the money out
but in the case in the case in the case
they also let's say there's
something happens in that slice say wife
and one day for girl to put some money
into the accounts the husbands is still
his his
withdraw a lot of money out
and they do not they do whatever they
are doing that they do not let each
other's know like the husband will not
ask the wife or have you earned enough
money into our bank
can I take it out he will not he will
they will not have a shared comments
what they did that what they did
husbands only knows I would take the
money out every day because she was
doing that every day but
but in the at one at one let's say one
day Wife puts on forgets to put in love
money in the accounts but she didn't let
her husband knows the husbands believe
that since they are still their minds in
so he got it out
that if that happens we call its race
condition happens the bank account comes
will be broken they will there will be
some penalty now
this this this happens this happens it's
just a real life example but
but whatever this happens in the OS in
OS you know as let's say we have
still the same example okay
let's say this is a shared variable this
is a shared variable this is a shared
variable let's say the variable is a we
know multiple process
we know multiple process
they are changing the value they are
changing the value simultaneously
they'll change the values simultaneously
and whenever whenever they do it
this you need to understand based on the
architecture or combiner knowledge okay
one p one one p one
one P1 change the value what will happen
it needs to there's several operations
there are several operations the first
is that it needs to read the current
value of a and then change the value of
a
then returns back so there's several
operations if we go to the compiler code
there's at least three operations just
changing
changing the a changing the value of a
there's at least three very tiny CPU
operations to change the value of a
let's from the zero to one
the same thing happens to P2 if P2 needs
to change some the value of a it needs
to read the current value of a right it
needs to read the current value of a
let's say P2 is read the current copy of
a
a equals to one and then let's say P2 is
doing adding two so it's changed to 2.
for this is also taking three at least
three operations same for P3 P4 P5
so why or what is exactly race condition
risk condition means that if they are
they want to changing the value at the
same time however CPU needs to
scheduling between this scheduling
between this
what it is let's say they're all adding
one for the a okay they were adding one
for the tape a for 10 times for 10 times
so they are doing this concurrently if
if if the CPU works fine we will get a
value of a equals to
15 equals to 15 but the the thing is
that if we run it 100 times at least one
time there's a race condition happens
what is raise condition risk happening
happens one
a is changing the P1 is changing the
value of a changing the value of a but
before before a P1 has exactly finished
this so it's these three components
three Atomic operations to finish
changing the value of a but just before
is actually changing the a the J is
still zero holding after is finished the
third operation it can change back to
one but before a is equal to Z1
CPU scheduling the order from P1 to P2
from P1 to P2 now when P2 reads it when
P2 reads the a it will not see a equals
to 1. it will still see a
equals to zero
it will not have a chance to see a
equals to 1 because 1 8 8 p 1 has not
yet change it then CPU is already
scheduling the time slot to P2 so P2 is
reading A's value and it didn't change
it so P2 change it to a equals to 1 then
context which happens
P2 goes back to P1 P1 change it to one
then if that happens at the last time we
get the value of a equals to 49 equals
to 49.
why this happens because race condition
happens while race condition happens
because they these operations are not
Atomic and the cpu's scheduling is very
fast so
in the textbooks there are some
explanation of what exactly race
condition is very long it's very long
but it does this is the misunderstanding
the when the CPU scheduling the CPU
scheduling order is unpredictable
once we are doing the context switch the
scheduling is unpredictable
so contact switch happens in the time
for each of each of this process finish
is atomic operation then raise condition
will happen raise condition will happen
um
in our next class we are going to uh
see this problem again okay so this is
today's class thank you and please
remember to do your assignments and do
your project