or six PhD students and many Master's
students or you can find out in my
website all my all of my PhD students
and Master's students they all go to the
best software companies I will tell you
uh what are they the Microsoft Google
Mata
I think uh yeah another PhD student
become a faculty member in another
California University so and I have been
interned in
a lot of
um having internet I can tell you I've
been internally in VMware IBM twice
Microsoft once and uh uh what else
yeah I've been interned in this
companies and I know what what they want
I I understand what they want in the day
I hope that why I hope that my course
can help you prepare well prepared for
you to enter the workplace workplace in
the future
so if you just want to have a good grade
or if you just want to learn the same
thing as the other for professors teach
so you you should not take my course
because I will tell you it's different
the syllabus is different than the other
professors operating system course
for example in my OS course I will spend
many times making a lot of time on the
memory and file systems and I will tell
you why you know the big data right big
data is very hot
Big Data Systems there are many good Big
Data Systems like the very long time ago
the map reduce systems right working on
a batch data and then later we designed
what the stream processing systems we
have graph stream processing systems
events stream processing system micro
batch stream processing systems one of
it is very famous called spark streaming
and the CEOs of the spark streaming
later create the company which is very
famous data brick
so you know all these systems this data
analytics systems they are running on
top of the or a data storage systems and
the key idea of the data storage system
is distributed file systems if you do
not know file system how do you
understand the distributed file systems
and you know how many workplace
positions are about the Big Data
professionals related positions they are
a large number of it right that is why
in this course I put the chapter of file
systems in in it
okay uh
so if because I I also received several
emails about that querying about that if
if you just want to
like learn the previous OS course then
feel free to drop this one and take
another professors and because every
Professor have different styles what I
teach is is that what I think is very
important to my students
and the truth comes out like all of my
own students they all get very good jobs
they do not go into like very small tiny
companies they all go to like good
companies and
they do uh my first prg students is now
a research scientist in the Mata and
he's in the data processing group
uh I'll tell you like they we he's not
graduate from very high ranked
University but he is not the one who's
who's lay off by by the company he has
been going through too late of that list
but he survives because in his PhD he's
he's been working with me and uh
learning a lot of data processing expert
experimental system details okay that is
how I designed this course and how I
design my projects in your projects too
you are going to you are going to learn
my produce and you are going to code
your own mapreduce I think it's very
interesting okay this is about my course
and my style
um
so in um
okay and another thing is that about
your grade I know I know my course is
very different than the other professors
course so you may not have a lot of
materials to refer to that is why in the
syllabus I mentioned that my course are
going to be curved right the final your
final grades are going to be curved I
try to give at least half of the
students in my course a okay that is my
goal because I want I want everyone that
who who is willing to put efforts into
the course I want you all of you guys to
succeed okay I do not want to hurt you
okay so um in order to vary I think what
you learn in this course well
definitely benefits you in the future
okay
uh
so uh let's I finally find out how to
get this working okay let's let's take a
look out of a real life example to see
what is a race condition okay
yeah peace cookie right okay
[Music]
this cookie represents a shared variable
of four cookies
one and then I'll have three
okay well I need some cookies oh
fantastic I need two
hey Jason that cookie looks good hey any
more yeah um I've got three three left
over
or do you what what happened
zero
good good
peace
cookie represents a shared variable of
four cookies
oh great there's four cookies here I'm
gonna take one and then I'll have three
okay well I need some cookies oh
fantastic
two great
hey Jason that cookie looks good hey got
any more yeah um I've got three three
left over
oh Lord do you what what happened
there's zero
good okay
uh so this is your textbook textbooks
example so let's look at that
this is a support directory so it's a
you can think of is a printer's queue a
queue of the printer queue of the
printer Okay so
so if if you want printer print a file
you enter the file named in this in this
specific spoiler directory
and the printer process are going to
productively check if they are filed to
be printed and if they are it print them
and then removed remove their names from
the directory remove their names from
the directory so when race condition
happens
um
always condition happens I'll give you
some time to think about that okay I
will tell you
so we have the process a okay process a
who is continually
and process B
they are their A and B
are going to are going to change the
value okay change the value and there it
is
always some new files got in
okay whatever whenever
whatever you see you see there's
you see there's a file then you print it
out and changed the value of the in
means that the ink means that what is
the current position okay the Out means
that what is the print position okay
take a look at that I will tell you that
when race condition happens is that
um
waste condition happens a process a and
process B are going to be way there
forever
there will be no there will be no files
print out
think of that why that happened okay why
did that happen so give give you some
time to think of it
foreign
students want to try
yeah yeah
oh okay so uh
this is the share uh let me
let's make a question uh easy easy
this is your your printer this is your
printer
right so we we have we have the fire
continuous goes in and I find and the
printer are going to check
to check the file to check the file
what a file comes out okay
so so the the case is that if there's
only one process if there's only one
process
if there's only one process
working on this printer working on this
printer like
change this value like continually
insert the insert the new files or get
all the old files if there's only one
process
it will work well it will work good
perfectly however if there's more than
one process
more than one process P1 P2 P3
if they are continually
continually working on this working on
this printer for example when P1 is
inserting the files P2 are also
inserting the file P3 P4 if there are
more than one if they are more than one
process
are working on this
the race condition will happen so my
question is that
you do not need to understand right now
what is exactly race condition but
what I tell you is that race condition
will happen and if that happens the bad
thing will happen what is the bad thing
bad thing is that
at least one of the process are going to
wait here forever they will not get any
turn okay let's say p if at first P1
p2's P3 they are they are working in
order to import the files into that
to let the printer to print out their
their files
okay
the One race condition happens
if if race condition happens it may
happens once in 100 1000 times if it
happens at least
one or two of the process are going to
be waited here forever
the the bad situation will happen and my
question is that why my question is why
yeah yes
um no no not exactly no this is um
not quite relevance then there are yeah
yes very good very good yeah
yeah okay very good I will combine you
guys two answers Okay so
here the one p one one P1 is trying to
impose a file let's say P1 is trying to
import a file into seven
just
one P1 you're trying to import a file
into seven let's say
is p1's file okay p1's file
p1's file
so if in the best case what will happen
when P1 inputs the seven right in
position seven
the seven
the ying
should plus one write the in the point
of in should be equal to two sorry equal
to eight right
right
so so here's what happened okay when P1
input my file into the seven so for this
first operation is the first operation
is that
I import
P1 dot C
in
seven right and the second operation is
one
I adding
in
adding in of one value okay so in should
be equals to eight and then
the third operation is that in
conforming in equals to eight okay
confirming in equals to eight so
so if if it works if it works normally
what will happen is when P1 trying to
insert the file into that here one two
three one two three should happen should
finish and it should finish
after one two three finish then P2 has a
chance
to insert his file his file then P2 will
import the file
into this the Precision H right position
H then P2
plus C and then in equals to nine that
that should happen right this is the
normal condition normal condition
however however
however if we run this process if we do
not allow this P1 p2p3 communicate each
other if we do not put any protection
mechanisms onto these shared variables
they are all aware of each other's
operation and
what will happen is that when P P1 is
doing the operation of inputs P1 dot C
into the slots 7 in plus plus and E
equals to eight these three operations
these three operations this is very
tricky okay
in ending this is not or not
not
atomic
operation
this one two three this operation are
not atomical operation and what will
happen
contact context which happens in here
P1 do not have time to change
to change the ins value to be A's
between at these moments at this moment
contact switch happens
the cpu's Gathering is gathering
scattering is com computation components
to P2 sub to P2
so this is p1's wheel View
and then we have p2's View
so P1
we switch to P2
at that time when P2 sees this see this
variable
when P2 sees this variable in
is not equals to A's okay in steel
equals to seven
in still equals to seven
because P2 has P1 has to does not have a
chance to finish all this operation CPU
already is gathering the
computation components to P2
then
what would be the p p two subbu in
equals to 7 right E equals to 7 then
inputs
P2 the C in
position
seven
okay P2 will put this puts the file into
the position seven so position seven
or have two values we'll have two values
it's P1 dot C and p2.c but two P2 does c
are going to overwrite the value of P1
dot C
so it will be P two dot C
p 2. c okay so here and then
say it's finished okay in plus plus and
then in
equals to eight okay now
now the scheduling order comes back to
P1 okay
scheduling scheduling order come back to
P1 now rp1 will see P1 go pick pick up
where it is
P1 will pick up where it is it's going
to
is going to
do this okay do this because it because
because it's left over at this position
okay
so it will do this okay then
but however it will never get is is file
back okay it will never get it's back
file back you're not going to use this
operation and then runs this operation
runs this operation
okay
so P1 are going to lose his file losing
his file and the P1
then what will happen is that in your
textbooks there's actually uh several or
several Solutions of that row P1 but in
the textbook there's a P1 just the way
there because it's waiting for the its
people it's its own file but it will
never get hit
okay because P2 overwrite this file
okay so this is this happens very rarely
why this happens because
these three operations these three
operations when you change are valuable
when you're trying to change your shared
variable you need to read this Value
First in change this value and then
commit commit to the changes so these
three operations are very tiny
operations they are not Atomic
operations while all s is that they are
not Atomic corporations if if contact
switch happens during this operation
then unexpected
unexpected
results will happen so that is the data
races okay
foreign
so how to avoid the raises how to avoid
the races so we have the mutual
exclusion we only allow one process at a
time can use a shared valuable on file
okay only one process at time can use a
shared variable as a file
so the key to prevent trouble here is in
many situations involving the like share
memory shared files shell objects when
you are sharing anything with more than
one process then you need to have some
protection mechanisms okay so this
what we are going to do is that we are
going to put the parts of the shared
memory
to be something we call the critical
region critical region and then we for
that specific region we ensure some
mechanisms called Mutual exclusion so we
allow only one process at a time can can
use that shared variable so in the real
life example what will happen is that we
are going to have a
you can think of that we are not going
to put the cookie
in a public position we are going to put
the cookie in our ATM machine if we put
the cookie in the ATM machine every time
you
like the machine that you gather your
water your water right every time you
got the cookie right then the cookies
numbers are going to be changed and
everyone can see that
so if you put a cookie in some like a
log give a box or ATM machine
it can protect it that's the same thing
okay
so uh
so a property of a good solution is that
it should ensure or Mutual exclusion
and there should be no assumption about
the speed or the number of CPUs there
should be no any assumption about that
um
none of the process outside the critical
region can block other process and
there's no starvation no process Waits
forever to enter the critical region
okay
so let's look at this example so these
two let's say two process okay we only
have two process
process one and process two
it's a process a enter the critical
region and then leave the critical
region one process a is enter the
critical region and
change the variable here
process B
can trying to can trying to continually
try to enter in this critical region
but of course as B is not allowed to
enter it because process a has not yet
leave it okay and you should not assume
like they are processing speed there's
no assumption about their processing
speed
and after a finish then B enter into
that okay
so you you are the software engineering
okay so how to implement that how to
implement that write some code to
implement that
you can do that it's very simple
you won't try
um you write some code like what kind of
code
they're they're all trying to changing a
value of the variable of a right what
we're going to do
we yes
um you you only need to write several
lines of code to do that what kind of
code look it looks like
I want I want to have some someone to
speak about the pseudo code
you
yeah
very good what kind of vlog
no no we do not talk about mutex let's
let's forget anything about mutex some
of them let's forget about that okay
very good while loop so we use a while
loop we create a integer let's say uh
well a Boolean okay we're saying that oh
this is a lock this only have two values
true or false okay whatever whenever
some process is like a lock this lock
this lock equals to
it has a is inside of the while loop
okay
so let's look at this how it is looks
like
it looks like this okay looks like this
we have a wire Loop okay
okay
this is the trend this is Trend okay we
have let's say we have process a and
process B we
ever
we are going to whenever a entries into
that b are going to
continually checking it okay checking
that the lock what whether the lock
is released okay when a entering into
that it's
push the lock on right a under the
critical region then a puts a lock and
if a leaves the critical region then a
release the lock that is how how it
works this is the release lock okay
look at this code
so we first we first we first give each
process let's say we only have two
process a and a b okay
now while
turn not equals to zero is going to be
wait forever so you see this code it's
going to be waiting forever
right wait forever when turned equals to
zero
then that means it is process a string
so process a goes into the critical
region process a goes to the critical
region
if process I finish the critical region
things change back to the log to be one
okay and so does B okay b one b
what B is doing is that is continue
checking if it's Houston if this equals
to 1 if not then B is going to wait here
forever
wait here forever
but if if the turn equals to one if a
release the code a release the code then
it means is speech turn where process B
string so B can enter the critical
region
after you finish after you finish then
release the lock
okay so this is a solution this is the
software this is a very straightforward
simple solution for to implement a
implements the critical region for
protection for two process
to process
now what will be the problem of that
what will be the problem
the problem is that one
this this lines of code you can try that
um
after you finish this course you can uh
at home you can write some while loop
and while you write oh
um and run the while loop operation then
you see the CPU utilization we will
consistency periodation becoming
extremely high like to 80 or 90
percentage so it's a waste of CPU
resources but then okay let's forget
about the let's forget about the the
limitation
another limitation about that is that
this solution can only work for two
process right two process what if you
have three process
what you are going to do
oh you're going yeah
um yeah
yes very good so I can if there's three
process I can I can make it to be 20
equals to one turn equals to 2 20 equals
to three and this is actually assigned
to each process so each process can just
checking this right you can check in
this but this has a very uh big big
limitation the big limitation is that um
so it's you you need to you need to
um to gather a limitation about this
approach you need to understand the
computer architecture so they are trying
to they are trying to this all three
process if there's unprocessed they are
going to continually changing one cache
line one question one specific cash cash
now in the cash and this costs a lot of
locking
locking overhead it caused a lot of
locking overhead it's not I will tell
you that for the system it's not it is
not
um efficients it is not efficient it
costs a lot of overhead
um
let me show you
so the solution that student is proposed
is that we instead of using uh to turn
angles to one with zero one turn
can be equals to n rise m equals to n
the n
like P1 P2 P3 PN and each of them can
just check whether it's their turn for
example when P1 release it 1p1 when P1
finishes it can it can the P1 train is
is zero it can after you release it can
add in add one right at one then it
becomes p2's order then you become P
series order and then p2pn so everyone
can get it fairly right so the the
limitation about this approach is that
you can see that they all there will be
there will be unwired Loop
there will be a while while loop here
so it will be um process
they are going to
this is the this is your memory okay
this is your memory
and since we continually using this
value so this value we're going to be
pushing to the cache so let's say this
is the cache
the cat there's
this is the word this is the Casual
which is saving the trans value
so this end process are going to be
continually changing
this value changing this value
to continue changing this value
so you know of course a lot of course a
lot of
locking overhead
it's not inefficient I'll tell you it's
not I'm telling you it's not an
efficient so so from a software
engineering point of view how are you
going to improve that how I'm going to
improve that
improve this solution
we are going to have 100 process and we
they are going to concurrently
they're going to share a variable
concurrently changing this variable so
you need to protect the valuable you
need to help them
only you you need to ensure only one
process can enter this critical region
so
a simple solution is that we we use the
value we change the variable of n but I
will tell you that it's going to from
the system architecture point of view is
going to change the same cache the same
cache line
okay it's it's not efficiency especially
if you have multiple calls if you have
module core you are basically waste all
the the rest of the coins few coins so
it's not efficient what will be our
better solution
try that you can think of it
it's called Peterson's approach so
pixels designed that is
let's maybe 40 years ago he designed
that
and then he published a paper about it
so and becomes his approach but you can
think of that it's just the easy very
easy fix very easy fix
very easy fix
so give you hints instead of instead of
continually checking the
instead of continually checking the
share the variable in one cache line you
are going to
check many
many
cache lines together the multiple
process
do not there will be no IO button like
there will be no IO Bolton lock in one
position
there will be no IO broken luck in this
so the solution is that now if no one
going to want to try I'm going to give
you the solution okay
foreign
so the solution is that Peterson's
solution so take a look at the parents
solution it's very
very straightforward very easy just one
tricky one tricky
so instead of using one variable we're
using our array
we're using our array
right instead of changing the only
variable for n to represent the logs we
using if there's unlocked and processed
then we use an arrange a ring you see
that's there
here
we are going to give
each one each one or their
Interventional log and proceeding a
brain then instead of looking at each
only one question we can check multiple
cache lines together
okay so that's more efficient however
this approach still have problem
this approach still has problem
this is Peterson's approach if you're
interested you can take a look of your
textbook okay so the the only trick here
is that we're using our ring to save the
logs instead of using one variable we're
using our array
thank you
okay this is the software approach so I
will tell you these are the this
solution is they are not good because it
this solution
still has raised condition
has raised condition where the race
condition happens is actually happens
here happens when you entering or
leaving the
um
the critical region so just to memorize
that it still has race condition
then how are we going to fix that
someone think of that or maybe we can
design some design
maybe we can design some other Solutions
like Hardware Solutions
the hardware solution
the hardware solution the hardware
solution is that
we are going to we are going to
use a lock into the register and the
okay so we are going to use a hardware
lock Hardware lock so for example when a
process is entering the critical region
we are going to use a hardware approach
to disable all the interrupts we're
going to disable all interrupts if we
disable or interrupt then none of the
other process can enter the critical
region so this can solve the problem
this this is the hardware solution can
solve the problem however it's
um it is not good for all us because now
OS has to give the very important kernel
operations the authority of Kernel
operations to the or give it to user
it's easy to get a mass okay
and then we have the solution of the um
tax sample so we are going you are going
to practice that on your project too
um
so to introduce the
to introduce the solution of some
formula text of this let's look at this
example okay this is a very very classic
very classic example of producer
customer problem you might heard of that
right
anyone
no
it's not right so uh
foreign
okay so let's look at the producer
customer problem okay
so I'll give you some time to read the
code so all the problem is that there's
a producer there's a there's a there's a
shared valuable the shared valuable and
so you can think of that it is a um
it's a box
okay please describe us what is producer
customer program
you've been talking all the class this
is not good okay you've been talking all
the class okay what is the producer
customer program
this is our tutors our tutors of this
class okay I think they have a lot of
good things to share with us
what is the producer customer problem
what
speak louder
you read producer read the
producer read the bounded buffer
okay so we have a buffer first we have a
buffer producers are going to produce
items
produce items like insert items into the
buffer
the customers are going to consume
consume the items from the buffer
so what customer one consumer did is
that it's need to check right if the
buffer is zero what it will do you're
going to sleep right because there's low
items there's no items so they cannot
take any items out what producer did is
that producers are going to check what
the powerful lesson the buffer has a
size of N and equals to 100 the producer
what the producer needs to do
yes
yeah check it for evidence forward or if
it is four producer needs to do our goes
to sleep right
okay so one producer goes to sleep who
can wake it up he cannot wait sleep
forever
try
yeah
a consumer weighted Hub when consumer
waking up consumer find out
it's not when producers sleep if if the
if if the item yes
what
if there's no space in the buffer if
there's no items in the buffer right and
if there's no no item in the bathroom
consumer cannot consume any items right
and then if the producer is still sleep
so consumer needs to wake it up to
produce the item the same thing happens
of the who are going who can wake up the
consumer if consumer is sleep consumers
see okay there's low items so I'm going
to go to sleep
s the producer the producer will produce
the first items then if it find out the
customers is in the Sleep stage so it's
going to
wake up the customer now look at this
code look at this code it has
um you can see that right
so we see we see
this is the producer the producer okay
the if the if the
buffer is for right if the
if a buffer is four it goes to sleep
if the buffer is four go to sleep right
if counts equals to one means that
there's items out so it needs to wake up
the consumer all right something
happened here consumers find out more
items about this empty goes to sleep
foreign
buffer is empty goes to sleep if not
then it's wake up the producer now I
have a question here I have a question
so here
so it's checks its checks versus checks
uh let me make it easy okay look at this
code
if the buffer is for the the producer
the one the producer did is that if the
if the buffer is full means there's no
empty slots left so producer is going to
go to sleep
why I use the code why I use the code of
equal to n why do not use the code of
like
like a greater
greater
greater than equals to n
or I should greater than M plus one
I just check the is equal to and this is
just a tricky very tricky question
anyone think of that
right why we cannot use this code
okay so saying the same the same thing
happens here why it's a lot to count one
count
what counts is why not it's just y count
is
larger and equal than one
well we can now say that the counter is
larger and equal
larger and equal to one right we can say
like larger and equal to one
larger and equals to one whatever it is
larger and equals to one you can wake up
the consumer
all right
can I write a code like that
yes
okay what are two answers
okay let's go the first okay so why why
because if we adding this we're adding
this is if from the combine or point of
view is actually two operations
okay you need to you you have a actual
operations to check it's not efficient
it's not efficient that's why you see
the taxable and taxable why this code
write this code is make it very com
efficient very efficient okay so it's
just just because of that okay it
actually if you go to the compiler code
it's actually two two operations it's
going to check two check two check equal
and check larger okay but however it
works if it works even you change my
change the code like what I propose the
code still works okay
now what will be the problem of this
code
race conditions VR happens race
condition still happens
even we write this Pro write this code
like that race condition still happens
when race condition happens
the producer will not produce anything
in the customer or not consume anything
they or both of them are wait for each
other forever both of them are going to
wait for each other forever so look take
a look at this code and tell me what
lines of the code that the race
condition happens
one line of the code the race condition
happened
you can discuss you can discuss or I'll
give several minutes
I will give you a hint okay a hint okay
so
annual this any of these lines will make
the race condition happen but let's look
at the example of just this line of code
okay this line of code but I can tell
you any lie of this code this one two
three four
any of these four lines any of these
four lines can make the raise condition
happen but let's take just take a look
at this take a look at this
risk condition happens in this line
and remember that this is actually not
Atomic operation they are not Atomic
operation
if its operation sleep is an operation
there are at least two operations where
there at least two operations they are
not Atomic and whatever is condition
happens
right
so yeah any student want to try
yes
the producer
counter equals to zero right when we see
counter customers see the counter equals
to zero
cons consumer does not have a chance to
go to sleep before consumers have goes
to sleep contacts which happens
and the producer produce an item into
that right
then what will happen is producer will
not goes to sleep
producer producer items into the buffer
cost producers since the item is the
buffer is zero right
so it's going to to what
producer produce an item is going to
wake up the customers right
way to take effects
will it take in fact
no customer has not yet goes to sleep so
you are trying to wake up a person who
is
nurture sleep so the wake up single is
lost here it's lost here
is going to be lost
it's going to be lost
you're going to be lost and then what
happened
and then the contact speech goes back to
goes back to home
to the consumer right then consumer
consumer is I was adding here I was
adding here right then consumers were
doing what what goes to sleep
so the wake up single
is released before customer goes to
sleep then what will happen customer
will never be wake up because it means
that the thing the wake up single the
wake-up single was happening here
happening here before the customer goes
to sleep
so customers are going to sleep forever
going to sleep forever and producer are
going to produce the
um items until the buffer comes full
when producer sees the buffer goes to
four producers are going to sleep
because customer already goes to sleep
no one wake up customer so both of them
are going to
going to in a sleep State forever
okay
okay so so so so we gotta
so this right the contact switching
happens here happens here happens here
right so the buffer is empty the
customer has just reached the counter to
see it's zero at that instant the
schedule CPU scheduler decides to stop
running the customer temporarily and the
contact switch to run the producer
process
the producer inserts an item in the
buffer in the buffer increase increments
the buffer to be one
and the notice that it is 1 so it's
going to wake up the customer is going
to sync to producer sync the customers
was in the Sleep States but actually not
actually not because at this time the
camera switch happens so it's going to
wake up the customer however the
customer is in the wake up state so the
wake up single are going to be dismissed
dismissed so what will happen the
customer are going to sleep goes back to
sleep stays right goes back to sleep
States and then customer going to in
sleep States waiting for another another
customers single right the produce a
single wake up single but it will not
wait it will not either not
wait why because this is the command
okay if count equals equal to one is
wake up
okay
that is why I asked a question earlier
like if we change it to be
this
if you change it to be this right it
can't avoid this situation right however
is it efficient it's not it's going to
send a lot of wake up singles right
yes
you are going to
um what
yes
yeah
so what do you want to do so it's so
this is the producer and customers
mechanisms right
it's like yes it's exactly like strict
alteration
right we I've been so it's just to check
right to check you check is if it is
four then you can sleep if if it is
empty you start producing same as the
customers if you customers see that if
it is
Amity is going to wake up the
if it is empty it's going to go to sleep
right if it is if if it is
um
right if it is empty buffer is empty
goes to sleep because there's no items
right but if the buffer is is four right
then it goes to wake up the producer so
the race condition still happening so
why because this this operation is not
Atomic operation
this operation is not Atomic operation
so what we can do is that we why not we
make them Atomic why not we make them
Atomic then that is why operating system
designed some phone and new text okay
let's look at what exactly it is
some phones are in integer variables
okay it's used to sleeping process and
the wake-up process okay
it has two operations down and up down
and up down checks sample if it's not
zero then
minus it one okay if it is zero the
producer goes to sleep up increments the
sum from if more than one processor
sleep one is chosen randomly and under
the critical region so it's Atomic
implementation Atomic implementation so
the interrupts is disabled okay this is
very tricky here so
interrupts is so we actually here
actually we actually leveraging OS help
to disable the interrupts when we
using the library of some phone and
mutex so we disabling this the
interrupts okay we are not asking user
to disable the
interlocked okay with Os or S provides
the library the OS Library code of some
formula text to program languages
program language different program
language have different implementations
of some form and new text like Java Java
have the synchronized command you may
heard of that and see they'll have their
own Library they each of them have their
own library but they are actually using
the OS code so why OS designed this code
because OS wants to provide user some
Atomic operations so help users to
protect their shared variables different
processors
can share some variables together so
someone okay it's an individual variable
here this is the takeaway
it is of integer it's integer it can be
one it can be 100 it cannot be active it
cannot be active Okay it can only
zero
more or equals zero okay there are two
operations only two operations down and
up down and up
is down operation the up operation is
that one more than one
pours us asleep wines chosen randomly to
enter the critical region okay and the
critical region
um
so let's look at the producer customer
problem solution with some functional
texts we have we have three cellophones
okay
four empty animal attacks so what is new
text mutex is a special sum phone it's
special something from so remember
someone is a integer right integer it
only has
um it can it can be
zero one two three to n very large value
but new text is a lock it's a lock it
only has two values one or zero one or
zero so it is a lock
later on our Discord I will show the
differences between mutax under some
form but let's look at let's remember
this for now
so no tax product variables which and
which contains the item produced and uh
consumer okay let's see mutex
so do not always lead to counting the
operations of something just Mutual
exclusion Parts Mutual exclusion parts
so how you're going to use the new text
so remember new text is a lock it's a
lock
is a lock so whenever
whenever process wants to enter the
critical region it will need to fetch
the mutex mutex fetch the lock fetch the
lock but somehow is you can think of
some form it suggests a value that shows
the number of shared variables shared
resources
so let's take a look at the uh
foreign
[Music]
awful
hi
in this video I will explain difference
between mutex and Sema 4. so in order to
show this difference we are going to
take one example we are taking here
toilet key example so let's assume we
are having a toilet and these three
person they want to use this toilet and
this door is locked and there is only
one key so at a time only one person can
own that key he can enter he can occupy
a toilet and once he's done he will give
this key to another person so this
scenario will work like this one
so he will go well it will be occupied
and after once he's done he will give
this P2 others so mutates also works as
same mutex are object that owned by a
chat at a time only by one thread so one
once that thread is done that thread
will release the new text
so there is a ownership in case of new
text a thread will be there if that
thread wants to access a
critical section that thread actually
has to own new text he has to lock the
mutex one it is done it will unlock the
new text now it might be possible while
this mutex object is owned by some other
thread and uh
another thread try to access that
critical section so in that case it will
return error so let's see the actual
scenario here so this is our resource
and these three object are trying to
access this resource so it can be a
simultaneous axis or it can be a
sequential axis so let's assume
This Thread one
all thread having this code they will
first lock the mutex then they will do
their work and then they will unlock the
button so third one actually start its
execution first so what this chart one
will do it will first of all log the
mutex
so let's say this resources this one is
representing a mutex object so it is
locked and this thread is having that
mutex object and it is doing its work
so we can say mutex object held by
thread one
now meanwhile thread 2 also trying to
access resources so thread 2 also will
execute the same code so thread to also
trying to occupy mutex object but that
mutex is already held by thread one so
this mutex object can be held by only
one thread at a time if another thread
try to occupy it whatever what will
happen
there will be one error so a chat two
attempt will return one error
so this is the way how mutex work mutex
is a object whenever a thread wants to
access a
resources that thread first of all
occupy the mutex object and once that
work is done it will release the object
so there is your ownership
now if we have a look on SEMA 4
so let's generalize our new text example
so now let's say we are having four
toilet and these four toilets are having
four identical keys so one key can be
used in any toilet and total person we
are having
five so here we are keeping total number
of keys available
so let's say this person wants to use
toilet facility so he will come here he
will pick one key and he will go to the
toilet so when he will pick the key the
total number of keys left are three
so same after him let's say two more
person came and they
used
these two objects so finally we are
having with one key so this variable
this variable actually specifying how
many keys are available
so at last when we are having no keys
available and If at this point of time
if this person trying to access
uh any of these toilet it will have to
wait because there is no keys available
so
variable can be used to see whether any
whether there will be a waiting or there
will be a access to the facility so Sima
for
so in case if there is no key this
person has to wait so SEMA for SEMA 4
actually used to provide how many number
of simultaneous axes can be allowed
and there is no ownership relationship
here this is actually a signaling
mechanism
so if we going to see our same example
with help of seamaphor so let's say the
sigma 4 is having a variable s and the
value of Sigma 4 is 2 so it actually
specifying how many number of thread can
simultaneously access this resource
whenever a thread tried to
access a
shared resource first
thread has to decrement value of schema
and after decrementing this value the
value is less than zero
This Thread has to fit so what this
thread will do it will decrease this
value this value become 1 and in that
case this value is not less than zero so
this axis will be allowed now let's
assume This Thread also wants to access
the source so this thread also
decrease the value of x
and after decreasing this value this
value becomes 0 and this one is not less
than zero so in that case this thread
also will be having access to resources
but now if there is another thread wants
to access that thread will come here and
this value become minus 1 after
decrementing or sorry after decreasing
so
that thread has to wait that side cannot
access this resource because a
simultaneous access only two
allowed and whenever
one of these thread is done they will
increase this value and as soon as this
value is increased the third thread
starts execution system 4 is actually a
signaling mechanism there is no
ownership here but in case of mutex
there is a ownership
so we can
same beauty mutex is a object which
owned by thread and third which is
having this muted subject he can access
that resource he can enter in the
critical action whereas in SEMA 4 Sigma
4 is a signaling signaling mechanism and
it allows how many uh maximum number of
simultaneous access can be allowed
thank you very much for watching Okay so
so here's turquoise is that full text is
has ownership has ownership okay only
has two values zero or one so it's like
a lock it's like a lock
we also we
if one person if there we have a share
of variables right and we have we have
shared variables they are in the it is
in the critical region we have multiple
threats who will process we want to
access this critical region then each of
them one before they enter into that
they need to get a what get a new text
they need to gather new text
okay because it has ownership because
only one process remember the mutual
exclusion definition only one process
can enter the critical region so we use
mutex as a log to protect the excess
protect them to access to the same
shared variable okay so remember this so
in that case in that case
in the producer customer example one
producer wants to change anything it
needs to get a change the buffer right
one producer needs to access the buffer
it's new to get a new text right because
there are there may be many producers
many many producers want to change the
buffer simultaneously so we need to each
of them needs to get a new text for the
buffer the same as the customer customer
One customer consume the items from the
buffer so also needs to get another new
text right so and what is some form okay
some form is not a lock it's a single
mechanisms remember to produce a
customer problems we have the wake up
and sleep operations rights so we use
sample whatever we need to wake up and
whenever we need the Sleep operation we
use some of them so let's look at how we
we use the new text and some form to fix
the producer customer problem
foreign
so
take a look at this that this is the
mutex right
see before you enter the critical region
you need to use some text right fashion
attacks right
same as here
yeah
this is the operation that whenever you
enter the critical region when a
customer enter the critical region when
producing under the critical region they
all each to get their own mutex
right
and then and then we have
we set up we Define n equals to 106
number of slot in the buffer and then we
have from a text Matrix just a log
controlled access to the critical region
okay and then we have two samples okay
this is one is for Amity Wines for four
why we need two sumphones because we
need to each of the sum frontal
single
difference type of process one type of
process is producer one type of process
is customer this is why we need to
search different samples
so um when Pro when the producer goes
sleep the producer goes to sleep when it
is four right when it is four
so we will see when it is four
we produce the item right producers item
and down the empty this is the mean the
empty slots empty empty slots right
right
so remember the down operation the down
operation
equal or larger than zero when it comes
zero it goes to sleep right it goes to
sleep so when Mt equals to zero means
there's no empty atoms then the producer
goes to sleep here
there's operation not not showing here
because it's Atomic operation is already
inside of it it's already inside of this
operation down down remember that let me
look at this
where where is that
some phones it has two operations down
under Opera if zero producers this this
process goes to sleep
remember that right
so now let's look at the code
so if it is zero if empty here the empty
was 100 at first but then
is going to every time it's creation new
items is going to
do your manners right when it becomes
zero it goes to sleep it's already
inside of it it's Atomic operation some
of our Atomic operation so it goes to
sleep
here uh sorry not this one not this Live
code so it's empty it goes to sleep
why needs why is when there's at least
one atom in the buffer it's going to it
is going to wake up at least one
customer right this is also Atomic
operation the wake up here the wake-up
code is inside of it inside of it look
at this call
up increments sample if more than one
processor sleep one is chosen randomly
and enter the critical region so it's
going to wake up one customer
is going to wake up one customer
same thing let's look at here
with down the four okay
down to four the four was
first so
we're going to do
if this speak if it's zero if it's zero
it's going to go to sleep it means
there's no item in the buffer so it goes
goes to sleep the customer goes to sleep
but
who always hit up this one this one
right
it will wake it up whenever there's one
item is going to wake up him
and then
if it's empty if it is empty here up M
empty if the empties value if empties
value
is
is larger than one then it's going to
wake up
it's going to wake up
producer
okay if it's find out that there's no
items here it's going to wake up
wake up the producer right
so that is the um how we use some of our
new text to solve the producer customer
problems like we said that there's a
buffer producer it's not just one
producer there are multiple producers
there are multiple customers okay they
are con they are sharing this buffer
producers are impose the item into that
customers and output the item onto that
so this is the code to help us solve the
produce a customer problem okay and we
can
avoid the race condition
uh
okay let's skip that
then another important concept with OS
is the barrier barrier so what exactly
barrier
um
so some applications can be divided into
phrases and uh
so
process was stress they may have
different speed they may have different
processing speed so battery or what we
do barrier is that
we want to ensure Ensure
they reach to the same States then start
the next processing if we want to have
this operation then we set a barrier to
do that a burial is you can think of it
that is another library of code that all
us can provide to to us
okay so this is about the race condition
let's do a very simple rehearsal then we
do the um
oh have no time left
okay
I need to I need to my ta asked me to do
some um introduction about mapreduce
because your second project will be will
be mapreduce so you are going to
practice uh process synchronization
using a map reduce example so what
exactly map reduce anyone heard of that
map reduce
foreign
[Applause]
into your canvas so
just a one minute let's Okay one minutes
so what is the map reduce okay map
produce is a divider conqueror um
conquer mastered okay or this the thing
is that if I found out something that
that you guys can do to empower
um
so the history of mapreduce is like this
I have a I do not have a very super high
performance motion I do not have that
but I have let's say this task is that I
want to combine the my word con I have a
lot of tens of thousands of work
documents I want combined convert it to
be PDF
but I do not have a super high
performance performance motion
but luckily I have many students like
you so what I'm going to do is that I'm
going to divide the my oh I'm asking my
ta to have all these documents divided
into many small batches and send each of
you to help me combine to PDF after each
of you finish that for example some of
you may do some uh one chapter of the
book right you are doing chapter a you
are doing chapter B of the same book
then after you guys all finish that I'm
going to combine the all together to
another
class another class of students I asked
them okay to find out which chapters are
from the same book then combined
together so you're doing to we're doing
the Divide first and doing the reduce
seconds that is the key idea for map
reduce okay we are going to talk about
more in our next class
so after the first project we are going
to release this second project okay so
this is today's course thank you