so here oh we know the OS what is the Os
Os has two rules right
uh the first rule is the resource
manager and the second row is
abstraction but in exam I will not test
you that simple I would say like okay if
this is a true first question ask okay
OS has two rules of abstraction or
resource manager I will not ask like
that
because you need to understand that
think of the example about what is the
abstraction what is a resource manager
okay for example how the OS allocates
the resources
like in memory right in memory address
space how the OS allocates the resources
like CPU time
right difference scheduling algorithms
they are all examples of resource
manager
right and for the obstruction so what is
abstraction
what is the example of obstruction
so for example process is an abstraction
of program this is what we have learned
right
so that is for the OS so rules over OS
hmm
give me one sec
show the computer and then we talking
about the computer architecture
um
so this is a different figure I I
intentionally remove the other like
monitor keyboards
drivers the other drivers from the
figure if you you look at the previous
slides of the introduction we have a
long picture about the pipe about the
data plan and control plan of the OS so
this is a simplified version so the
computer is a sensor just a
communication system data is constantly
being moved between the CPU memory and
the various devices
the CPU use IO address to direct data to
particular devices and the device in
turn used to interrupt mode divide CPU
and operating system of their needs so
um
so if we see that the data is transfer
right it's basically just a data
Communication System data is being
transferred moved between different
devices between this
okay
so here you need to understand what is
interrupts okay what is the interrupt
how how OS handles interrupts
what is dma so what is dma
osdmi
director my direct memory access can
anyone explain to me what is dma
director memory of the SAS so what
exactly is the Mi yes
the device does not go to the CPU and
change the memory well it's very close
so device and memory exchange the data
right without the intervention of the
CPU that is the direct memory access
that is this kind of this is one part
this is just the one type
of one type of data transfer
between CPU device and memory and the
other transfer we have
IO by pouring right and IO by interrupt
and then dma direct memory access
so you need to understand what is
interrupt
what is interrupts or is the ma
okay
so then in the introduction we're
talking about the pipeline CPU pipeline
when we talk about like
um
what is exactly the pipeline and why we
need the pipeline
right pipeline is just a
multi-programming technology that CPU
uses to improve the throughput and CPU
has
three units right fetch decode and
excuse factual instruction
decoder instruction and execute the
instruction so when we are
so you need to understand what it how to
how to pipeline how the pipeline is
executed okay
so what are the PC like IR
what are they
yes
they're very good they are what are they
they are just registered inside of the
CPU right they're just the registers
okay
what is CPU pipeline now how the CPU how
the OS handle the interrupt how do you
CPU response to the interrupt
so um
before we before we're talking about the
interrupts I want to ask you a question
there's two mode in the OS
what are they
yeah
kernel mode and user mode now you need
to understand so
once once CPU responds to the interrupt
would involves a mode change mode switch
it worked right it would then how it
happens how it happens
so let's using this example okay
so if you look at this this is an
example
so this is your user's code right so we
are in the user mode and now it's kernel
mode so
um how the interrupts happens
how to interrupt happens
it is a lot of failure yeah
call it the Trap instruction I think
[Music]
after the after okay very good so
so control we see the control plane is
is switched from the
user amount to Kernel mode right so
let's look at this code let's look at
this code
so for Corporation
so this is a this is let's say this is a
user's mode right user smart user needs
to call this function
right and then what happens
what happens
so the process runs this process find
out that
this function needs some
Priority Access and it's the kernel mode
to handle that the user mode cannot
handle this right it needs to call some
library in OS to handle that and we call
it interrupt Handler there's an
interrupt Handler too specifically
handle this so
when we run the code and the instruction
comes these lines of the code when we
have a pointer to point this line of the
code
the state and or register of values for
the process are saved are saved then we
have our chop instruction trap
instruction we go to
the interrupt Handler interrupt Handler
the CPU mode is switched to the super
like supervision mode we call it a
kernel mode and then and then the
pointer the pointer the point what is
the point the pointer is something if
you look at this the point is here right
see this is a pointer
pointer and it points to the line of the
code
right points to the line of the code
so we have a pointer here we found out
this instruction the user cannot handle
in the center interrupts to the CPU and
CPU will make a trap instruction to come
to the kernels and find out the
interruption Handler to handle this
score to handle this instruction and
then the pointer are going to point to
the
to the code in the kernel to the code in
the kernel this is not users mode code
it's not it's not written by user it's
randomized OS right then it's called
this system Fork right this is this is
the interrupt Handler
so my question is that one point points
to this is the user modes is the user's
code still running or not
they are not running right it is not
running why they are waiting for the OS
to give back the control to the user
so we go to the interrupt Handler
to handle the code
now after finish it how about we finish
it after the interrupt Vector will save
the values about like the pro previous
program counter and I asked value and
then after we send it back we are going
to retrieve the value from the previous
saved register value and goes back to
the code goes back to this so this is
the how the CPU handles the interrupts
now you need to understand it because in
the exam one we are going to testing you
is whether you can understand it or not
because I'm going I may create some very
confusing questions asks you like the
true false question like next
give some
yeah
so if you understand that then you you
know how to answer so be careful about
this okay be careful about this so uh
another question is that so Mo this is
mode switch right from the user mode to
Kernel mode so then
another switch we call it contact switch
so what's the difference is between the
mode switch and contact switch
are they the same are they the same
no if they are not the same then what's
the difference
well you need to understand like it's
every context switch always
causing a model switch or mode switch
are always causing contact switch
or in understand the differences between
these two they are quite they are
actually very confusing Concepts
okay I'll leave the answers to you so
think about that contact solution mode
switch
yeah Andrew
the Trump
the Trump table Yeah so sometimes it's
called interrupt table no need to
yeah yeah
handle the exception no while you handle
the exceptions based on how you write
your code you may have your own
exception Handler
when you write a code in the user mode
you you when you're writing a Java code
for C plus plus code you may trap the
exception right I think Java you have to
try exception right the code
if you know this code have some problem
you may you you wrap it with a try
right
oh you
what's the question is is this slide on
the canvas
it will be on Converse I will be posting
that
Okay so
okay I will be posted after the class
okay yes
no not exactly not exactly Andrew
I guess like so here
um it's clearly stated that like Fork is
a trap construction so trap instructions
are basically just any sort of
instruction which causes a like a mode
switch from user to Kernel but
what other kind of instructions
basically
like I understand like why they are trap
instructions like they just require the
kernel but like what are you you have
you'll have a homework you have a
homework question right they ask you
like could you give some examples about
the
uh
yeah yeah yes it will right caught like
a second okay that's a Soulful wild trap
right
that's different yeah that's different
that's different that is why in the
homework I I I
in the homework I ask you a question
like could you give some examples about
the
um
the interruption right is that the
homework it's some types of different
interrupts right ask you this question
right there's many types I
um it is clearly posting the correct
order like North Koreans I mean the
example solution
he's not okay I'm not going to ask a
material to post in the uh example
solution okay and then so there's many
uh
many types one time is the software like
software trap
right social life
like this right this is like oh you you
create a file you create all four
cooperation right this is a software
shop another is like
you catch up the exception the software
exception software instruction another
is the hardware hardware error something
like
um
for example we started divided by zero
that will be a hardware error because
you are you you are or segmentation
fault you are going to some other
address space that is not belonging to
you that all all of this all of this
were causing the OS to help you handle
that and you it will of course are
interrupt
it will cause the interrupts okay
okay so you need to understand see some
core differences between system core and
interrupts that's another trap here so
it's like mode mode switch contact
switch interrupts system core these
consumptions are very uh confusing right
so system core
what's the relationship between system
core and interrupt
the code they both called mode switch
very good when what the relationship why
we just call it the system quality
here
foreign
counter switch
mode switch
yeah any student can
you what do you want to say
in the process and usually it can like
call an IL
draft I think is more
so let's let's
and any student want to try this because
these concepts are really confusing even
when I read a textbook I found like
because they are everywhere but they are
sometimes they use this term some where
sometimes they use their term
right so this is what we need to learn
in from the in in in
the introduction this is some take away
here in the intro what is trap
interrupts system called Contact switch
mode switch you may know exactly how
they are what they are you may exactly
you may know that okay the Trap what is
the Trap means right what is the
interrupted means what is system core
means what is the context switch means
what is mode switch means but my
question is that do you know the
relationship between this between all
these five
to make a system call
uh the system problem
s
interrupts interrupts actually
um
consists of system core right
it actually will interrupt as the
software interrupts
and Hardware interrupts right and many
software will interrupts is just a
system core system core is that when
user write some code AS write some code
like call some functions that need
system to handle rather than we call a
system core so the interrupts
these are see some core
and system called leads what this trap
instruction right system code then leads
a sharp instruction for to do what
to do account to do a mode switch right
to more switch from
you some out to kernels
and then
what is contact switch
what is a contact switch
Andrew
well yeah
and you still don't have a different
opinion
Andrew Aaron
very good very good okay this is the
answer this is answer okay
yeah
are they uh are are these going to be
going on the actual slides when they're
published because when you do this
um
our
English
oh I have a video recorded you guys know
that the video is it you can
um
I think I take the video recorded for
every class
yeah no problem yeah thank you Sharon so
let's go back okay
when you contact switch what is contact
switch contacts which is CPU
this is superior if you want to
want to give the time recipe is running
a running process a
now CPU needs to run in process B so CPU
is saving all the all the data States
about process a into its register and
switch towards as B so in order for CPU
to do that first is need to do what
you need to do more switch right because
it cannot happen in the user mode
now this is a relationship okay
okay so now now I'll repeat that okay so
interrupt
so I will repeat that okay so in summary
in summary we know interrupts is a very
big word interrupts is a very big word
and some students mentioned that like
the concepts you have the concept yeah
yeah
that's a very good question that depends
right
let's defends any students know that
yeah and what's your name
Lily
it depends on stress in a different
process right remember that if threats
are in the same process then they
are going to share
address space
if they share the address space
there's no contact switch it's very it's
very it's very the CPU does not need to
save all these states because they are
going to share the same data structure
okay
oh now let's repeat that again okay okay
interrupts is a very big word so
interrupts means that uh
CPU is running something
she feels running something now we need
to interrupt the CPU okay say indirect
okay do something else it can be what it
can be it can be waiting for the i o it
can be waiting for the io right it can
be waiting for some
um
another another process inputs it can be
just to terminate that it can be
anything you just stop doing what you
are doing it now and doing something
else so interrupt we have the software
Interruption Hardware interrupt and
under the software interrupt system core
is one part of the software interrupts
okay and one that's super well
interrupts happens we issue a system
core system core okay system core means
large we need to call the system look at
the name we need to call the system
system is what system we need to call
the OS or S we need to call Os to help
us then when we call Os to help us that
means that we need to go from the user
mode to the kernel mode so that is the
traffic instruction that is drop
instruction and then we need to go to a
model switch to the model switch and
what contact switch
contact switch is a very special case
that CPU is switching the processing
water from one process to another
process so to do that to ensure this
happens we need to do the mode switch
because we need to go to the kernel mode
first to ensure that
contact switch can happen so now we
understand the relationship between
these two this five right so are we
clear okay this is something
switch contact switch
where do you think of contact switches
okay connect switch contact switch okay
think of that
contact switch is
a scenario it's a scenario that CPU
needs to scheduling its order processing
order from one process to another
process
okay okay so okay let's let's continue
so this is what you need to learn from
the introduction okay okay wait
was from kernel mode back to user mode
so what did it so after
the content after the contact switch
what will happen is that your question
no they are in the user process
when you approach when you are running
process a right forces a
process a is already in the user process
now contact switch means contact switch
means that we need to for some reason we
need to run give the processing give the
CPU time
to the process B
okay
okay so you need to remember okay just
remember that okay contact yeah
contact well well contacts which think
of that contacts which can we do contact
switching your most user mode
can we do that conduct switch is a part
of resource management
policy in the OS right OS has two rules
resource manager and abstraction
contacts so contact switch is OS trying
to especially see people trying to
allow cases resource right so it's in
the kernel mode right it's in the kernel
mode
Okay so
no it's not exactly that it's not
exactly I do not remember like that I'm
I'm using the the directions to help you
understand the differences between these
these five you need to understand
exactly what it means okay they are
there's not exactly a preceding or after
relationships okay this is trap what is
trap just action right season core what
is system core is just a
is it just a name of right it's like
trap is an action trap is an action and
then interrupts Interruption system core
a kind of parallel terms it's just
some some system code belongs to the
interrupt right and contact switcher
mode switch
are two different cases but there's
relationship between this yeah
yeah you can think of that yeah
okay
we talked that after class okay yeah
yeah
we have many others to think about okay
okay
yeah yeah let's talk about after the
class of Sharon okay so um
then in the introduction you also need
to know the examples of the chop
instruction system core interrupt you
need to understand the examples if you
do not know that then put that in your
checklist okay you definitely need to
know like
what kind of instructions is the Trap
instruction it's a system core
right it's open a file system called
something like that you delete a file a
system call is like click the keyboard
system core
and the same as the traffic instruction
right you understand like if I'm I'm
using the mathematical function is that
a system call or not
examples like that what kind of
examples of each like and the dma right
or what is exactly direct memory access
what is IO by Pauline what is IO by
interrupts they are all in our slides
okay so let's come to our
come to our
chapter 2 process process and threat
processor threat so first question is
that what is the process
what is the process
Andrew
then what's inside of the process
something like that then where are this
something
where are they where are they
we have
in memory
any other opinion yeah
slowly on a transfer is about what is
our dress pace
address space
is a data structure where is address
space
address space is in registers
Lily
yeah
is on the page another space
your address phase is the address in
your memory
right
okay so come back to my question well so
Andrew said that a process is just a
running program it basically has the
information about the program in the
address space into input outputs with
files
and all other information that my
question is that where are they
where are they so why you load launching
a process
when you're launching it in the CPU
well we put these data structures
some of them in the memory right
some of them in the
something okay
so this is a little cold okay A little
cold
then you combine your code
into some process let's say this is your
process in a P1
then P1
now we have the
One OS
using a data structure to represent the
process what they are using
broken up into like a few different
parts so one of them is like the
so like all the variables basically
another one I think is just like all the
third one was I think there were three
but I kind of forget yeah very good
thank you Andrew okay
so let's continue so we have the process
okay we have process so come back to my
question when OS CPU is lodging the
process launching the process we
we use the data structure to represent
the process or as you start remember
that is in our lecture in the
introduction it's in the process lecture
lecture five four
six
the process table right
any students remember we have process
table and inside of the table
there are many variables right some
variable is the process named the
priority and what
name
priority
a lot of a lot of things like date
creation date creation times it should
call time creation time and states
right States process States
and the address
space
in many other things right
many other things so my question is that
okay these are in the process table
process table data structure
so when we're launching this process or
us are going to create a data structure
to represent this process it will save
all the information about the process
into this data structure into the data
structure my question is where or as
Store Dust okay the answer is that most
of them are in a memory
we later are talking about where they
are in the memory okay and some of them
in a
some of them in the
registers yes where is the registers
in CPU right in removing our first cell
second slide we have the data structure
CPU architecture I told you there's a ir
and the PC IPC register right now you
need to you need to connect with the the
channel in most challenging part of os
course is that students find out it's
very difficult to connect all these
Concepts together but that is what we
should learn we need to connect connect
them all together in a whole picture
yes
what
yeah some some of them are in the CPU
right in the summer register right
especially even remember the IPC like
the program counter the pro sorry the
program counter the IR the program
counter now for the program counter
so that is the process that is the
process then inside of the memory we're
talking about that
inside of the memory that is the address
space especially the address space so
it's this data structure when the OS
creates a data structure for the process
it saves all the information in this
process table and then we put the other
information saved in the memory in the
memory also in memory in memory
memory is consists come memory consists
of pages Pages we are not going to test
in that but you need to know that what
we are going to test that in your final
pages one page is 4 KB the fourth of the
4 KB is a page we call it a page so the
address space will tell exactly what
page of this process is of these
processes and to ensure a very efficient
computation to manage in the process or
what OS did this Dutch he or us she was
going to put all the data together
together
so it's a tax text phase code space
and there are some hip and stack step
Haze to dynamically allocation of the
memory to that process right so it will
be there it will be there
then that is the that is the process now
to come to the threads
so if if this process creates a stress
and we call it stress one
it will be
where it is where it is
yes
in the same address space right in the
same address space that is why we say
that
stress is more lightweight
than a process that is why we say that
stress is more lightweight than a
process
we have the like the difference between
process and threat right
right
is that why it's more lightweight
threat so let's come what's the
difference between process and stress
um this is in our lectures yes
the same information
yeah very good very good so well if you
look how you remember the one we
mentioned in the lecture the textbook we
say that stress has almost the same data
structure as process right we have this
this exactly the sentence but the
difference is that only difference is
that if
if a process creates a stress and
creates several threats then the
contacts video will be no contact switch
between This Thread however however if
here is process one so his process one
is crazy stress when process 2 creates a
threat too
then if we need to conduct switch
between threads one through two
if we switch if CPU is switching from
stress one thread to
then it will be the same old head of of
switch from slash one and thread 2.
however if this if the stress there's a
stress three
threads one and three three
if they belonging to the same process if
they belonging to the same process then
there will be no contacts we we just
switched from Source one to three three
then there will be no contact switch
there will not come because they are
going to share the same address space
the CPU does not need to yeah
yeah it has but it is going to share
with the process parents process
yes right that is why the context which
does not cost much because they are
going to use the same
yeah it's IR
what's IR
there's a lot of registers but the most
important register you need to remember
is
program counter what is program counter
for this program counter yeah Andrew
yeah it's just pointed to the currency
instruction
point to the current instruction
of the code okay
so this is the process this is the
process
Okay so
oh
yeah
this is looks like an address space this
is why I told you this is an address
space you see a little process are going
to be
I'm going to use the uh the same data
structure so they did what we have a
different name but they are the same you
can think of that like this is just
inherited from that class
the process does not use what
they all have different names
they were no they were not going to use
that
if in the code they will be different it
will be different
so look at that address space this is
like address space right
so each process you will its memory as a
continuous set of logical memory address
and the operating system management
transition of logical respect to
physical address space of the computer
and we call in this we actually
mentioned that in our introduction and
we call it um
we use the page table to do that we use
the page table to do and this is the
mapping from The Logical address space
to the physical address space this is
what I go we are going to learn in our
memory chapter
now it's come to the uh
it's come to the
let's come to the process States
come to the process States
here you you need to you need to
you you need to connect the discount I
believe most of you have already
remember this stage but we are not going
to test you or start easy like ask you
to draw the picture about the stage
transition between
the three states like the running block
ready
right so so you need to using this
connecting this with something else that
we learned in the chapter for example
for example this is the status
transition right stage transition
so
how is it connected with the CPU
scheduling
in in all in in the surround process and
the third chapter when we are talking
about the states
after we're talking about the states the
state transitions we're talking about
mutexamophones and then later we're
talking about the
CPU scheduling right we'll talk about a
lot of skills Gathering algorithm we
will talk about the or system
performance Matrix another like the
batch system interactive systems
then I a whale see some something like
Dash and then we talk about the
scheduling algorithms we're talking
about the CPU queue like the radical
right spill radical and scheduling
algorithms you remember that so how it
how it's connected with them
see this is what I'm talking about this
is the ready list right ready list
and then we are talking about a lot of
algorithms if you still remember the
round robin algorithms the priority
algorithms the first Surfers to come
first come first serve algorithms
the
like shortest time sure she's a job
showed his job time algorithm showed his
remaining job time algorithms so how
these two concepts are connected to to
each other
I feel sorry about that how these two
concepts connected to each other
Lily
the transition between ready and running
very good and then by the world how
about this block how about block
how about block
let's say let's say okay let's say
okay
these three states okay so first of
first someone can help me to
finish this the transition between the
Slate the process each process can have
these three states right
can you go from ready to block
yes or no
yes
we discussion in the class right we
discussed that in the class anyone
remember why
anyone remember why
yeah what's your name
Andrew
together
uh
okay we have three Andrews that's good
okay
so okay so my question is that can we go
from ready state to the Vlog state
so if anything
it has not done anything it's in the
radical how could you block someone's
already
it's already it's not running right he's
he's staying in the in the CPU radical
it's a very long queue so data structure
is that it's not even noticed about OS
yeah
how would you ask
you after him how am I asked
no I'm not going to ask this this is too
sweet stupid I'm going to ask you a very
tricky question you will see that
I'm not going to ask because there will
be a lot of answers and I do not want to
put myself in a situation that to look
at your
your words like one word after one word
still no
you you are I have a question but if you
understand that I think it will be
well I'll make an example okay I'll help
you okay make the example okay
so think of that we have we have
different scheduling algorithms right we
have different schedule algorithms first
what is that
first come first serve
when I first come first is serve
so if I have three process if I have
three process P1 just to two process P1
and P2
what kind of states are they look going
to look at a first come first serve
first come first serve scheduling
algorithms
what what kind of stage transition looks
like a first conversation
let me make the question more concrete I
have P1 okay P1 P1 needs five
CPU time to finish P2 needs two CPU
timer to finish to spill time to finish
but I do not tell you how what is
gathering order is but I tell you now I
have the CPU scheduling order of P1 P1
P1 P1 P1 and P2 P2
so I'm asking like what will be the most
possible scheduling algorithms it looks
like
it will look like a first come first
serve right but if it is the P1 P2 P1 P2
is like they saying like I'm saying like
this is the running this is the running
running and P2 is P2 is always in the
block State block stays
and after waiting two blocks this is
starting running
so P1 is always running running running
then I will be mostly exactly looks like
a first come first serve right so this
is how you connect this is just an
example very stupid example that help
you to help you to understand the the
the concept between this Gathering
algorithms and the stage transition
the most challenging part of the OS
course is that to connecting all these
components together yes
no no you see that let's say P1 comes at
1 pm P2 at the other like one one pm2
but it's slightly later than P1 so P2
are going to be blocked for
five slots because P1 is let's say just
one nanoseconds earlier and P1 is going
to be on the
sorry
United States right
ready
right it will be in the ready States for
for five slots until P1 finish that then
use P2
okay okay then you think of that what
will be the
round robin looks like right round robin
looks like what will be the shortest job
first looks like what is the shortest
remaining job first looks like
so try to try to connect them together
now let's come to our
schedule schedule this is the attack oh
sorry this is the architecture of our
scheduler so looking at that look at
that
here
ready list we have we have been talking
that a lot of time right writing is just
radical this is the radical radical we
have the ready process we put it in
color and then we put in the ready list
and then we dispatch it now this is the
this is where you you
you connect the contact switch concepts
with the CPU scheduling algorithm
together
whenever a CPU are picking a process
picking a process that's reaching from
one process to another process
scheduling that you it's going to cause
a contact switch contact switch and then
we go to CPU and for running
right that is the structure of the CPUs
process scheduler
okay so CPU utilization you remember
when we're talking about visualization
we're talking about the formula
yes
you cannot go from ready to walk block
means that you ecpu needs to interrupt
the process
in the radical one some process it puts
it include in the radical and that means
it's ready
it means it's already ready
you cannot go back you cannot go back
okay now now after we're talking about
the process the difference is pushing
process and stress which contact switch
and scattering before we talk about
scheduling algorithm and we're talking
about
CPU utilization in the lecture we have a
formula any student remember that
I hope you do not forget okay if we if I
have a
if I have a process one
it's used it's used 15 percentage of
time to do the i o waiting
to do the eye all waiting
what is the average CPU utilization of
the system we just have only one process
the systems
that's just 50 percent
if our P1 and P2 both have 15 percentage
of the i o waiting what is the
what is a CPU utilization
what will be the CPU utilization
angel
how much
you know how to calculate that right
is one
where's this
this run
is
right
yes
what will be the answer
how much
30 50.
right
okay
okay what is the waiting time what is
the waiting hour
so we know the cpu's utilization slow
puts how to calculate our system's
throughputs
you have we have 100 jobs submitted to
the system the system needs three
seconds to process these drops then what
is throughput
is 100 divided 3 right and then 33
.3 drops per second that is the
throughput throughput means
at the time units how much you can
finish how much you can finish that's
the throughput
what is the waiting time why is the
waiting time
what is the service time
run time response time
let's just focus on this okay
waiting home to run time
the amount of time the process has to
wait to go like the rifle minus or like
time it starts minus arrival time I
believe time Stars
arrival time and uh
but what if we start running for a while
then it needs to be waited for the other
process to proceed because it's a
shortage shortest remaining job first
the algorithm is a preemptive algorithms
what if in that case yeah
uh it's very good we tell the time it's
it's been putting in the waiting queue
until it's finished we we calculate the
time we call it on time is it starts its
arrival when it's after his arrivals
okay after its arrive time we call him
the total time it has been put in the
waiting queue not just the time
before it starts but also plus the time
it's been if it is a preemptive
algorithms it is going to be put back in
the queue we're going to also calculate
that time that is the waiting time
right that is a waiting time
how about the turnaround time
how about two runtime for process
yes
the time gap between
is arrival right it's arrival then is
finished right
that's the same thing the same thing
about like
for example it's arrived as one but it's
finished at 1 15 then that will be the
15 minutes it's the turnaround time for
that process
okay
so turnaround time is time is time Gap
time gap between its arrival and
is finished
okay then what is the service Hammer
response time okay so service time means
actually it's actually running the CPU
that's a service time
structures of this time
so if you look at the waiting time plus
the service time equals to the turn
runtime and then what is the response
time that response form is partially
what is the responsive
and you still know
response is just part of the waiting
time
together
well
I don't know when to confuse you but the
takeaway here is that you need to
understand what is the queue
waiting time
and turn around time
there's another time record service time
service time means
the time is actually running the CPU
right so QA time plus the service time
equals to the turnaround time
right and then there's another time of
course the response time
with some response time means that what
it arrival it arrival at this time and
then it's just the it's it is being
pulled into the CPU to run search the
time Gap is the response time so
response time is just a part of the QA
time it's just a part of the Q a time
it's just the first the very first what
just
said that is actually the response time
okay so uh
so we have the first come first serve
scheduler let's see
this is the yanju
if a process is blocked that is the your
question is that if if a block then that
is the large surface time it's in the
waiting time Services means the CPU is
actually solving that okay so let's look
at this okay if we have a first
circumference of scheduler we have
different process right they have
different service times
you see this service time is actually
the CPU CPU running time right this is
this from this you can see that yeah
the block processes are in the waiting
time if a process is blocked then it's
all it in this level in the schedule we
are not considering this situation like
the block if it is blocked then there
will be
um a lot of diff like situation happens
but if it is blocked you should
calculating it as part of the
um
waiting time yeah
where for now you remember that it's
just the time is in the queue in the
scheduling queuing see this
here is the time in the in this in this
place
okay
so let's look at this we have this
process so it first come first the surf
let's see then we are going to have P1
P2 let's say P1 come first p2p3 P4 P5 so
they are going to see Gathering us this
order right
now if the shortest job first we have
and they arrive at the same time let's
say they arrive at the same time
then we're going to scattering based on
their their service times right
and if it is a round robin schedule we
need to set a column now my question is
that is it always to settle good a small
cotton
is it always too good to infusions to
set a small cotton and then why why not
if is it is it always good to set up a
big Cotton white and white lot
sound like
we're doing context switches right so to
be
very low Quantum yeah but if it how
about the larger quantum
larger quantum
yes
a lot of CPU CPU waste time okay a lot
of CPU waste time
yes
no actually no no for the wrong Robin
schedule why we said the wrong lobbying
schedule we want to avoid the situation
of starvation right so which algorithms
will cause starvation starvation which
algorithm
yes
first come first serve very good very
good that is the algorithm of course
starvation so what algorithm is
is to the best extent to ensure the
failures
what algorithms to the best extent to
ensure the fairness
yeah because it gives everyone a chance
to to run right
the very which kind of algorithm
minimize the average term wrong time
monjish
SRT yeah very good it's minimize the
average turnaround time right
what algorithms are going to minimize
the total
turnaround time
service time
right
uh
okay emojis
work
yeah yeah um yeah my question is
actually not quite accurate so um well I
should say that okay think of that why
we already have the shortest job time
for we already have the shortest job
time algorithms and we know that it can
minimize the original runtime right we
know that then why we still needs the
shortest remaining job time algorithms
why we need that
think of the
we might not that it might not be very
good if they if like one of them if one
of them runs while the others don't then
like basically if you if we need them
all equally then it's the better ideas
[Music]
but if if I if I if I want to make it
equally I just use the round robin right
my question is that we already have the
shortest job first why we have the
shortest remaining job first
why we need that
why we need that I need to be fast okay
the answer is that stance is that
because which is preemptive
which is non-preemptive
oh you forgot that preemptive and along
preemptive which is preemptive yes
this is preemptive right
this is preemptive
tremending means like the time it can
take away right now this shortage job
time is long preemptive right
then why we need to show to The Dropper
room show the remaining time job first
so because that's when we run the
shortest job first we found out some
some job may may have very long
sorry very long term wrong time
they have very long story service time
because we cannot predict their
processing time
we cannot exactly know where they are
when they are running some some jobs may
run very slow
so even they have like for example I
have a job I say that I only use five
minutes to finish but actually one
Nightline is in this specific
laptop is texting me an hour then it
will cause starvation of the rest of the
jobs
right it will cause the starvation of
the rest of jobs then that will
significantly increase the turnaround
time so shortly the job time is not as
efficiently as short shortest remaining
job first time because this is the
algorithm that can minimize the actual
average turnaround timer you can save
the average the term wrong time so think
of that remember that long preemptive
and preemptive
okay then we talk about the new tax and
some from inter-process communication
and synchronization so you need to
um
so you need to understand
if you read the code you you need to
know how to write that right you need to
know what is what part of the code
should be put in the critical region
what part of code you should set some
phone and mute tags to protect to
protect these shared variables okay
we have the software solution disable
interrupts new toxins some phone this is
very important
so when we are talking about this
chapter we we're talking about the
software resolution remember when we
talk about the Peterson's QR Peterson
solution we're first talking about the
the lock alternative lock solution with
a while loop
some students I think mentioned that
authorities lock with the while loop and
then we introduce the Peterson's
approach Peterson's approach instead of
using just the two logs like true or
false two locks it's using a ring of the
locks that is a Peterson's approach so
they all belonging to the software
solution and there's a hardware solution
we call it we just disabled interrupts
whenever we use one hour a process goes
to the critical region we use some
aggregate we use some special Hardware
to disabled interrupt and the
circumstances that it will it will be
very dangerous because the user user
code May destroy the system so that's
why we
designed the mutex and a sample
and we talk about the producer customer
problem so you need to understand what
is exactly producer and customer
programs we also talk about
philosophy dining problems
um think of that if I have if I have
five
if I have a 5 if I have a five let's say
if I have five philosophies so what is
the maximum number
what is the maximum number that they
can they can run concurrently
you still remember the philosophy
dieting problem
they have the frogs right
each of them have Forks
so we have five philosophies we have
Five Forks there
then when they did they have pasta in
front of them
in their face there's a pasta each
philosophy needs to
folks to eat the pasta
that is the philosophy dining problem go
back to the lectures
look at that advent philosophy dining
program so you need to understand how
how we solve that in the like at the
very beginning
like after we suffer it towards the
maximum number of this
this guy
can eat the pasta together tutu yeah
okay
dialogue
okay we talk about dialogue in our last
lecture there's four conditions for
dialogue to happen what are they there
are four conditions for dialogue to
happen
and Aaron
yeah
hold on wait
non-preemption
Circle as a circle circular chain
relationship between between the inner
resource allocation graph right the
circular chain resource allocation graph
so these four conditions so here's the
true or false okay
um
we just need to satisfy one of the
conditions of just one of the condition
happens then that lock is highly
possible to happen
like these four conditions I will
mention okay these are these four
conditions if one or two of these
conditions happen then it's highly
possible dialogue may happen in the
future is that true or false who think
is true
who think is false yeah it's forced
right how about others I think it's a
chore for answering yeah it's forced
right the answer is the solution is what
only in four conditions we satisfy the
dialogue may happen the dialogue may
happen
then how to avoid how to how to handle
the dialogue how to handle the dialogue
we have several strategies what are they
what are they
we've been learning that in just two
days ago
come on
yeah
so oh forget it
yeah Andrew I'm sorry Eric
yeah very good
no no not look at your slime okay
okay you detach it and then
any other students
yes
four strategies what are the four
strategies tell me the name
tell me the name and tell me what the
key idea of each approach
key idea of each approach four
strategies we have the first Global
problem then when we grow the problem
what we are going to do
we just do like see some reboots right
we just kill the process and restart it
if this system is hand there we just
rebooting the system part of it and we
put it that's the equal problem then how
about the second one
we go let's go from the most passive one
to the most active one so the growth
problem is the most passive one how
about the next one
yes
avoidance or something what is something
the bank is algorithms is part of the
what kind of algorithm they worry about
the second approach do we let it happen
do we let the dialogue happen we let the
deadlock happen then Andrew
that is not the second solution the
second strategy Andrew
that is that is the fourth strategy to
substance subcategory of the fourth
strategy we do not come to that yet the
second solution is we learn what's your
name much
we just killed the process or something
or something yeah it does it is detox
and Recovery detection recovery and how
about the third one the third one
how about the third one that is where
the bank algorithm is
yes
yeah
Dynamic avoidance is what is the key
idea
what is a key idea
do we let it happen
do we let the dialogue happen no we do
not what we do is that we
keep tracking the process their process
and then
doing some dynamical location the
resource right and then the fourth
approach the first approach
the fourth approach yes
make sure one of the condition never
happens and we call that approach is
prevention
prevention that is the most active
approach now now as a system designer
when we're talking about that dialogue
situation as a system designer
which approach do they use
the four strategies as a system designer
if it is a data center very big data
center or system administrator
what kind of approach they are going to
use
it it depends depends right we will talk
about that we talk about that we say
that to prevent a deadlock is very
expensive
if the dialog only happens every five
years one dialogue do we do that do we
do the academic avoidance where like
detection recovery
we just let it happen but if the
dialogue happens very frequently and if
the if this system is very important the
cost of recovering the system is very
very expensive then we need to do
prevention
now come to the prevention how to avoid
any of these four conditions
the first condition is
Mutual exclusion how to avoid a mutual
exclusion
how to avoid a non-preemption how to
avoid Holden the weights how to avoid
the circular chain in the resource
allocation graph
how to avoid it
go back to your slides okay we have the
supporting everything right that is
covers
avoid the mission exclusion we we allow
them to
take the resource away that is how we
always learn preemption right and then
we hold and waste how we just
no we do not kill a process we remember
hold on wait how how do we avoid the
cold and weights
if if I am a process I need
three resources to to proceed how to
avoid that
very good the first process to allocate
the resources at the very beginning as
you can only get three resources
together or you get long of the resource
that is the way how we avoid the holding
weights so no one can hold something and
ask something and create it avoid the
situation of creating a
a chain a circle in the resource
allocation graph right then how we
avoid the force conditioner
circulation
yeah we order the results pneumatically
right we order the resource numerically
we now we have you can only gather
resource in the order
in the order
okay now the uh
so you need to understand how to detect
uh detached based on the action of the
like I say this process is ask resource
requires some resource you need to have
to you need to know how to draw the
resource allocation graph and find out
if there are locked inside of the graph
okay uh
okay that is basically what we have or
my tips is that to go back to look at
the slides if you do not understand it
go to the tutor session we have tutor
session ta session
I also have my office hours
and you have your textbook you have your
textbook
go back to read the slides this is the
first thing and the second thing go back
to redo your homework
how many homework do you have now two
or just one just an introduction you do
not have homework assignment tool
oh okay that's
you do not have any homework of process
and thread
that's interesting
you also have your homework soon okay
today maybe
yeah sorry about that but I'm going to
eat 109.
because I wanted you to look at what
kind of example questions are and you're
going to well okay I'm going to release
two homeworks today okay the Denmark and
the Denmark and the process and threads
okay but you do not need to finish it
before the midterm you can finish it
yeah that's tricky that's really my ti
should release that
um
okay yeah okay okay good luck okay good
luck
that's a problem
desktop
for some reason it's giving me this even
though I have darker rice here
yeah
you need to ask for the RTA oh it's an
email to Tia
is not here using the TA session they
have we have two sessions almost every
day
[Music]
um
tutor can you can you open a session
more session before the meeting more
sessions yeah yes
four more time in the in in the city
it's real more time we have in two
sessions
before the midterm because I is packed I
will be here okay here I will be I will
be here in uh Tuesday in I will be in
Zoom to answer any questions
on Tuesday but
um
it's better you cannot have some
sessions in before like in Monday okay
let's say in Monday yeah
yeah can you like um adding more
sessions
I mean we have like how many buildings
here and we don't have to you know we
just want proper end I mean Eric was
holding a session
project questions
12 times
[Music]
something