uh so
so here's my plan uh
we have two weeks left
so beside this week we have another two
weeks left so my plan is that we
um I'm going to try to finish uh all
chapters next week and for the
um so your exams on beyond June I think
it's John 13s
your exams are being on
oh June 15th
your exam will be on June 15th or
Thursday Thursday 7 13 pm to 10 30 p.m
so that will be the final week we will
not have any QA session on that week
because that week you may have other
exams there's no class in that week but
I will give you a
um like rehearsal final final rehearsal
exam rehearsal on the
on a week 10 so week 10.
so my plan is that we we finished all
the contents like the
OS hard topics such as system
virtualization containers
distributed file systems on next week
and then so um
because I didn't see many students there
so the scenes my tips is there
um definitely come to the final exam
review class I'm going to put at least
two class for final exam review
okay so and it will be on the um on the
one week before your final so it will be
on the um
on the June 6 and June June 8th because
you all have the exam on June 15th okay
under exam will be accumulative so it
will cover everything we have learned so
far
but focus is the uh
the focus it will be the memory file
systems and the osr topics but we will
still cover a little bit about
processors dialogue
the OS structure
so another thing is that unfortunately
there's many students who are suspected
progressions in my class that is not
good we already been so fragile um
so what is probabilism so you cannot
copy the code from your classmate if I
found out that both of you guys up
will get the grade zero another case is
that you copy the code from the internet
in that case it will be also a
priorities
if you if you if the TA found out dance
and I cannot do anything about that
that is very unfortunate I think I
believe in our last year in the same OS
course around the 40s 40 percentage
students
who are considers as the plagiarisms at
the end and they all fail that is very
unfortunate so do not try to do that
because this if you um
so this course not is not that difficult
and uh we I know we have many
assignments we have many uh projects but
it is not that difficult even for the
projects I try to simplify that ask ta
to provide as much as code that he can
so you just need to fill in the part of
the code to finish the project
um
and it is your responsibility to protect
your code
so do not say that okay someone take
your code so then you do not know that I
cannot do anything about that so
um
okay and we we we we we
the T we have several graders who
continually runs the probabilism check
so do not feel
strange they're like will you receive a
your grades become zero then that means
you they think that you are progressing
you you have some academic misbehavior
okay so any questions
yes
I'm talking about projects one project
two
especially projects two we we the the we
have several graders they I ask them to
do the program check but it's very slow
it's not that easy because they we we
um they they are required to non-owning
use the tools I ask them to read The
Code by themselves so they need to read
the code read read the code that are
suspicious to be product to
um are treating
yeah
so I have been repeated that about that
many times in the class
if you write your own by The Code by
yourself you should not not worry about
that
okay oh
okay so today we are going to finish the
fight uh we are going to finish most
part of the file system the key things
about the file system is that so later
we are we are going to talk about an
important concept called inode inode I
hope you can memorize it for now
I know everything in the file system
will be surrounded about about the eye
load the same thing like a page okay
everything in the memory we we do
everything talking about everything else
about page like page in page map uh hash
uh sorry tlb everything's about paging
right page four but in the file systems
the key concept here is inode so we are
so let's see what is inode
uh-huh
numbers that correspond
a whole table a table that lists the
numbers corresponding to the files very
good that is very close people we are
going to learn yeah
we should have a like yeah
I believe there's like each each file
has for each of being in the in the uh
in the table has like a file
yeah the Beetles have an eye note and
the I node uh has information about like
the owner the place and the address
um the priority and et cetera et cetera
yeah yeah that's very good okay so we
are going to learn that it's about like
I know that I know the table I know the
number they are all corresponding to
inode but standing in front of that what
is exactly I know why we need inode so
we are going to learn that okay so let's
see the file implementation so uh in our
last class we see file system from the
user's protective point of view now in
this class we are going to learn the
file systems from the implementation
point of view okay
so file store on the disk disk broken
into one or more partitions with the
separate file system descriptors on each
partition
so uh
okay there's no picture about that so
the files or
so this is a disk right the disk so this
the disks are going to be partitioned
into many many
are broken into many partitions this is
partition this is partition so this is
the disk
and we have that each partition a
partition one partition zero actually
starting from zero partition zero
partition one two and in each partition
they divide it into more about the
sectors that is the a capture of the
disk that means architecture of the disk
now we know the operating system is an
abstraction and resource manager right
resource doing the resource management
so
um now this is the hardware Hardware
how to use the software interface API to
represent this Hardware that is the file
implementation okay file implementation
so we look at the
um so the first thing is that
everything is on the disk right
nothing in the memory when we boot the
operating systems we need to load the
scenes load OS node OS operating system
from the disk into the memory so how do
we know that
how we loaded the code we need to load
the code okay the who did that that is
the a boot computer okay the
bios okay the BIOS are doing that so
where is the BIOS
so the first thing about
about the file systems to booting
operating system is to locate the active
partition reads its first block we call
it super block
sometimes we call it the boot block and
excuse it
so you can think of that as the this is
the this is the disk this is the whole
disk and we broken this disk into many
partitions right we broken data into
many partitions and in front of this
partition there's a partition zero
partition zero and inside of the
partition zero there will be the BIOS
code biosole you mean very familiar with
that that is the code
that is the entry of the operating
system that is the entry of the
operating system
the award OS did at the beginning when
you launch your OS launch the system is
read the code reader code in BIOS
and then xq start excuse it so let's
look at this picture so you see the
so there is a partition table right we
know that this this is the whole disk
entire disk okay entire disk
many times if in the windows then that
is The discus C okay the entire disk and
we broke the disk into many partitions
so here's the partition disk partition
and here we have the partition table so
the partition table the partition table
tells you where exactly each partition
is
and inside of each
inside of each partition it's the we
have the boot block super block free
space inode loot dir files and a file
directories
oh
so let's look at this okay
so let's see from the first time we see
the hardware okay Hardware
we know this is a disk
you throw it in front that way
this is a disk right this is a
this is a disk
so the disk the whole disk
is divided into partitions and inside
inside the partition there's something
called the sector
right that is the disk that is a disk
structure the hardware the hardware
structure of the disk now operating
system will see the discards like this
this is the whole disc
it'll hold this
Leslie this is just the one over we we
may have many disks in the OS but this
is just one of the disk now remember
last time we see last time we learned
the OS from the operating from the
user's point of view we see the files
are structured into a tree structure so
if you remember
we have the first is the looter right
the loot
of the loot directory right
and then we have several for other
folders right like the Etc
device
user
right we have we have we have several
folders and we're talking about the
absolute parts and the relative paths
and there's other like the other folders
so there's other folders now
now let's think about that if you are
the system designer you are the system
designer
how you're going to make a data
structure for the for all these files
you want to you want you you need to you
need to
save these files into the hardware the
hard disease is the disk right this is a
disk you need to save these files into
your disk and using a tree structure
so what's the information you need to
put in the init
into that then it comes true
we first we first saw
OS why the OS data operating system data
is large for this disk you are using
you will divide the disk into many
partitions and the fifth
we can see the rest of partitions may
use to save our users contents like
these files these important files but at
the beginning of this partition at the
beginning of this partition we need to
know we need to know some important
information so what are these important
information the important information
includes
includes the
space
okay the space
so what is exactly space space means
for each partition how much space is how
much space is right and then
we need our information about inode it
actually is a i node table we talk about
I know later but you can think of the
inode it's like the if if the whole
whole disk is like a book then I notice
just the chapter
chapter the index of the book the same
as same as a
the page table okay so like idle it's
like the index of a book in this will be
the index I know table with the index of
all the files or files
then we have
we have the other directories right loot
dir
then the this difference dirs okay
they are there
before that before that we have a
super block
so what exactly super block is super
block and boot Glock boot block
boost block may only contains
several lines of code
so it is the it is the entry entry of
the operating system one always report
it was starting the boot block and after
it read the book block it goes to Super
block so what a super block contains it
contains the most important information
about this partition this is one
partition okay this partition so what
are the most important information about
this partition contains it contains
the owner of this disk right owner of
this disk success control of this disk
the number of blocks in the districts
and other key administrative information
key administrative information so if we
look out if we go from the um
whole point of view we can see that
the file system is actually a
hierarchical structure hierarchical
structure so first it's like it's like
uh it's like this okay it's like this
first we have the entry so we entry
we enter into the disk and then we read
the most important information about
this disk like who owned these sticks
who creates this disk
which user has the most uh most of
priority control of this disk so
everything is in here that is the super
super block super block
will have this information
and then and then we have the inode
inode I know that what tells you
where each directory is a directory root
directory where it is
the subdirectory where it is the files
each of files where it is that is the
inode I node okay I know I know the
structure will tell you this and then
after that we have
hundreds of thousands of files that
there so it's like a hierarchical
structure it is like a hierarchical
structure that is a file system
structure
in a modern operating system okay so I
will repeat that
the file system layout is like a
oh yes
hierarchical structure so it first
contains the
uh the boot block for each partition
the first the disk is divided into many
partitions and for each partition it
contains the boot block boot block is
the entry of that partition and then we
have the super block the super block
contains the most important information
about that partition includes that who
owns this partition
the number of blocks in this partition
the key administrative information about
this partition like which user which
group user group has the most priority
control and then we have the inode
information I know the information will
tell the tells you
how many files how many folders
in in total in this partition and where
are they it's like a index of a book or
tells you okay well what the contents it
contains and then the rest of them about
19 percentage of the disk was saved the
real complex information about like the
user's files like your movies your
documents your
your code like that okay
so this is a file system layout
so again the super block contains the
information about the file system like
the type of the file system the number
of blocks so by the way what is blocks
or this block
yes
uh it's not memory yeah Lily
the sector over the partition very very
good very close but it's not exactly the
sector so if
um
is a lawyer accountants inside of the
sector so we know the disk you see the
disk is divided into partitions right
and inside the pattern so these are all
sectors these are all sectors the block
is the
b l o c k it's called block
s the units the units of the disk
Hardware disk that we use to store the
files so um sometimes the blocks can be
64 megabytes sometimes they can be 16
megabytes
it depends it depends every every
operating system has their own defaults
block size so block the block size the
block is is very similar to what we
learned in the memory of the page right
each page is 4kb but it's belonging to
the memory but in the disk we use the
units of block yes
so with this cat picture have like what
could this cat picture be divided into
blocks maybe if it is larger than 64
megabytes then it will be divided into
blocks that that's is true okay let's
say you have a cat picture and it's 1 GB
so it's very large very very large but
from the user's point of view when you
see that you you didn't feel it broke
down into many blocks right but from the
OS point of view at the back at the back
they are broken into many blocks and
stored in different partitions in
different places yeah you have any
questions
you have let's see
blocks
why do you say again so what if we have
for thousands of blocks each block is 64
megabytes and then
a thousand of files each one is
that
only one megabyte that's that's a very
that's that's a very good question
that's very good question so are we
going to do that's why we are going to
learn later that is the way how you
track how to like track the available
free resources in a disk and then how
you love how you make the best use of
the available resources in the disk that
is the um
resource management issue of the file
system we're going to learn that later
okay if I say some layout so that is the
um
okay
and that is what we're going to learn
allocating blocks to files the same
question like we have what we we have a
very large file how are we going to
allocate the blocks for files what if we
have very small files how we're going to
allocate the blocks to files
so there's
so
so here
we need to keep track of which these
blocks go with which file
we have the blocks right we have the
blocks you think of the each block is
like 64 megabytes then we have the files
the files can have different size it's
made as large as
10 gigabytes it once fire 10 gigabytes
of movie
made a small also one megabytes so how
you're going to locate the blocks to
these different size of files so you
want to make a guess and you still want
to make a guess
are we going to do that
how we're going to assign the files of
different sides to the blocks
so the question is this we have
this is your resource pool
this is a result pool here this is your
disc right this is my disk
my disk is very Lush
let's say
1000 gigabytes so right 1000 gigabytes
okay then then we have
we have many blocks right as I told as I
told you in the in the disk everything
is the disk is broken into many blocks
okay blocks
okay
they are blocks
they block each one of them is Block
it's blocked like empty spaces like
empty seats but they have the same size
now you have a file you have a incoming
streams of files
we have many files many files okay menu
files so how are we going to organize it
put it into the disk put it into the
blocks like we need to decide which
below blocks belonging to which file
right we need to decide that so any
algorithms come into your mind
any algorithms so how we allocate the
files how we how do we allocate the
files we have many files coming one is
big one is small one is super big one is
super small like super small they are
coming they are coming we do not know
when they are calm and the word of their
coming but they are coming they're
coming continuously so how do we
allocate these files into the disk
that is a key question about the file
system so you want to make a gas monkey
continuous allocation
so what is continually allocation
we allocated continuously so one by one
right one by one like first come first
to serve like one by one okay one by one
that is one solution that is one
solution
so let's look at that
so continuous allocation continually
allocation
so what we do is that so file a
we put file a there then we put file B
there we put file C so we put them one
by one that is the continually
allocation continually allocation so
what is the problem we know they are
coming okay we know they are coming
you will not save the file forever right
I download a file I use it then I delete
it you are not going to use it forever
some files may only live for a couple of
minutes some files may leave for longer
much longer time what will be the
problem of continually allocation and
you
in it's called a fragmentation right
fragmentation internal fragmentation so
what is the internal fragmentation
a lot of little holes or wider of course
that yeah what's your name
oh you are Andrew we have four Andrew
okay Alejandro
internal but why it will cause internal
fragmentation the answer is true like
the the problem is that there will be
internal fragmentation
but what Lily
evenly partition into the like unit
block size
the size of files
not exactly so so the internal
fragmentation means that when when we
run it for a long time when we write for
long time like files keeps comes in some
files keeps come out like files keeps
coming come out like this when we grind
for a long time we are going to find out
the disc is full of many small empty
holes
Andrew
after you evict a larger one
yes very good so let's say we in weeks
the larger first let's say some larger
files goes out let's say the larger
files let's say it's like
if the file is have five blocks right if
if he goes out or 10 blocks if he goes
out only the size is smaller than 10 can
fit in
Rising off that only the size of smaller
than 10 can fit in after it fits in
after it runs for a while
then we will we will see many of
the same empty holes like this because
you want you are not getting see this
picture may have better wheel
you see we have this we have this right
we have this at the beginning
everything's good okay everything's good
and then we found out okay we I used up
these files I do not need it anymore so
I invicted it out
are recycle it from the disk and then
what happens it will have a and it will
have an empty hole like the empty space
like this but it may still become large
it may still a very large space but then
then what happens
then what happened is that of course we
owning next time one new file comes in
let's say the file is six it is six
blocks it cannot fit in this place right
owning only the file owning the file
that is smaller than five let's say
three can fit in it can fit in the same
as this place the same as this only the
file that is smaller or equal than six
can fit in So eventually only only the
small files can get satisfied also the
new file moved out only small files can
get satisfied and eventually we will
have many this continually empty spaces
that we call the internal fragmentation
yes
because we had a because I mean we
already I guess that is kind of the idea
of internal fragmentation
yeah that's very similar that is not a
virtual memory we learned that it's from
swapping in remember that that's another
it's a it's called swapping so we have
two technologies for allocates the
memory spaces to the uh to the to the
process right the one technology is
called swapping another is called
virtual memory so this is the same as
swapping technology
that is not a virtual memory okay
virtual memory you actually use paging
the paging that one of the best feeds of
the paging algorithm is that it's
avoided
internal fragmentation problem because
it divides the process into many small
pages each page is 4kb so you will not
have any
big holes because everything is into the
page yeah
oh you you see you're asking if a file e
is growing
if e equal to 13
diagram a okay if
e okay if e is equal to 13 it will not
put there so continue our location it
will continually find out the m key
space is the larger than 30 if there's
no space is larger than 30 it will be
way there until
a larger 30 space is coming out so only
the small files can be satisfied first
the
like it always has to in continual
location so this is so the picture is
tell you the story that at first
everything is empty so we we have
different file a b c d e comms so they
are going to serve the one by one
then
no no no no no so here's the thing
continue what is the continue allocation
it means that first can we continually
allocate them so like a comes will get a
first that is why you see a b c d e f g
so the if the E equals to certain then e
was taking this space and then when F
comes f for taking this
I do not get that
yeah it's
just
happens
if you are asking the file become one
block larger
after you see it a while yeah that is
the problem that is problem it will not
allow that because that is a continually
allocation it will not allow that it
will be
but it is not the case in I know
allocations or what we are going to
learn that later okay so we see the
continue allocation the good thing is
that it's easy to implement easy to
implement the Real Performance is great
why read performance is great
why read performance is great yes
so so when we say read the performance
you see like you you want to see a movie
right you you let's say we have a movie
you want you want to go to the middle of
the movie right you want to see the
middle of the movie so for that page for
spare parts this is this continue
allocation approach is super great what
because you can directly go to the
middle of the movie because you already
know the start of the movie is so you're
just adding the contents then you know
you can point to the middle of the movie
if this is a movie okay
so that is the that is white is good but
if it is not a continual location like
the file is goes to everywhere in the
disk then you will never know where the
middle of the movie is
single in that way okay
we have this file so we have this this
let's say the file is a movie okay file
is a movie so why we say the read
performance is ways
of course
you only need to seek to allocate the
first block in the file then you can
know where the other block is you only
need to know where the first is then you
can know where the other is
because they are like like that students
say they are next to each other they are
next to each other you can easy to find
out but think and extreme cases that if
it is not continually a location if it
is not a continuing location the blocks
will be everywhere the file e will be
everywhere in the disk so you will never
find out the like the middle of the
movie and you need to find it one by one
one by one block to find out oh well my
the middle of the movie is that's why
the Real Performance is great
so let's see
the bad things is that first thing is
that the disk becomes fragmented over
time over time
so who are using the continuous equation
our CD oh
it's not maybe not the your age you are
not using CD right you're not reusing CD
to read the music to to listen to the
music right no no one using CD but you
know what CD is right yeah yeah that's
CD so at my
um
three and each truck is actually like a
music like a music they they use also
they read it one by one so CD-ROM use
continual occasion because the file size
file system size is low in events
as you saw same as the video okay okay
so another approach is linked list
allocation
oh that's very similar to what we
learned in the swapping technology in
the memory
um
chapter so linked lists are very similar
so the second method for storing file is
keep each one keep each one as a linked
list of the disk blocks as shown in the
figure
so the key idea of the linked list the
key idea of the linked list
so you look at a picture can you make a
guess
with the disk blocks so so this is the
file a so file how many blocks that the
file a has
my first instinct would be five five
blocks okay the five blocks of file a
but they allocates near to each other in
the physically disk
um no because linked lists operate on
pointers so they are not then where are
each of the blocks so we know the file a
have has five blocks right
then where are their actual location in
the disk
and one block two have an offset of two
and then walk walk four has an opposite
of 10. yeah there were good that is a
physical block number so here
so here we use the
they are not going to store next to each
other they're going not going to store
next to each other owning owning the
previous blocks knows where the next
block is
yes
yeah that's what I'm going to say later
okay so you see that is why the um
so the good thing about that is what is
a good thing
the good thing
yes
yes it's reduced get risk of
fragmentation there's no fragmentation
right because the files no matter how
large it is how small it is it's going
to be divided into blocks and we spread
out the blocks into the disk so the
blocks so each file like if I'm a fire
or I'm broken into many parts or any
part of the of this file can be anywhere
of the disk we the only each disk each
block only needs to know the next block
is the next block is so they let's say
the file they have a pointer we use a
pointer to point out the next the next
block
so the bad thing about that is like we
yeah
Andrew
yeah really slow of what
yeah so the random access is very slow
the read performance is not good right
because you need to the Rhythm
especially the random access let's say
same thing like you want to locate it at
the end of the movie you need to go to
the start of the movie and jump it one
by one one by one and to find out where
exactly the end of the movie is the
random access is slow so you need to
chase the pointers to get a block Nick
chase the pointer to get her block
this is a good thing about bad thing the
good thing about the link list the best
thing about linked list
any improvements before we go to the eye
note we say any improvements for the
linked list approach any Improvement
magician
s
yeah that is what I write in slides but
what exactly it is
developed you keep them in the memory so
the memory is going to say okay so this
so this is the next uh block is over
here and then that guy's next block is
over there and so forth you're very good
so the so the so the key idea is that
the key ideas are so we see that
why it is slow because we need to we do
not know let's say we know the file the
file blocks zero we only know the start
start of the file right but we do not
know we do not know the file blocks one
two three four five we do not know where
it is in the physically location so the
key idea of the Improvement is that how
about we just save the mapping we just
save the mapping into the into the
memory
we do not we we still use the linked
list allocation structure to keep track
of the files in the disk about how
beside that we're adding another
abstraction in the memory and what we do
is that we just saving the maps the map
like okay five the virtual block 3 is
mapping to the physical block 10.
that's a very very familiar with that's
why I say the file system is very
similar to the memory system right
that's the same idea so we're using
using a table in the memory using a
table in the memory that we save the
information
of the mapping between the virtual
blocks to the physical blocks so we know
where each block is okay we know where
each group is let's say here
that is the solution linked list
allocation using a table in the memory
using a table in the memory we have the
file a file a is starting at 7 right 7.
then we
then you see it's enough
uh we see this together okay
let's file a you see the start is
starting zero right it's in in the
physical properties of four right and
then we have the one and it's mapped to
seven so you look at this
so file a start here right five I start
here so start here so then it needs to
go to the seven so we go to seven in
front of the next two and we'll go to
formula 10 and then 12 and then that is
the end this is how they how they start
how they installed
then we know the file I use the disk
blocks four seven two ten twelve in that
order and it will be used disk
C63 11 14 in that order
so we save the information in the memory
so the next time we do not need to track
physically track the blocks like using
the disk pointer to point block that is
very slow we just at least we we just
need to
try to track the information in the
memory map the memory table that is very
straightforward yes
that is a little intensive that is why
later we introduce the New Concept
called I node okay I know the table
maybe comes really big and this also
needs to jump a one and a fourth right
you need to jump to find out where
exactly each but it's actually is
actually very fast it's not just slow
because everything is in memory that is
the key differences if you do not have
this table in the memory then everything
you need to
look at this this is in the disk if it
is not in memory you need to
keep tracking it in the disk disk access
is slow it's much slower the memory
access in remember the memory
hierarchical structure that is why the
crazy table to maintain the pointer
information in the memory because memory
is faster much faster is actually here
this table is exactly the same as the
pointer the pointer in the link list
right but it's since it's in the memory
so it's not that slow it's just
because the this table may become very
big become very big and it's not that
it's kind of expensive to keep tracking
like that keep reading
then we have the key idea then we have a
key idea about the inode
so before we're talking about inode so I
want to you go uh remember some
important concepts of the OS
we first look at the continual
allocation right we find out it's not
good because its cost of fragmentation
then we use the linked list we okay we
say that it's also not good because it's
what the the read performance right the
random access is very slow so the both
both approaches are not good one
approach complements another right the
continual location has the benefits of
goodread access the linked list has the
benefits of avoid fragmentation But A
and B they are both not good they are
both not good then
you have a certain solution so here the
the thing what I want you to take away
here is that is um out of the textbook
okay everything in the operating systems
that you cannot fix everything almost
everything you can do that that is a
famous
researcher said that everything we
cannot fix that in operating systems
by using different data structures
so any problem that you cannot fix just
by changing the data structures you can
fix that problem with adding an extra
obstruction by adding an extra
abstraction so that is why for the negle
list that they're adding a new
obstruction like this like this that is
actually a new abstraction but this
abstraction is still not good then we
change the abstraction into the I node
into inode so what exactly I notice what
exactly I know this so first I know
there is a data structure okay it's a
data structure
so
each file has a separates I node like
each of you have a
student card or driver license okay each
file has an important
I know the data structure
so and then what I know I know the data
structure contains what I know the data
structure contains so we create I know
let's say I know the class right the
class I node then we need to design the
variables and inside of the I know the
right and the operations the variables
and operations inside of the inode
then what are they
so think of that your Drive lessons
contains who you are write the name of
you the date of birth of you
the address of you and maybe the ID
driver license ID of you
right same as I know it I know that will
create will have the information about
who creates this file
where the fire is how many blocks this
file has
I know
I know the right I know that we have a
let's say your driver
lessons
the job lessons you have the uh your
name right the name the name of you who
you are right
like Andrew
right so that I know that the I node
okay this file the file that it will has
let's say the name the name of the file
let's say the name of the file is
is a DOT t x t that is the name of the
file now what else in the drive lessons
you have the dob right
ptob the same other stuff I know the
same creation dates right
there's some creation days what else
what else you remember that we learned
from the user's point of view we see we
used to see a table the table shows the
many information about the file right
let's say the access
because the excess pattern
like read write execute
right it will show that too or what else
so that's the same thing right in your
drive lessons you also have your access
pattern uses like you'll see a b c d
so most of us have the C right so you we
are allowed to drive small cars small
cars same as this what what else then it
has the your address that's very
important whenever you change your
address you need to report to the
to the DDS right that's the same thing
as the I node I know this is for file
this file the address so now the tricky
is here
the trick is here for us we for us we we
are just the person right we address is
just where we live it's a one one
address right it's just a one dress but
for I know the slightly different so
what is the difference what are the
difference
any student know what are the difference
if if just the persons only have one of
the drugs but for that I know it's a
file it's a file yeah every
much more
for each block you're very good remember
the file is broken into the blocks right
the file is broken this is a large file
the file the file is the a DOT txt it's
blocked into many blocks right it's
broken into many blocks so the addresses
block one
block two
block three
block and
so here the I know the container
information about
the block recorded the block address the
address of each blocks
so it points to where
a physical physical
block number right the physical block
number
the physical address you can think of
the physical address in the disk
um
so many times it will just show you the
partition number and then the block
number it will show you two numbers
partition number and block number the
physical that is a physical block
physical
Rachel that is the I node I node
so we see this is actually a
Improvement than the
the link release the table what's the
difference
in a linked list in remember in the link
in the table for the linked list we we
use the memory we have a one table for
all the files right for one order files
so the table may be coming extremely
large but in this case we do not have a
memory table for I know right we just
each file have a data structure of this
so each file each file has a data
structure we called inode
I node
I node each each file has a data
structure called inode we do not put it
we do not have a table
for whole files it's not like it's not
like what we learned in My Maria in in
this
it's completely different than this
right in this approach
every file is inside you see every file
is inside so that is why the table may
become huge may become huge but for
inode
for inode we only need this information
the file attributes right and the
address of each of its blocks physical
address of each blocks and then and then
question comes to you
how do you decide which so the I know
that is a data structure right we
where we should put it in the disk or in
the memory
where we should put it
Andrew anjura
neck okay neck
if we use it we keep it in memory very
good if you use it we give you the
memory if you do not use it we do not
keep it the memory we just put it in the
disk right where in the disk
we learned that half an hour ago where
it is we are in the disk
Maji
near the start of the disc right here
here
[Music]
the very start of this after super block
that is I know right but if we use it we
put this data structure in the memory
now the question is that how do you know
when do you when you are going to usage
when you are not using it
like you you could you need to have you
need to have a space for this eye node
right then it comes to another
data structure called I node table I
know the table
I know table so in I know the table what
we are going to do is that
here here see
we are going to put all the frequently
used inode into the inode table so I
know table is actually has two layers
the first layer is the each I know that
I'm going to give you give them a number
let's say this is one two three and then
there's many I know the right one two
three four five six let's say what we
have ten thousand files then the number
may become ten thousand ten thousand ten
ten thousand tenkates then in the I know
the table it's in the memory I know the
table is in memory in I know the table
I'm going to put the frequently used
files into the table so let's say one
three seven
eleven thirteen one thousand one
thousand twenty four this is the the my
frequently used the file so I put it in
the I know the table then points after
points to I know the table is the I node
that's the where the exactly I know this
then we can find out the I know so this
this I know table is in the memory and
the source that I know the frequently
used I know then I can find out well
exactly the
I know that we can know the physical
address of the inode and then we can
locate the file so I have a video to
show the past uh give me one second
see
you
it's in format is the popular file
system format is the extended format
commonly used in Linux each file in the
disk has a data structure called an
inode associated with it the inode is
fixed link popular another popular file
system format is the extended format
commonly used in Linux each file in the
disk has a data structure called an
inode associated with it the inode is
fixed length it contains the metadata
for the file and it serves as the glue
linking the data blocks together in the
right order is this gluing function that
is the most interesting the inode stores
15 data block addresses or pointers the
first 12 of these Point directly to the
first 12 data blocks of the file this
makes the strategy efficient for small
files the 13th of these addresses points
to a block that consists of a table of
addresses for the next blocks in the
file this vastly increases the number of
blocks that we can use in a file the
downside is that we've introduced a
layer of indirection if this doesn't
give the file enough space then we use
this 14th pointer and not one but two
layers of indirection giving us even
more space and if this isn't enough we
have a 15th pointer which uses triple n
direction for more space still
just like in fact directories are traded
as files only instead of mapping a file
name to the first file block then map a
file name to its inode that path for
accessing slash Foo slash file.txt would
look something like this we start at the
inode for the root directory
and then following its data pointers we
find the data for the root directory
there we find that Foo maps to another
inode
following that address we consult that
inode and find the address for its data
block
looking in there we find the contents of
Slash Foo that's a directory so it's
going to map the file name file.txt to
the appropriate inode and then using
that inode structure we're able to piece
together the data that we need
the data that we need so if if we look
at this so here this is the absolute
path right that's the absolute pass
so the file is in the dash Foo Dash file
dot txt right the file that is the
absolute part of that file so this video
tells you
like how the printing system find out
the file the exactly file accounting so
we first look at for this file that txt
there is I node right every file has an
inode so we see the file the activity
has a I know so it has the metadata and
then block address of each of the blocks
right so this is each of the blocks so
we have the um
so this is the case that the file what
if the file is extremely large if the
file is extremely large then that I know
that maybe they may need several layers
of the inode to represent the file
because you cannot hold everything broke
out the broker address maybe very very
long a lot of entries so you want to
avoid that
then they use several layers but we can
just look at the first layer okay
doesn't matter they don't match the data
like who I want to file the creation of
the file the file access patterns and
then we have the each blocks each block
of the file we have first of several
first several blocks we see then there
we locate to there then we can find out
exactly data of the file.txt that is
exactly file.txt but then to locate the
file txt we need to know the absolute
path right remember the everything in
the um in the linear systems is the
files are organized into a tree
structure starting from the loose folder
to the subfolders and then to the files
right there's many many directories and
they organize the other three then we
need to locate the exactly I node for
file txt we need to locate the folder
for their directory first and we find
out that
I node for the root directory but it
only tells you the physical address of
the blue directory then we go to the
physical address and find out the data
of the I know the root directory and
then see we see the data inside of the
data this is a directory right so the
directory will tell the
inside of the directory it will be the
subdirectories right that is the context
of that directory right it will not it
only tells you next level of the
contents so that is why we need to find
out the I node for the dash Foo for
dashfo so the after we find out the dash
I node for dash fo we look at the
physical address of the dash flow so
when we find out the dash file and the
dash of
under the dash Foo there may be many
files not just the file.txt there may be
a file B TST fail ctsd but we know that
we can find out the data for the for the
file txt under the dash of all after
that we look at the I node for the file
txt and then we find out the exactly
exactly data is
wait so that is the whole story about
how we use the inode tool to find out
the data okay
okay and then implementing directories
okay
so how do we Implement in directories
so the directory entries provides the
information needed to find the data disk
blocks depending on the system this
information maybe the discount address
of the entire file or the number of the
file blocks or the number of inode
so the directory so here the takeaway
here is this okay the directory
so let's see how do we implement this
directory how do we implement the
directory
so did The Rock refers so you need to
know the directory is the same as the
files the directory have the same
structures of files they just
um
the difference is between the directory
and the file is that the file they do
not have many subdirectory but directly
they have subdirectory so that is why
um
we need each entry this is the directory
let's say this is the directory under
this directly there are several folders
and then we need to point to the next
folders right so each entry refers to a
inode okay and then how we
okay let's skip that that's the how do
we do uh deal with the directory names I
think this is a kind of old
let's say I feel like
what if there's a user who likes to
create a weird directory names so how do
we fix that because some users Andrew
yes
whatever file what speak louder I
couldn't hear you
were only pointer if it's very small
then you only use one block so there's
only one block of the dress
the point is for the end is the data of
the file right the pointer to the end is
the data of the file
check this this is the same as the uh
you know in the video what we learned
but let's just find out the video may be
better so easy if you want let's look at
this
the step of looking at this file and box
and box is the file that you are looking
at
so your question is that if Mbox is too
small
you know like
if you like to be like that uh that
diagram where it kind of breaks down the
structure that I know
we do okay okay sure sure let's go back
to the video
another popular file system format
is the extended format commonly used
something like this
find that Foo the root directory
oh you you are seeing this the indirect
right yeah okay the indirect means okay
so here's the thing if the file is very
very very very large then they mean then
they have many
if we do not have this indirect table
then the entries of the inode the number
of lines in anode will be extremely long
because let's say you don't have 100K
blocks 100K blocks then this then the
size you can think of the size of the
eye load will be very large right so
that is why this the break is actually
like a breakdown I know into many parts
different parts
like with
if it's more than there's no direct
indirect tables it's just the several
fronts
how how do we set the pointers to every
setting the blocks means that this how
do we know this
this one
this
oh dear price means that this has the
two indirect pointer so it has like this
table this let's say this is the middle
of the movie right at the middle of
movies
we see that we just save where the
middle of the movie is the next five
minutes and then the next five minutes
will tell you the next next 30 minutes
where it is and then the next 30 minutes
what goes there
how come it has two pointer
because it's super large you see let's
say pharmaceutical system format is the
extended format commonly used in Linux
each file on the disk has a data
structure called an inode associated
with it the inode is fixed length it
contains the metadata for the file and
it serves as the glue linking the data
blocks together in the right order it is
a schooling function that is the most
interesting the inode stores 15 data
block addresses or pointers the first 12
of these Point directly to the first 12
data blocks of the file this makes the
strategy efficient for small files the
13th of these this makes the strategies
in vision for small
addresses points to a block that
consists of a table of addresses for the
next blocks in the file this vastly
increases the number of blocks that we
can use in a file the downside is that
we've introduced a layer of indirection
if this doesn't give the file enough
space then we use this it does not give
it a file enough space means that if
this is the are not in love with we have
very super large files we may need this
14th pointer and not one but two layers
of indirection giving us even more space
and if this isn't enough more spaces
to so the key idea why we need to keep
the I know the short because sometimes
you need to if the fire is frequently
used you need to load the inode into the
memory right you do not want to waste
the memory resources that is why
sometimes they put several layers of the
inode table
okay
let's continue
okay we say share files share files
when several users are working together
on our projects
often lead to Shear fails
oh God I do not work together on your
projects okay do not share your files
with each other
share fails so you you as a result it is
often convenient for share file to
appear simultaneously different
directories belonging to different users
so share fail um
so let's say here this is the C right
this is the user B user B and this is
user C uses C so B let's say B has a
file and he wants to share with the c
wants us to share with you see they are
working together to our projects so they
have a shared folder and inside the
folder there are some shared data so
they want to work together with the data
and they want to touch the convenience
for Shear fail to appears materials in
different directory blown into different
users so data whenever I make a change
on this file it needs to reflected on
the C's location also this location so
how can we Implement search so how can
we Implement that
for example if B or C are new blocks how
does others owner find out
um
so we first we first using
so first this problem can be solved in
two ways okay in the first solution
these blocks are not least in
directories
so the first you think I want to ask you
what do you think I I can tell you there
are two solutions there are two
solutions
what kind of these two solutions is
there's a there's a two two two two
solution one is called hard links one
called softer link software link
any more amount to make a gas Hardware
link and the software link
so the Okay so
so in the first so yeah majest you can
say yeah you can try
hard link and a software link
it's okay it's a simple way in a simple
way don't make it complicated so what's
the difference between the software Link
and Link Heart Link
is
stored in the software
Hardware how can I can install the link
in the hardware
um
I mean one eye node we're having
different items that point to the same
physical addresses versus having a
this is very close and we are going to
learn later okay that I change the eye
note change the eye note first
so okay so yeah Andrew
yeah yeah okay okay so here's the C okay
so for the for the hard link the hard
link so in the the
so this is this is the this is the idea
okay for the hard link for hard link we
have the I know that right but this
still points to the same physical this
points to the same physical
address the same physical but a software
link for suffering instead of saving
instead of saving the link to the
physical address
player in the file 2 file two if fail to
is sharing the name sharing the same
file file one the file tool was not save
the director link to the hardware like
the physical address the physical
address the file 2 was only Safe Link
is linked to the file one
shared files so that's the that's the
key difference is the file tool was only
saved this this okay
okay under them let's see let's see
let's see how we using I node so we are
okay these two approaches differences
operating system they have different
approaches so you know what we are what
we are learning so what we are using
sorry what we are using in the in Ubuntu
huddling course of Link
so there are two approaches to implement
the fair sharing if yeah
huh
a soft links any other Solutions
we're actually using this using this we
Implement start using the inode okay
yeah
if you just look at as a picture you can
see that in the Heart Link in the Heart
Link
this file file one they have I node
right it points to this
point to this point to the same physical
file this file two will have the same I
know it was points to this the same
thing
but then they will have the same exactly
I node right then it will cause the
problem so we are going to change a
little data structure in I node to
specify that the file is shared by some
users other users that's the difference
things so in the software link the
software link
in a software Link in a soft link sums
operating file system uses soft link
they do not they do not save the I know
the information they installed save the
link to that file
you are going to access the file once I
know the information
it actually points to the fire once file
so it's like adding a separate jump
okay so let's see so
the network system are using this
approach okay the heart this this is
what we are going to learn so how to
implement that how do we Implement that
the since each of the file if they are
sharing they're sharing each of the
directories if they are sharing a same
file then they are going to save the
same I know the information for that
file right but then how do we know
then the case is that we have this file
we know this files are shared by many
people but I do not know how many people
is if it is shared by owning me and my
teammates then the other problem is that
if I delete the file my teammates have
not deleted the file then the file
should be still inside of the disk it
should not disappear right because my
teammates may still work on it the same
thing is that if we have the whole class
sharing the same file the only one all
of us all overs decides to delete the
file then the file disappears like in
the recycling stage so how do you know
that how do you use a data structure to
represent that then they also important
data structure we call it a reference
count reference count
here the count okay the count
we use another count number to represent
how many users are sharing the file
sharing the file and we use the owner
the owner is the first user that creates
the file
the crazy file and then we use account
number to
specify how many users how many
directory according to point to the same
file as a sharing the owning only one
account
one only one account
equals to zero then operating system
decides to recycle that file
that's the takeaway for file sharing
okay so um
so this is what we have learned today
and the next in next class we are going
to learn the
um
we're going to have a review about about
what we have learned so far
and then we are going to learn the hdfs
or distributed file system okay
everybody
foreign
thank you