is to create an abstract memory space
that is distinct from the physical
memory address
so that each program can have its own
memory space
and that are independent of each other
and we call it the other space of the
program
so there are a bunch of ways you can
implement this I think the basic one is
that you can have uh two values for each
process so one is the base so that
specifies where
the address space for that process
begins and limit is the length of the
program
so
basically you can use those two values
to figure out where in the physical
memory your process can access to
but it doesn't really scale and uh
well so
we talked about the Swap and virtual
memory so those are two approaches you
can run more programs in the memory
and swapping basically means
um
if your program sorry if your process is
not actively running you can just write
the content out to the disk so you your
memory can be used for other processes
and
you can do malloc in your program or you
can call a function that will create a
stack space
so
in modern systems programs grow as they
execute
so there are a couple of ways you can
allocate space
while supporting changing the program
size
and basically you are going to need
um
like a space in between
so
basically the stack grows One Direction
Heath goes the other direction so you
can do
um Dynamic allocation this way
so
the next thing we talked about was how
to manage the free memory
so the physical memory is just one giant
memory right
and the question is how are you going to
assign
like the memory into processes
and two techniques are described in a
textbook
one is called bitmaps and the other is
called linked list
so the idea is that basically you're
going to create a data structure so this
one's the bitmap and this one is the
linked list
and by checking those data structures
you can tell
where like which portion of the memory
is being used and which one is not
and when you want when the new process
is created
you can just find a free space
and you're going to assign that free
space
um to the process
so
um
there's a pros and cons of the
approaches bitmaps it's compact but you
need to search memory for K consecutive
zeros and this can be expensive
linked list is what you imagine so you
are basically going to have a node for
each like partition in memory
and you're going to have a flag on um if
this plot if this section is being used
or not
and using linked lists there are a
couple of ways you can find
uh
uh them like section of the memory where
you
um assign it to the pro the new process
so the next fit best fit worst fit quick
fit or like four options
and I think last week the professor did
some drawing here right
so
um
the trade-offs
okay
and
yeah so we also talked about uh virtual
memory memory so that's
um how modern operating systems manage
memory
and okay so virtual memory
so the key idea of virtual memory is
programs address space is broken up into
fixed pay size pages and pages are
mapped to physical memory
and there is a special component in
machine called memory management unit
and that takes care of the conversion
from physical address to Virtual address
right
so I think this picture is good so
as you can see in here
uh
virtual address space is larger than the
physical memory of this
so when you want to talk to
um the virtual page
you you first have to load the page into
your physical memory
so that you can read or set
um to your page
and yeah so
so this mapping is called page map
and typically it has a couple of an
additional metadata to keep track of you
know which page is modified or if each
page is being referenced and those are
represented by those a couple of bits
so
if you want to access a page or like I
mean the virtual page but if the page is
not in memory that'll cause a page fault
and now it is up to the operating system
to fetch the data from the disk to
memory
and that's called page fold processing
and
okay so that's page fold
and as I was saying so page table
um
is basically um
a metadata associated with each page
and
at least it has the virtual page number
and offset so the offset
um
right
so anyway you walk like like this
and yeah so structure so page table is a
just a data structure so
you
create this structure in your memory
and
right
sorry no difference
right yeah so
whenever you access memory
this page mapping has to happen so it is
important that these operations can be
done very fast
it up address translation
NMU typically have what's called tlb
translation look outside buffer and that
stores frequently accessed frames so it
can respond really fast
there's that
so the description is there
and
you can also have multiple levels of
page tables
um
to so that you don't have to keep the
entire page table in memory
and here's a diagram
and I think you guys watched the video
last time
so because that was my 10 Minute review
from the last week
and I'll be talking about page
replacement algorithms today
so
as I was saying earlier there are more
virtual Pages than the physical page
and if the physical memory is full and
you want to bring in the new page
you basically have to kick out one of
the pages so that you can bring the new
one in
but the question is which one do you
want to evict
and as you can imagine you don't want to
evict heavily used Pages because if you
evict that page and if that page is
needed in the next clock cycle they're
just waste of resources right
so
um
pastry replacement algorithms determine
um like how you replace
um Pages inside memory
so there are a couple of algorithms and
I'll be talking about them today
so there's one algorithm called optimal
page replacement
so this is simple
um
you're going to pick the one that will
not used before the longest time
but as you can imagine like if you're
computer you don't know which page will
be needed in future
so this is called optimal because it has
the Optimal Performance but you cannot
implement it in practice
but it is used as a reference algorithm
so you know given the workload you
basically calculate
um
in with this optimal page replacement
algorithm how many page faults will
happen so that would be the Baseline and
you're going to evaluate the other
algorithms
um
in comparison to this one
so
um
I thought I can do some examples here
so let's just do that
you guys still hear me I mean okay yeah
so
so this one is
code
optimal policy
and suppose that your system will
receive access to page 0 and then one
two
uh zero one
three
zero three
one two one something like that
okay
so this is the access
and suppose that the cache size is three
so that means you can
um
you can store three pages in memory at a
time
so um
okay
so
a new goal in this order
so first you want to read page zero
and
let's see
so
so in the beginning
your cache is empty
so what you're going to do is
um well so it will cause a page fault so
it's not
uh
cash hits so I'm going to write cache
Miss
and you don't have to evict anything
right now and your cash is going to
become zero
because you just accessed page 0 and you
brought that into the cash
okay next you're going to read page one
this is again a cash Miss
because again it's not in cash right
and then your cash is going to be
0 1.
it'll keep doing this so the same thing
happened for
um this one so it's not in the cache
you add it to cash
and if you want to read zero
so that's a cash hit
because page 0 is in memory right now
so you don't have to evict anything and
the cash remains 0 and 2.
and if you access one no problem
that's a cash hit
no eviction zero one two
so now
you want to read page three
but that's not in memory
so you have to load it from somewhere
and you want to put three in cash right
so the question is
you have to evict one of these pages
which one should be evict in this case
okay so people are saying two
zero
okay so why do you think it's zero
yeah so
right so if you evicts zero
you're gonna need it here right
so then you evict zero and then you load
it in the next cycle so that's
doesn't sound a good idea
so
if you look at this so one is used here
but two is used here
so two is not needed right now right so
that's the like least needed page in
this context
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
evict
2 here
and so this is cache Miss
and I'm going to basically replace
two with three
so it'll be zero
one three
yeah so that's why we cannot Implement
optimal policy in practice because you
don't know what's going to happen right
so yeah
yeah so that's this is a page table
essential
yeah but in general you don't know what
can happen in future so you can
implement this but I mean just sort of
demonstrating how it works okay
so next
um zero
is in cash so this is hit
and you don't have to change uh
the cache
and then so three is also hit so Hit
and then one is also
cash
right yes
and then
the two shows up and that's the one we
evicted earlier
so this is cache Miss
and well in this case
um
neither zero nor three is needed in
future so we can evict um like either of
them I'm just gonna pick three
so it's going to replace
um three with two so it'll be zero one
two
and then
this will be hit
and do one two
so this is the um
how ultimate policy might work but as I
was saying you can't implement this
because you don't know what's gonna
happen in future
okay
so
now
going back to the slides
so okay so that's the one you cannot
implement
and the other algorithms are ones that
you can actually implement
so this one is called not recently used
and the idea is that if the page is not
recently used that's probably
not required so you can just evict one
right
so each entry will have two bits
R and M bits
and the operating system periodically
clear our bit or or actually R stands
for reference bit so I'm just going to
call it reference speed
and
basically
when you read that page you're going to
turn on the orbit
and if you modify the page you're going
to set the M bit so M4 modifier yeah
so
yeah
yeah yeah
and so it periodically clear our bit you
cannot periodically clear M bit because
m means the page is modified right so
you're going to want to keep that
or actually
you don't have to keep it but
um
evicting the modified page is more
expensive than evicting not modified
ones because there's a
currency issue
so
um so using those two bits
each page can be categorized into those
four classes
so sometimes
um
it can be neither more referenced nor
modified
or some of them or not reference but
modified that's always possible and some
of them are referenced not modified and
reference modified right so there are
four categories
and when you have to evict something you
basically pick
the page with
lowest like number here
so if there is a page that is not
referenced and not modified that's the
one you want to kick out
and if there's no such entry then you
fall back to this class one so that's
not a reference but modified
yeah so
uh
yes
I mean priority to be kept in the page
table
right
because you want to keep the referenced
and the modified one so that have the
priority
and I'm not going to do the drawing here
because
um periodically clear our bit part is
kind of complicated like you don't know
how often it happens right
okay so that's
um not the recently used one
and there's one called fifo so it's
first in first out
so basically you're going to keep the
list ordered by time
and evict the oldest one this is easy to
implement
and but the question is
if the page is old
doesn't mean it's not important right so
for example if you think about
well never mind yeah but
oh this doesn't necessarily mean
it's not important
and that's the sort of drawback
um
for this algorithm
Okay so
I actually want to do the same example
using fifo
so let's do that
so yes
so I'm going to create the same table
so this is
so this is fifo
so it says X
s
it
effect
and cash
and it's zero one two zero one three
zero three one two one okay
so
the first first three axis will be the
same and if you miss miss
and you're going to put these entries in
order
so um let's do something like this so
after reading zero the cast is going to
be zero and after reading one
you're going to shift it by one
so
in this case
uh like a one on the left is older and
one right is newer right
and it is the same so it'll be zero one
two okay
uh this so if you want to read zero
that's in cash so that's cash hit you
don't have to evict anything you keep
the cash
so now
okay so okay
one is also in cash you do this
what happens if you want to read three
well
uh
you have to evict something
and because we're using fifo order
we are going to evict the oldest
page entry
in a page table which is this one
right
so this one was the oldest
so I'm going to evict 0 so this is cache
Miss
and the page table is going to look like
one
two three
so this is different from the often
policy right it's optimal policy
but also the optimal decision was to
evict too
but because we don't know and we're
using fifo we are kicking out zero which
is used here so this is it turns out to
be inefficient so this is going to be
cash Miss
and again we're going to kick out the
older one so it's just this one
so it's going to evict
one
two
three and you're going to bring zero
okay
so three is in cash it's hit
two three zero
uh one is not in memory so you have to
do
load again
this will be a cache Miss
you're going to evict this one
and then it will be three zero one
right
two again we just evicted two so
unfortunately we have to do it again
we're going to kick out three
so it'll be zero one two and finally one
is in gas so this is Cash hit
and
yeah
so you can see the clear difference in
here right so
in the optimal policy
uh
there are a bunch of hits around here
and you don't really have to evict
twice
but in five four because you don't know
what's going to happen in future you
might evict
one that
um is used right after
and that are going to increase the rate
of page Folds
okay
so this is fifo
not that complicated right
so
the problem with
fifo was that
the old old entry doesn't mean you don't
need it
so how can we how we can implement it
sorry how we can improve it is to modify
the algorithm slightly to make it a
second chance algorithm
so we're going to use the reference bit
again
and so we're going to
basically do the fifo until
um you have to evict an entry
so you sort things in order
like this
and
when you um
evict the page
instead of just picking the entry that's
at the top of the
um
list
you're going to evict the page whose
reference bit is zero
so if RB is true that means that's
referenced recently so you don't want to
evict that so you're going to avoid the
problem
and
okay
so if
the orbit is zero you can evict it and
yeah if the orbit is set
you actually put the page at the end of
the list and you're going to reset the
um
reference bit
so even if
old the reference bits are true
you're basically are going to go over
the list and turn all the bits false so
you get the um
there is no one I you decide to evict
the original one
and yeah sorry
why don't we look at the modified bit
didn't even know
uh why we use reference speed not the
modified bit
any idea
right yeah you're right yeah
because modification is a reference
right yeah yeah
yeah sure do you have a question
yeah it takes the
one that was originally at the top
the oldest
is it cute yeah
so okay so this is good
but one downside is that you're gonna
have to
um move the page around right so you're
gonna have to
basically check the first
um element in a queue and if the
reference speed is one
you have to copy it to all the way back
to the queue so this is inefficient so
there is a way to improve that so this
clock algorithm
will basically achieve the same thing
without
um
without moving around the pages
and okay I forgot to mention
but
so in Project four you're gonna have to
implement three page replacement
algorithms so it's fifo
clock this one and least recently used
so
um anyway so the idea is
you're gonna have to implement this so
okay
so
okay so I should I think I should
explain
the clock algorithm first
so you're going to have
a memory in circle
like you can think of like taking a
modulo by the length of the list right
and if the page fault occurs
the page hand
the page the hand is pointing to is
inspected so in this case this we're
going to inspect this C
and we do the following depending on the
status of the reference bit if reference
speed is zero you evict this page and if
reference speed is one you clear this
reference bit and Advance hand which
means you're going clockwise so the hand
moves to C to D
so I want to do the example
here
in camera
so this is
clock
and
then I'll do a slightly different
example so but the still size equals
three
so you're going to have
um
actually
I'm going to be using pencil because I
want to erase things
yeah okay
so first
we're gonna need
three
cash entries
so one two
three
and you make it
a circle like this
okay
and
we're going to get access
like this zero
four one
four two four three
four
two four okay
so first
the hand
okay
this is inconvenient
okay so suppose that this eraser is a
hand right so it's the first hand
is pointing to this node
and we want to load zero so what's going
to happen is we are going to load
page zero
into here
and we move the hand to the next entry
okay
so now next we need four so we load four
here
okay
number four here
and remove the hand
next is going to be one same thing
right
sorry can't see it
so now we've completed those three steps
uh so next we want to read four and that
is in memory so you can just do it right
check
so next you want to read two
that is not in page table
so what's going to happen
is I'm going to it's okay so okay so
here
so it's the hand is pointing to this one
so we're going to check the reference
bit of this entry
and because we didn't reference this
node
this is the one we're going to evict
so I'm just going to replace 0 with
two
and remove the hand
to here because we just wrote
to the entry right
so now two is done
so next is four
right
okay so I actually made a mistake so
let's step back
and
well okay so nevermind sorry
when
we are here
uh we were like this right
so we read four so we have to set the
reference bit of this entry so I'm just
going to write
R here
to denote that reference speed is set
for this entry
so now so we're going to read two so we
place this one
we move the hand to here
and okay so we read four again but and
so we have to read the reference bit but
because it's already set you don't have
to do anything
or a set again right so if you complete
these steps
and then in the next step we're gonna
have to read three that is not in cash
so
the hand
is pointing to this node
but we cannot evict this page because of
the reference speed because we read we
referenced this node earlier
we decide not to evict this one
so we move the hand
and now so this one
is not referenced so this is the one
we're going to evict
so it'll be three
check
s and okay so we move the hand again
here
so 4 is in cash you can do it
to
uh is in cash no problem we set the
error
and four is in cash so
yes so that's important right so suppose
that
somehow we end up in this situation
right so two three four in cash and
they're all referenced and if you want
to load for example one
right so here oh actually so I forgot to
erase the reference bits all right okay
so that's a problem anyway so if you
want to load page one
this one is referenced so we cannot
evict this one we moved hand
and we remove the reference bit
okay
so we keep doing this so this one is
also referenced so I'm going to erase
the reference speed move the hand
this one's also referenced
remember the bit and then you come back
to this one
and this one's not I mean this one was
the reference but it's no longer so you
leave this one and change it to one yeah
okay
did I not I'm sorry
okay yeah look at my new right yeah you
moved hand
yeah so you just
yes
okay
uh
so that is
clock page replacement algorithms
and as far as I understand
it works the same as second chance
okay so the next one is called
lru or least recently used
and
so
the there are variations to this and but
I want to do I want to First do the
actual
lru with the examples I'm just going to
switch back to camera I'm sorry
so
yeah so I actually looked it up and it
seems that
it's like a design choice
so you can either set the reference
speed to one or zero when you load a new
entry
yeah it
yes yeah it'll be different
uh can we talk about it later because I
want to agree on that
Okay so
moving on so I want to do
where are you cash
so
I'm gonna just gonna use the same
table here
okay
so okay and I'm gonna have to write this
if they want to
okay
so
lru
so the first is going to be Mrs cash
misses
and
because it's lru
it's gonna be
I mean it's similar to fifo
but um basically
entries are on the left
or at least recently used so this is
least recently used
and one on the right is the most
recently used page so
okay
so here
I'm going to read page zero
so this is Cash hit right
you do not evict anything but the
difference between
so difference between this algorithm and
others is that
because you reference this
and you want to know which page was
least recently used you're going to have
to modif okay remember which page was
referenced like in order
so what I'm gonna have to do is I'm
going to move this zero to most recently
used area
so it will be one two zero
does it make sense because we access
zero
uh
we want to say that zero was the most
recent
ly used page
so the same thing for here so this is
Cash hit
but you move things around so it'll be
two zero one right
okay so next
we need page three sorry yeah
um
order is important because one on the
left is this is a least listen to used
one this is the most recent used one so
this is the order in which the page is
used
Okay so
we need page three
not in cash so this is cache Miss
and we're gonna evict the recent least
recently used
page that is two
so two and then
um it'll be
zero one three
so
moving on zero is in cash so it'll be
one
three zero so you move 0 here
let's hit
three
is Cash hit
you move it to the right so it'll be one
zero three
right
and
great
yes
so one is in memory so this is hit
and this is gonna be so one you want to
move one to the right so it'll be zero
three one
and two is not in memory so you're going
to evict zero so you're gonna fix zero
so this is cache Miss
and it'll be three one
two
and this is catch hit
and you move one so it should be three
two one
okay
makes sense
so this is
the you know naive implementation
second
so what I did in this example is really
expensive and the reason is whenever you
access the page you're gonna have to
like reorder stuff right
and because your computer
access memory
very frequently
if you naively do that like that's too
expensive and there are a couple of ways
you can approximate about you using some
clever techniques
so one way to do that is to use the
hardware array
so um basically we're going to associate
the counter with each page
and at each
um
reference increment the counter and
evict page with lowest counter and you
can do it using this clever rule so in
Hardware you keep and by NRA for n pages
so if you have n pages
um you're going to create like N squared
entries
and upon reference page K put ones in
the row K and zeros in column k
and after doing this when you have to
evict something you can choose
the one that's least recently used by
picking the smallest binary value
corresponds to the page
and this can be relatively easily done
in Hardware
so I don't know if you guys can see this
but I'm just gonna go over
so here
at time step 0
we want page zero like we access page
zero
so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to put once
in row zero so this is this row
so I'm just going to set one one one one
okay
and then put zeros in column zero so
it's this one and we set once first so
it's gonna be one one one one and then
we zero zero zero zero so it'll end up
something like this
and then in the next step
we access page one so we do the same
right so we change we set
every element in row one
to be one so reset one one one one
and we said column one to zero it's like
this
so we keep doing this so if it's two
set ones zeros right and if it's three
set it once and zeros
so for example suppose that we have to
evict a page at this step
what we're going to do is we're going to
read those binary numbers
and so in this case this one is zero and
this one is what like one two four eight
so this is eight I think but as you can
see the smallest one is this one
so you're going to evict zero and it
turns out to be the least recently used
one right because this is the one that's
used at least recently
so by using this Hardware like Matrix
you can implement lru
with counter efficiently
is it okay
so now
um
I mean it's we're not counting zeros or
ones we're evaluating like we're reading
each row as a binary number
so here
the smallest number
yeah so
you're bad
about your simple ones to mark
like the most recently used yeah
what columns you wipe out the other one
yes
it is kind of clever right
yeah
and but this require additional Hardware
in your
like computer like in a machine
and if you do not want to
you know take up space by that component
you can use software implementation
and
so the algorithm described in this slide
is called Aging algorithm
and this is
not strictly the same as lru which I
described earlier but it's like
approximates it
so what's going to happen is we keep a
string of values of the reference bit
for each clock tick
and after tick
with shift bits right and add new
reference bit on the left
okay so I think it doesn't make sense
without taking a look at the example
so suppose
that we have six pages zero zero through
five
and at this time
the reference bits are this stage so
page 0 is referenced page one is not
page two is referenced
going forward and
we're going to create a
like entry like this
so in the first step we'll just have to
modify the most significant bit to be on
those bits so for page 0 because it's
referenced you set the most significant
bit to be one
and page two it's not reference so if
you keep it zero
page two is referenced
right and
so the reference bits are cleared at
clock cycle so I clock interrupt
so
after you
sort of write those bits this Arrow bits
are clear
and you let the system run for a while
and so I don't know like some
milliseconds after
so during those time
uh I think zero page zero one and this
one is referenced
so what we're going to do is first we
are going to spit shift right by one
so this will be like zero one zero zero
zero
right
and we change the most significant bit
to those reference bits so for example
this one so we change we beat shift
right this will be zero one zero zero
zero zero and we set the most
significant bit to one so it'll be one
one zero zero zero
and
so you keep doing this
and you can check
the
smallest number
so you evict the smallest number right
so because
if the page is referenced recently
um like for example if the page is
referenced between the clock interrupts
the most significant bit will be one
so
basically larger number means
um
that page is referenced recently
so in the the reverse of that is if the
number is small that means that's not
referenced recently yeah it's on the
beginning all the strings would be
because in this example like all like
the entire string is like defined like
it's all zeros yeah
so when you load a new page I think
those are initialized to zeros because
it's not reference right
yeah okay so yeah if you think of this
as well but it's fixed in width right
I mean you can't bit shift between right
so yeah so I said string it's a string
of zeros and ones up to a certain length
so
yeah so I think it's like you know so in
this case it's like what 8 bit
so it's like one byte
so you can think of it as an integer
basically
any other questions okay
so and this is not exactly
lru
because
um basically if those bits are one that
means those pages are referenced
sometime in between those two steps
right but there's actually an order
there must be order but we don't know
the order so but um you can implement
this is much more efficient than
actually keeping track of the order
and you don't really have to do that
okay
so I guess those are page replacement
algorithms and next thing I want to talk
about is what's called working set model
so
the idea is that
in your program
you have access to a bunch of variables
right
but usually
you do not access to
um like all of them
you just access some of them right
so there can be a variable that's
defined and your program has access to
but you don't you just don't access and
maybe that's required sometime later in
the process but yeah
so
demand paging
means
um
so okay
imagine you're starting a program right
so let's say
um
you start your project one
implementation bobcat
that will access a bunch of variables so
for example that will probably read
um ARG V right
so and because arcv is not reference
because you're just starting that's
going to cause a page fault
and you probably need a buffer and that
will also cause a
page fault and demand paging says
the demand paging just means um
load pages on demand
so
if you employ demand paging at the
beginning of the program you get a bunch
of page faults and as the time goes on
the rate at which you encounter page
fold will decrease because you know you
already loaded a bunch of stuff
and
but you can make sure that the memory
required for the process is already in
Cache and that's called pre-paging so
basically you know loading the necessary
page to Cache
and there's another keyword called
thrashing
and that it basically means if the
memory is too small to contain the
working set so working set is the pages
you your program needs to make progress
and if the memory is too small
you'll basically have to you get paid
for it all the time and that's like a
really inefficient state
so
right
so we can think of the size of the
working set as a function of K so
actually
I actually think this diagrams really
um hard to understand so I also want to
do an example
so
let's do that
so we're talking about
working set
and
okay
so
so walking set is a set of pages that
your program needs to like make progress
okay then suppose let us Define w
the function that takes two things k and
t
and let it be
the number of
pages
used
by
K most
recent
memory references
so
you don't really know which pages are
needed by the program right
so one way to approximate that is
you
[Music]
basically keep track of recent memory
access
and so you instead of constant k
and if the page is accessed
in the past K references
you say that that page is in um
in the working set
so for example
suppose that
suppose the system needs pages in like
this
and suppose that we're at here
and we're going to call it like
T right
so
the working set
w
of 1T
means number of pages used by
the most recent memory reference
so if this is one
so this is one
because
the working set
is a Singleton set of four right
so this is
the one most recent memory references
and its size is one
okay
so what if
2T
so it is the working set
is two most recent memory references
so it will be three and four right
so the size of this set
is going to be 2.
and because this is a set
there's no like a duplicated elements
right
so even if we change it to two from two
to three
or the working set is still three and
four
so
um
there are size of the working set is
still two
so
notice here
as you increase k
it will only increase right there's no
way that element
in the working set it's gonna like
disappear basically
if
right
so if I do k equals 4
it'll be three because I now have two
three four
but there's no way
um for example this four is disappeared
as we increase
the K right
so that is actually what
this means
so
so this is a graph
of that function and as you increase the
k
basically it will
increase
and
you know
because the memory is limited
it doesn't go like all the way up to
Infinity you know
saturate at some point
so this is behavior of working set as a
function of K
and
so basically we can use
um
this model
uh
to
decide which page to evict
so
we basically keep track of
the recent page references
and if
the page is in the working set that's
the page
your process needs to make progress so
you want to keep it and if the page is
not in the working set that means that's
probably not required so you're just
gonna um so right away
[Music]
so I guess two things to note here is
that you have to
um your operating system have to keep
track of which pages are in The Working
set
and you know you're gonna have to have a
storage for that
and another thing is this can be
expensive
um
right yeah this can be expensive and
also you have to pick K and
basically the size of the working set
may vary for each process
so picking Decay is not trivial
and you could also use Virtual time
instead of number of references
um
right so yeah
the
the K was the sort of
how much
in in past you look for right and it
doesn't have to be uh
reference is it can be some notion of
time
and
because CPU has um those like virtual
times the notion of notion of virtual
time you can also use that
so yeah so here's the um
diagram
for how operating system might Implement
working set replacement algorithm
yeah and some of the weaknesses or you
need to scan the entire page table
at each page fault to find a victim
right
so I think that was
the overview of page replacement
algorithms so there are a couple of I
mean I didn't cover all of them but
they're all described in a textbook
fairly
in detail so I highly recommend you read
the textbook
and
yep
okay
when does the class end
so I guess that was everything I wanted
to talk about today in terms of this
slides
so we have to run it first because
optimal is
like impossible to yes yeah
um
well I think so yeah because you can do
that right so you can um
always
like a record
the order
in which the you know I mean which we
can just record
the pages that are like requested
right and you can just
use it
to
yeah
but you need a like a workload
to do that right yeah
and actually coming up with a workload
can be tricky because it's not random
right so
um
you have to have a program that you want
to optimize for anything
or you can use an array right
no even if the you don't know the size
you can still use linked list because
you can have an array of pointers right
bonding like if you already know the
size then a ring makes more sense than
yes
but we usually know the size of cash
right because
yeah
so I think using array makes more sense
for assignment it doesn't matter
yeah so for the assignment I'm more
interested in correctness than
performance
so
you can
use whatever data structure you want to
use
okay
if there is no questions I think we can
let you go yeah
uh we actually haven't started graded
yet
and that is
um yeah for reasons but
we'll try to
finished grading by
early next week
like as soon as possible but that's the
sort of realistic timeline
sorry I
saw your Piazza questions didn't have
time to answer
up