um where in the system the key and the
value resides so
um
yeah so suppose that you have this
overlay Network or distribute hash table
and it has a bunch of computers there
right
and imagine it's like a bit trained and
you store
um
like movie data in this hash table so
key is the title of the movie and value
is it's like MP4 data right
and so this hash table needs to support
um two operations just like project four
it needs to be able to insert data
so in this case
um insert Star Wars and you should be
able to
save data to this hash table and you
also need to be able to find data so if
you want to watch Star Wars you do look
up of Star Wars and
um you should be able to get data out of
it and because it's hashtable we will be
using
um hashed value of this key
and
right
so the question is if you want to do
insert or lookup it doesn't really
matter
um suppose that you want to watch
um Star Wars right and you
can do you can call your hash function
and pass the title of the movie Star
Wars and that will give you the hashed
value the K right so the question now is
given this hash
how can you find a computer in this
system that stores
um
the movie beta of
um Star Wars
right
so in this case
it's this computer and your job is to be
able to find this computer just by
looking at this game
and
yeah so you need a way to Route this
request
to this computer
okay
so
in today's lecture we'll be talking
about pastry which is one specific
implementation of dhtp but other
distributed hash table implementations
work quite similarly
okay
so in pastry each node gets assigned an
ID
and it's 128 bit string that is placed
in the following range so
um
you are given so each node has its 128
bit ID you can think of it as like IPv6
address
each node has its unique ID
and your key is 164-bit so it's a little
bit larger but you can use a hash
function to get reduce it to 128 bit
so
in pastry we imagine this circular
um space
so in this case
zero is here
and because the address space is 128 bit
the maximum value is possible is 2 to
the power of 128 minus 1. and it's here
and
basically
each node and each key gets assigned
to somewhere
on this ring
so in this case node ones here node two
is here and key ones here K2 is here
everything good so far
okay
so now
um
basically
given the key so this key one belongs to
node one because node one is the closest
node
um that's located on the ring right so
because q1 is here
um
the data of q1 is saved at node one and
similarly
so you take a hash of key two and you
look for the closest node
and you basically save that key to this
node so
like this
and by doing this
each key gets assigned to some node and
that node will store data for that key
and value
okay
so
the question is
um
given the key
how can we find the node
that has that key
so imagine you're or
just a your node that's somewhere on on
this ring
and you have the key that you want to
look up
right
how you can do that yeah
and
the places
are indexed yeah
go to wherever
yeah right
yeah so
um
yeah that's right that's one way of
doing it so one way of doing it is to
have a global index and every node
basically has a list of all the other
nodes right so if you have a list of all
participating nodes then you can just
calculate the hash of key
and it was just no
um which node is the closest right and
you can just send a request to that node
the problem with that approach is that
um
okay so yeah if you know all the
information about precipitive
participating nodes you can send a
request just by one hop right
this is great but that means all nodes
have to maintain all the other nodes
and because this is distributed system
um the nodes are not fixed right
sometimes sometimes nodes might leave
the system sometimes it knows new nodes
comes in and you have and every time
the sort of topology changes you have to
update the information and that can be
expensive right so that's probably not
what you want to do
another approach is to basically
create a linked list so imagine this
ring as a doubly linked list
and each node maintains its neighbors so
everyone knows who's
left
to the node and who's right to the node
so if you do that approach you only have
to maintain
two accuracy sorry two pointers right so
the storage used is o1
but that slows down the lookup because
in the worst case you have to go through
the entire ring right
so
um you know suppose you are here and if
you want to get
data
in here you basically have to relay
information like
all the way and that can be slow yeah
Okay so
node is a computer
key is just data
and we take hash value sorry we we take
a hash of key to basically map the key
into the same like address space
so we can calculate the closest node to
that key
yeah
multiple keys
well no so
sorry could you repeat one thing
H node is a computer yeah
no so key so we're talking about hash
table right so everything is a key value
and
you basically want to store
key value pairs
in a distributed way right so you want
to distribute
data over
number of nodes yeah
yeah um
yeah yeah so
so suppose that um you know in this node
one so key one is Star Wars right so
then
um some other movie
I don't know like Indiana Jones
it doesn't have to be have it doesn't
have to have the same key but it doesn't
the hash value has to be close to the
address of node one
so
you know node one is responsible for all
the keys around like this area
so Star Wars mind map to this here and
then that if that's the case node one
saves the data for Star Wars but some
other movie
the hash value of some other movie title
may have value similar to like those
right
and
if that's the case then node one will
also store that data yeah sorry
yeah so when you take a hash right it'll
just be
an integer I mean it's a number right
it's a binary right so you can just um
calculate like yeah
so yeah what's the range a good point so
um
the key is stored in the closest node so
basically like
how can I explain
okay so okay okay so can I annotate this
yeah
so okay
so suppose that
um
well let me think
Okay so
okay so two to the one 28th is like too
large so suppose that everything is 32
right
to make it simpler so
all the value like this address space is
32 like 31 okay so suppose that
this node one
has address 6.
and node 2
has address
Ed I don't know 10.
okay
so if key one
value is five
then this node one is the closest node
right because it's the difference is
just one
so this key one
is saved at node 1.
ok
suppose the key to
is
has value eight
well let's not do eight
um
nine
so the closest node is either Node 1 or
node two but the difference
between nine and ten is one right
but
the distance here is three
so we choose node two to store key2 does
that make sense so if the key was like
seven it'll go to node one
the key idb 164 bits because doesn't
that mean you have a lot of keys yeah
you're right so um
I'm not sure actually but I think in
reality
we'll probably just use like first 128
bit or maybe take another hash take
because we have to
well
yeah
um
right
um well it doesn't matter you just have
to decide which one to pick like you
know but it there has to be a rule right
there has to be one way to interpret
that so if we decide node 8 goes to node
one then all the keys in the middle has
to go
make it smaller one but yeah yeah it
doesn't really matter
okay yeah sorry
these are the I
the ID and the key
ID yeah essentially
okay
so what was I talking about um yeah so
we were talking about
the information each node has to store
right so
um
yeah so if you if each node
knows about all the other nodes you can
do
basically one hop
to get to any key
but that's expensive in that you have to
keep track of all the all the
participating nodes
if you just store constant number of
pointers like you know yeah sorry if you
extort one on the right and one on the
left you can do linear search so
um the you have to store all one
information but the time to search the
key becomes o-n yeah sorry
the one master computer sort of and
it does kind of
kind of year but this master computer
remember everybody all the all the keys
locations yeah so then you could go to
the master
yeah so
like
yeah yeah so yeah that's defeats the
purpose of P2P right but in some
situation that's allowed and that gives
you performance right
um but
at the same time that
um that primary server can be a single
point of failure right so if the primary
server goes down then
you won't be doing anything right so
there's a trade-off
Okay so
yeah so we were talking about like how
we can route requests and I talked about
two strategies so one is the store all
nodes and like this is similar to having
global index so if you do that you can
do one hop to get to any key
but you have to store on information
if you just store neighboring nodes you
have to do linear search so number hops
it becomes on but you can just store two
pointers which is a one
so the question is can we do
better or like we cannot do better but
can we take like a middle like
this o-n
is not quite good right so can we do
something
strike a balance between the two
and
yes there is a way and the basic idea is
to delete a binary search of nodes
okay so I'm just gonna
explain how that works
so um
the idea here
is that
we hop number of times
and every time you make a jump
you basically fix one letter in the
address
and the more hop you make the closer you
get to the key
so
suppose that your this node
and you want to find a data for this key
d46 A1C okay
so first
this node
knows one node that begins with the
first letter of address so in this case
d
so we don't know about the rest like
four six A1C part but we know one node
that starts with letter d
in this case it's this one
so it's closer right
so what's going to do happen is it will
just send request to this node
so it's one step closer okay
so now
this second node
knows
um a node that starts with D4 so that's
another one step closer
so in this case this one
so we don't know about two one three F
part
but we know that this node begins with
D4
so we make that jump and we're a step
closer to the goal
then this node
knows one node that starts with d46
so it's another step closer and we keep
doing this and eventually
we'll find a node that has the key we
were looking for
yes
no so the node has
it like
so yeah yeah so um
well so this request
is saying
find
sorry um
basically find the key that has to do
this right this value right
so when you request so when you receive
this request you can check if you have
this value right
and if you do you can just return the
response otherwise you have to forward
the request to the closer node
okay
and how many um how many notes does each
node know of then
uh
I'll talk about that in the next slide
okay so will you get that yeah right so
basically what happens in the first
um hop is that because this
um
this no sorry um this key begins with
letter d
we're going to basically
limit the search space into everything
every node that starts with d
and we don't know the exact range but we
know that we know one node that starts
with d
and this node
will basically
um
like make the search space even smaller
by forwarding the request
to a node that starts with D1 and we
keep doing this until we find data
so the question is what
information does each node have to store
so
this is
the routing table
that this node 65 A1 FG which is this
node needs to maintain okay
so first
um
well so
in this case
we had a request that begins with d
and we have to know one node that starts
with d right and a similar thing can
happen
with an address that begins with one two
three and so on
so in the top row
of this table
is basically all the nodes that begins
with certain like number so we know one
node that starts with zero we know one
node that begins with one and so on
and we use this to um like a make a
request right
and another so the second row basically
says so because this node begins with
six
we may receive a request that begins
with six right so this can be this node
can be a representative node
for all the addresses that begins with
six
so we need to be able to forward the
request to one step closer
so we have to know all the nodes that
start with
sorry we have to know some node that
starts with six zero six one six two and
so on yeah so the basic idea is that
instead of remember instead of each
having each node remember so instead of
having each node remember the exact
nodes you have each node kind of
remember properties of the node so like
it can remember that okay there's one
with there's something with a d there's
something with there's something with
five or four yeah yeah
unbelievable
no peer-to-peer is not related to Hash
table so hash table is just a data
structure we want to construct
um in a distributed system and you can
have a distributed hash table that is
not peer-to-peer right like as he was
saying we can have a primary server that
has all the information or something
like that
so yeah
mm-hmm
what is the
box oh right um let me explain in the
next slide okay
so
but you get this idea right so basically
you have
you have a list of notes that begins
with one letter two letter three letter
and so on
so what we want to know is
okay let me second
okay so we want to know is how many
number of hops this system will need and
how much storage it will need right
so in terms of the number of hops as I
was saying it's basically doing a binary
search I mean okay every time you make a
hop the search space gets like
one of the 16th right so
because you make one hop you fix one
letter
so you narrow the search Space by a
factor of 16.
and you keep doing this right so I mean
it's not binary search but it's like
16 version of binary right
so the number of steps or the number of
hops required is basically log 16 log
base 16 and hops where n is the number
of nodes
well
in a way it is sorted right
the keys are sorted right and
so
so in the first hop
you are going to send a request to a
node that starts with d right
and it is this node's job to figure out
the rest
so we basically reduce the search space
from
well so they're like so at the beginning
there are like 16
to the power of six like possible
addresses right but by for sending this
request to this we narrow the search
space to 16.
to the five
does that make sense yeah yeah okay
you know it has that
you can't just uh automatically insert
these
like insert your
um d46 and
start from there like is there any
reason you have to
is there any reason you have to do
the big hop then do four then make a hop
wait what do you mean so so what can you
do here so
you know a node that starts with d right
yeah but we don't know anything more
about
addresses that starts with d right
uh wait why don't we
because all the other roles start with
six right for example in this case
wait are you saying that we know for a
fact there's no like e nodes Maybe
what do you mean
like obviously we're starting from a
sixth note and then and then like
like like from six five a1m what's FC
yeah like basically what I'm saying is
like why do we not know why would we not
know that a d46 doesn't exist already
well so it might exist right
but
um in general it doesn't because so
um
[Music]
we want
but in this
neo4601c yeah
and then basically
yeah what I'm saying is why can't you
just why can't you just automatically
use d46
no because you don't know which node has
the
5A right
because you know one node that begins
with d but you don't know anything else
about addresses that begins with d
so that's the information you have to
keep track of
like let's say
9B board doesn't exist
or does exist well so if you
what did you say name
four like like yeah
so if you want to look for something
that begins with 9b4
you stand
a request to this node right
so this node has can figure out
[Music]
um
basically everything that starts with
nine
and
I mean this is all the information this
node has about address that start with
nine
so all this node can do is to let this
node figure out the rest
okay
so instead of thinking of the node
thinking of the nodes as like entire
streams they're thinking of them just
like here
yeah
okay so okay so
so let's say we are looking for 9 B4
right
um
so we have we have no choice but to send
this request to this address right and
this address
maybe 94 but may not be 9 before right
and suppose that this address was 9
see something right
so
but this node
knows where to okay so in this node node
the address that starts with B 9B right
because this is second right so in the
second row
of this node
we know
all the nodes
that starts with six something right so
in this node this node knows every this
node that starts with nine
something right so they can forward
request in the right direction
okay
like this yeah yeah yeah it knows
yes
yeah and then
uh
yeah I mean it's this row right
yeah but he also knows old notes that
starts with six something yeah
yeah yeah
yeah going on the way
yeah so it's storing a lot of
information but how much right so
how much information
like how big is this table
I mean there's this answer but
right so um
yeah we're writing in HEX
so I mean so the number of columns is
fixed right we just have 16 columns for
each row and how many rows we need well
it's log base 16n right
because yeah
where
oh I think it's just type or I mean this
x means some address so
um yeah
we know address
of node that starts with letter f
okay
this is a mix
does this make sense
okay
I don't know I feel like I'm terrible at
explaining this so
let me know if you have any more
questions later
so um actually so this concludes our
discussion of how this would be hash
table but um yeah I think it's
interesting so if you think about this
table we basically have o log n all
again
um in these two cells
and in general that's a good balance
right and I don't think we can beat that
because
yeah
okay
so that's that
and we will move to this discussion of
container
so
yeah container is a focus of project
five so I think it's worth going over
these slides
and
well so container is kind of a
just a you know
type of software but in this lecture
we'll focus on Docker which is the most
popular container solution
so what is Docker well
Docker is an open source project
that automates the deployment of
applications inside software containers
by providing an additional now layer of
abstraction automation sorry abstraction
and automation of operating system level
virtualization on Linux so yeah
when you say container it usually means
on Linux I think there's a thing called
Windows containers but it's not really
popular So when you say container it
usually means container on Linux
so here's a little history of Docker so
it started as a DOT Cloud project yeah
so it's a
platform as a service provider and yeah
so it roughly started around 2013 and
it's released right down the same time
and I think in the past Docker was open
source now it's closed Source I mean
it's some some parts of Docker is open
source but now it's closed closed those
but it had a lot of stores when it was
open source and yeah so and Dot Cloud
the company behind Docker was
basically it was a platform as a service
provider so it was like you know cloud
service provider but they switched their
business to
um container Solutions
in 2013.
and here's a short list of features that
Docker has so it is comparative virtual
machines it is lightweight
so it has minimum overhead or on CPU IO
and Network
it is based on Linux containers it uses
layered file system to save space
and uses a copy on write file system to
track changes
it is portable
which means that it can well a container
can run on any Linux system that
supports something called lxc
and
um
yeah so
I think in the very first era of Docker
it only supported like special type of
Linux distributions but now it's
supposed everywhere supported everywhere
Raspberry Pi even can run docker
and
yeah
it says possible future support of other
operating systems on this slide but
like for example we have Docker desktop
now so I think Windows and Mac
are supported now yeah
is it more lightweight than WSL
uh
uh no because Docker desktop for Windows
requires WSL inside
so it's kind of different layer so in
order to use Docker you need to have
Linux running
underneath
so
yeah it's kind of different layer of
abstraction yeah
right
right I think I'll talk about that for
the rest of the slides so um if you can
wait a little bit
and yeah I'll be happy to take questions
after the lecture okay
so and another thing is called
self-sufficient so that means
um well the letters are too small but it
says Docker container contains
everything it needs to run and
um it has OS libraries and Frameworks
and applications so it has everything
you want for um basically you want to do
so you just you can just download
container and it just runs and does
whatever
you want it to do
so here's a yeah sorry
yeah so
um yeah I'll go over but um Linux
containers share the kernel right so in
a way it doesn't have the kernel so it's
not iOS but at the same time like when
you say OS
um
it means more than kernel right so for
example like if you say
so you know Windows is an OS and it has
Windows kernel but it has you know
Windows system or you know Internet
Explorer like Microsoft Edge now
um that's also part of the OS right so
um if you count that as OS then
container has all the you know software
that's required as an OS so
in a way it has some parts of like upper
layer of os but not the kernel yeah
so here's a little background of um
Docker and why it was needed so um
so basically
um
in like if you're developing a web
service or something
um you have a bunch of components that
you need to deploy right so you have
might have an ecstatic website your
company website and you might have
database you might have queue you might
have database like analytics analytical
database that's different from you know
transactional database you might have
API web front and back-end workers and
so on and you have to run all these
different components in a different
um like environment so if you're working
on your personal laptop to develop one
of those things you have to have you
know development virtual machine
and
you know once you're done with
developing you might have Corey
Assurance people that checks your code
and make sure it's all working and then
when it sits then you might want to
deploy that code to public cloud or your
customer data center or then you know
once the service gets bigger you might
want to shift it to production cluster
and if it's open source project then you
must run on contributors laptop
and basically all of these components
must run on all of these environments
and this is the you know product right
so you know you can make a table here
and
it's like basically M by n Matrix and
it's really complicated to maintain all
these environments and making sure all
of these um work properly
and so the analogy made in this context
is a cargo transport before 1960s
where
um you know we're on a transport cars
and
you know pianos and so on all of those
have different shapes
and we want to transport those those
through you know ships and trains and so
on and we basically have to
think how we can carry a car without
scratching it right and
basically the same idea
and it also forms a matrix from hell and
a solution in the transport industry was
to basically standardize the container
right so we have this one
thing called the container that's fixed
size and
basically you have to think how you can
fit one of these things into this
container
and then all of these other you know
forms of transformation needs to support
this one type of container
so
this is
M plus n
things you have to do right which is
much better than n times n
and yeah so Docker is basically a
container for code not the
things you want to carry around and so
what's going to happen is you create a
container for website DB front end queue
and such and pack it as a container
and this container will run on any of
these platforms
so it solves the problem
so here's a little bit of architecture
so
when you say docker
you sometimes mean you know refer to the
docker command so that's a CLI and
that's the sort of front end of the
entire system and Docker CLI talks to
Docker Daemon that's running
in background and that does the um
well that's all the
complex things underneath and there's
Docker registry that's also running
underneath
there's this thing called Docker Hub and
that is a cloud service where you can
upload container
and those containers can be downloaded
and to run certain like applications
or you can use those images as a base to
create your own container
and yeah so don't have those all these
and
there's Docker image
that's basically like a template that
has all source code and dependencies and
from images you can create a Docker
container that's running instance of a
machine
so
so okay so what is Docker container well
so Docker container is a unit of
software delivery and container runs
everywhere
um in particular it runs regardless of
Kernel version well I mean it's it
doesn't run on any kernel version but as
long as the kernel is
sufficiently new it will probably run
and it runs regardless of hostile
distribution so if you want to install
software directly on your machine
there were
a command you need to run to install on
Ubuntu made different from
I don't know Red Hat Centos but if you
use Docker container you don't have to
worry about those things
I guess one caveat is that container and
host architecture must match so
um I guess this is a quite a little bit
different from virtual machine where
virtual machine can execute the code for
different
um
architecture through emulation sometimes
but in Docker you have to have you have
to have the matching container for your
host architecture so yeah
and you can run anything
basically and yeah those things
so Docker container is Created from
Docker image
and yeah so it is not a virtual hard
drive it is not a file system it is a
read-only layer of files it doesn't have
state
it's basically a top file it has a
hierarchy I think I have a better slide
on my um TS slides which I'll show later
so here's a little difference between
virtual machines and containers so in a
virtual machine
I think the professor will talk more
about full virtualization next week
but if you're using virtual machines
um
you have host OS the OS running on your
computer and then on top of that there's
a thing called hypervisor and hypervisor
can run different osis at the same time
so here's guest OS fun here's guest os2
and these two OSIS
have its own binaries libraries and
application and
it would look like this
container
doesn't rely on hypervisor and it has
Docker image or container run sorry
Docker engine or container runtime
and on top of that we have no more
overseas and we'll just have
dependencies and application
so in a way this is more lightweight
because
you don't have to run multiple os's
right but at the same time virtual
machine
is sometimes useful so for example
um
if you use container your host OS must
match the operating system that this
application runs right so I mean in
reality everything has to be on Linux
but if you use virtual machine that can
change but so for example if you even if
you're on Windows you can run a Linux
virtual machine so that gives you more
power in a way
oh
here's another image but I think it's
basically saying the same thing so
you'll just skip it
and here's a list of commands that you
can use to manage Docker containers
so
at the beginning of the life cycle you
have Docker build command so there's a
file called Docker file it's like a
shell script that runs at the beginning
to initialize the container so that's
called Docker build
and then so this will create a Docker
image right
and next you can run sorry you can do
Docker run to create a container from an
image
and
yeah
and for reproduction you have Docker
commit to basically save the state of
running a container and save it as a new
image this Docker kill
uh
it's not listed here but there's a
command called Docker stop to stop the
container and stop the container can be
started using this command there's RM to
delete and also you can there's a
separate command called RMI to
um delete an image
yep
uh
why don't I switch to my ts slides and
talk about it it's okay
so okay
yeah so project five
um is about
um
creating a container runtime so you know
implementing a smaller version of um
docker
so I think it um
it makes sense
to talk about it a little bit
and I know some people came to TA
sections and I think we went through
these slides but so I don't know some
part of maybe repetitive sorry but um
I'm just going to talk about it a little
bit
so I think I already talked about this
okay
so the question was what exactly is uh
uh what exactly is
image right
does anyone have any good idea
[Music]
is supposed to be similar to that or
there's someone else you can draw to
that
but
I mean you could you could assume that
maybe it's like the image of the
container that's the thing yeah
it gives you an idea of what the
container has n't have okay do you want
to give a shot
okay so if you say blueprint I think
it's more close to Docker file because
that like tell us how to yeah
okay ISO
like a boot image right yeah
yes okay yeah sure I think okay that's
closer okay You Wanna Give a shot
yeah what's an image
sure
yeah
okay so I think
okay any other
attempts yeah
sure
let me think
what exactly is not Greenwich
resistance
so
okay okay so here's my answer um
in order to run
your application
you need
you okay so you first need an
application itself right so you know
imagine a c code
um
you need a binary right so that's one
thing you need
uh another thing you need is uh
dependency right so
it's hard to talk about dependencies in
C but for example if you imagine a
python right your python script might
import
I don't know numpy and that's dependency
right so in order for your application
to run
you have you you also so you have to
have all those things so
um you have to have your python script
your Python dependencies and also you
have to have python interpreter itself
right
um
Docker image
basically packages all of these
into
like a one unit
and that's we're calling it image
yeah
by one it's like
it's late it's just basically
yeah yeah okay so okay
so okay that's one thing I wanted to do
so let me do that so
I think it's just
it makes more sense if I just
um
use Docker right
so
I mean doku is like a platform and one
of the components is called Docker Hub
and
it's like GitHub
but GitHub is for source code right
Docker Hub is for containers so this is
helpful containers you can download one
of these images and you can use it so
um let's see here
so you have Alpine
Linux image and it's not application
it's just a lightweight
um OS sorry you can think of it as like
empty image
engine X is a web server so if you
download this image basically you have
a web server
right away
um visit box is another base image
Ubuntu OS and I think what
um it's easy to understand is this
python image so if I click on it
um
well so
this is an image that has python
interpreter built in yeah
yeah yeah so that's a good point yeah so
let's do that right so
here
we have something called tag and you can
think of it as a version
and there are a bunch of versions right
so but
um for example
let's see here
so you have
give me a second
okay so we have this image 3.11
well
yeah so okay
let's do that
so
okay so first let's run python 3.11
using Docker right so first here we're
going to docker
pull
and we can do python colon and whatever
one of these tags
so let's just do
um
well it's good
okay uh okay so 3.11 Alpine I think it's
good so 3.11
[Music]
Alpine
if I do that
that will download
something and I just downloaded an image
right
to create okay so let's do Docker images
and this will create a list of images
I have on your my on my computer and
as you can see
well
one of this is
three point Sorry python 3.11 Alpine and
this is the image ID
and I can start a Docker container from
this image by Docker run
uh python
3.11
alt point I think
is that right
three point
eleven open yes
and I actually have to add
um this well do I have to yeah
right so
I added bunch of options to
um like open a terminal but basically I
called this python command
inside this python container that's
created from python image and now I have
um python 3.113 running in the docker
container and I can do I don't know
print
one plus four five right
so
so yeah so this Docker image
has everything you need to run python
script which is python interpreter and
its standard libraries yeah
uh-huh we
need so is that like the same thing like
we'll we'll download like Microsoft
Office into
it yeah sure sure yeah so you know
because it's Linux it doesn't run uh you
know
office don't run but yeah basically yeah
basically that yeah
but um it's
well so if you compare this to sort of
installing things directly on host OS
this one so everything inside container
is
contained in the container right so for
example if I want to use python 3.11 on
my computer I just have to install it
but the problem is for example if I had
python 3.9 installed and if I want to
use Python 3.11 I might have to
delete 3.11 first right but if you're
using container everything is contained
so you can have you know a container for
3.9 container for 3.11 you can make
those things can coexist together
yeah I just okay
so far understanding but like so the
definitely you know to mentioned like so
an image you can just think of it as
like a collection of all like everything
and application all the dependencies in
the library needs to run
container is a way for you to create a
self-printed environment
so we can anything
the library's needs everything you need
and on the pencies
question
I'm like confused on like the difference
between docker file okay sure sure so
okay
um
let me see
so
Docker file
is like a blueprint of Docker image
and what do I mean by that is
um
docophile
describes how you can create an image
okay so let's see so
I should have prepared an example Okay
so
okay so this is a good one so
this is an example
of Docker file
and I think this Docker file creates a
container for
application written in JavaScript or
like node.js
so
in the first line we say create a image
based off of this node 18 Alpine image
so you know I was using python 3.11
Alpine this one's node 18 Alpine just
means
um
this image
this is a base image we'll use as a
basis and it has node.js installed okay
so now we're gonna set up the working
directory we're going to copy so suppose
that you have your application your
JavaScript application in the same
directory as Docker file if you run
Docker build this copy will
basically copy everything in your
directory to the new Docker image
and then inside that image it'll run
yarn install so it's like pip install so
it'll install all the dependencies
and
so in a way this specifies how you can
create an image from your source code
right
so yeah
okay so the question is did the
difference between Python virtual
environment and documents right so
it is similar right you want a
sort of
independent environment right so in a
way that's similar but if you use Python
virtual environment
what you can virtualize is python
version and its dependencies right if
you use Docker you can virtualize more
you can virtualize yeah
generalized version of Pi yeah
yeah
yeah that's a good analogy yeah
right no no no no so
um
that's not exactly right
um I think the purpose sorry the point
of using Docker is
to like have a container
and you can
um
I mean that container or image is
portable right so you can isolate it so
yeah so suppose that you didn't have
Docker right and if you have a python
script that runs on python 3.11
um if you didn't have Docker and if you
want to run your script on someone else
computer first thing you have to do is
to install python 3.11 on that computer
right
yeah but if you use a Docker yeah you
can just I mean your image has python
3.11 so you can just use it
but like does does every container have
like Linux pre-installed to it yeah
because container depends on features
that Linux kernel provide so it has to
be
like it has to run on top of Linux
kernel
uh so
well
no so there's no way
Linux container can run directly on
Windows
because those two things are completely
different right so you can think of a
container that runs on windows so um you
have Windows kernel and on top of that
you know you have a container and that
container can run on any windows that
something you can think of but um yeah
because it's a kernel so it has to have
the same kernel
and yeah so portability is the key and
so for example
[Music]
um
if you know um
Google Cloud run
this is
um sort of Google's
cloud
and here
you can upload a Docker image to run on
their server
so
you build a image and upload it to con
This Cloud run and this will run the
container for you
so um
you know you know you no longer have to
SSH into your server and install python
to install your Django application
okay
yeah so portability sticky
uh
okay any questions on doco yeah
what do you mean uh change what
yeah okay so
but doctors
because
um
well so
okay
so here I changed python from Tosh and I
have a shell inside Docker right
um I can do something like so everything
you see inside
um Docker is
contained in the container right so you
can make whatever changes inside the
container and that will not affect the
host OS
oh right right okay so that's something
you can also do so
um Docker yeah so Docker um
Okay so
yeah so
there is uh
where is V
yeah so there is uh dock around has this
volume option and you can use this
option to mount your host file system
inside the container
so if you do that
you'll have access to
the file system of the host machine
inside docker and that can do some bad
things if you want to
but by default it's a file system or
isolated
right
so
yeah so I'll talk a little bit about
projects because I think it's important
so
um
project five the goal of project five is
to implement a small container runtime
so you'll be able to use your program to
run Docker containers basically Docker
images basically and
your doc so there are a couple of things
it has to provide and first thing is
isolation so
as I was saying everything happens
inside docker
must not affect the outside system right
so it uses
um kernel features to do that and
you know fully fledged container
runtimes like Docker provides
isolation for all kinds of resources in
computer so
it can provide isolation for CPU memory
Network file system
and but you know doing all this is
impossible for this project so we'll
just focus on
two aspects of isolation processes in
the file system
and
so what do I mean by
um
separating so I providing isolation for
processes well so if you or
in
make your host OS and if you do
something like PSA
you'll see a list of processes running
on your computer right
but inside the container
you don't want those containers to be
able to see the processes that's running
outside the container
so actually if I do
open a cell in this Docker container and
if I do PSA
you see no processes that's running
outside the container so this is what I
mean by um providing isolation for
processes
and
um
Linux kernel
has this thing called PID namespace so
that's basically a you can create a
separate namespace for process ID
process IDs and this is how you can
prevent
processes inside the containers from
interfering with processes outside the
container
[Music]
your container runtime will also provide
isolation for file system and this is
called Mount namespace so it's
almost identical to PID namespace but
each process can have
um its own namespace for file system
so that's the idea
and
in order to create a new namespace you
use this clone system call so when you
call this clone it will create a new
process and it's similar to Fork but
it's more flexible and you can pass
options to say
create new namespace for PID and create
new space for Mount space
so you have to do that and
just like P thread create it takes a
function
to execute inside a process inside a new
process and you can pass a void pointer
that is the argument
to this function
and part of the assignment is to
basically store everything
your child process will need to this
container T struct so the process inside
the container will be able to execute
the command you're given
so
another thing you have to do and I think
this might give you a better idea of
what an image is is to um
well so here's the problem so container
image is a read only so what that means
is that
your container
cannot change files that are in
the image directly so you can have you
know let's suppose that you have
an image and you can have multiple
containers
from that image right if container a
changes the file in the image that will
affect container B in container C which
is not good right
so um
basically you want an image to be read
only but each container should be able
to change files
and the way we achieve this feature is
to use something called oval AFS
and
overlay FS
um
yeah so
there are there'll be three layers to
this overlay FS
there is a lower layer
where all files are read only
then on top of that there is a upper
layer
where you can write things
and then in the end at the top of the
layer is the overlay and you see sort of
the combined view of those two layers so
I think this image
um this describes it so
at the very bottom you have an image
layer and you have a couple of files
then on top of that you have a container
layer and this container layer is per
container so each container has this
layer
when you so at the root of each
container you have this merged View and
it basically sees files from both this
image layer and container layer
yeah sorry this question
in the local machine too like outside of
the container like like if we were to
happen are you talking about Dev
container four five four is going to
show up so wait are you talking about a
Dev container
so the container is a little bit
different because
um the point of they have a container
is to be able to run your code inside
um
inside the container right so the
container so okay
you want to use Dev container because
container has all the tools needed
for development right so in our case we
need clan we need you know Cloud format
make those things and everything is
installed in a container
and
you want to run your program
inside
the container and
that internally uses a volume so that's
a v option I was just describing to sort
of sync files inside the container and
outside the container this is a little
bit different
um this is about
um
sort of how you can like how you um
create
how you allow containers to make changes
while keeping the image read-only
okay
so
yeah so
I think I can
do this demo I did this demo
um
in my section but that's okay
container merged folder like merge
directory like your host computer
basically
it makes the changes to your computer
okay okay yeah
kind of similar that's similar that's
the image but not exactly how the the
container works but yeah it's similar
yeah yeah okay so let's do this example
so
okay as some people pointed out this
example runs only on Native Linux so if
you do that in your Dev container it
might not work
uh
apologize
so first thing we can do is to make
four directories lower upper work merged
okay
and this will create four directories
first thing we do is we create this is
in lower
file
in lower so
if I do this
so I enter her four directories
and I have file full inside lower and
this lower will be like a container
image
so next
I'll execute this command
to uh sorry
create
uh
sorry
it's probably your
um
okay so I executed this Mount command
and this created overlay file system
and we told it to use this lower
directory as lower dire and this upward
directory which is now empty as upper
directory and yeah so overlap have a
system requires some workspace so I just
said use this work directory
as that and then we Mount this
um created overlay file system into this
merged view okay
so first let's do
LS of merged
so inside merged we have Foo so
maybe I should do three on this
so
in this case
this file Foo
is
in the image layer in lower directory
right
and everything inside lower directory
appears in this merged View
so here this is in the most View and I
can I should be able to see the content
of
nourished Foo and it says this is in
lower
and this is the
you know content we
did in the First Command right
and
so the next thing we can do is we can
create a file
um inside
um this merged folder so let's say hello
emerged and we are going to make a file
inside merged
um bar okay
so I created a file inside merged
and so I now have food and Power
and so the real question is so this
merge is overlay file system it's kind
of a virtual file system where does this
file really go
because lower directory is a read-only
directory we cannot write to this
directory so what's going to happen is
every change you make on this merged
view goes into this upper so if I do
three and here
see so this merged View
has everything inside lower and upper
and
the file I created bar inside merged is
saved inside this apple directory okay
so if I do view of merge sorry up bar
bar
you see Hello merged message here okay
and finally
so this full is now created so so this
Foo is an image of this lower food right
what happens if I
um make change
to this file so open them
and edit that in merged
oh
so if I do this and I save this
so because lower is read only this
change is not going to go to lower
and what happens is
it's basically created a new file inside
this upper writable layer and I have I
now have three foods
and
if I see upper full
it has a change right
but
low or flu
remains
unchanged
so this is how you can
um basically reuse image over containers
and this is part of the assignment
okay
when does this class end 45
minutes okay so I'm just gonna quickly
go over what do you have to do
um
in process five okay so
container.c is the only file you have to
edit it implements a small container
runtime it creates a new PID and mounts
namespace set up the overlay fs and run
the program
okay so in this project
container image is a directory that
contains the root file system of the
container
and so Docker image the real Docker
image is too complicated to deal with so
we'll use
um you'll just use a directory and we
use these commands to create an image
so let me actually
um open it
Okay so
so first
you execute this command
to start the container in Dockers okay
so we'll be using Docker to create a
image that we'll use for our container
runtime
and you're going to do Docker PS
to um
either identify the ID
of
um
this container
and you'll do Docker export container ID
alpine.tar to export
this container as a turbo
like this
so now I have alpine.tar in the
directory
and what you're going to do is you're
going to create a directory
using this command and I'll do this to
basically
expand whatever is inside this
alpine.talk
so now I have a image
that
can be run with our container runtime
so if I do LS images
okay so LS images Alpine is in image and
if I do CD
let me just Alpine
so you get this so you have been
directly
Etc home so this is the sort of
all the files needed to run the
container and that's there
and
yeah
so the command line interface of
container is look is like this
so you have ID image and command so ID
is the idea of the container and Docker
uses a random string but here we expect
the users to provide one image is the
name of the image directory so in this
case we have images outline so the name
of the image is outline if you have
something else maybe something else and
command is the command to run inside the
container
so um I don't know sh or Echo hello or
something like that
so I think I can do an example here so I
have a finished version of container I
think
so if I do sudo container C1 so C1 is
the ID I'm just I'm giving it an Alpine
Echo hello world if I did this
sorry wrong place
[Music]
hmm
it doesn't work I don't know why
I must have edited the source code so
I'm not going to bother fixing it but it
should say hello world and it should
work just like docker
okay
so
yeah you have to do a couple of steps
um
I think with me has the most detailed
explanation okay sorry yeah
the TA section slides online or universe
that for this
yeah so this is
on the website yeah
yeah so the reason there's no slides for
project four is that just it's just that
I didn't have time to make one on that
week I was busy sorry