the discussion so for example what do
what do I mean by reasonable questions
it's not okay to ask like okay or what
is the operating systems what is the two
rules of operating systems because
because what we can easily find out that
right we can easily find out in the
textbook or just Google it so you can
ask some questions for example
um
just an example okay like for many
systems like throughputs you can say
like throughput is
is our performance very important
performance by matrix
but I also think like the fair list is
also a very important performance
metrics for example World War one and so
my question is that
like is there any relationship between
the between the uh the trade-off between
the uh throughputs and fairies something
like that and also like scheduling
algorithms you can say like
um
we know that lru list recently used
algorithm for paging right pagans
Gathering paging replacement algorithms
right we were going to learn that like
if you can ask a question like that like
the lru algorithms like it seems like
these algorithms need has incurred some
actual memory overhead is there any way
to reduce this overhead I have found
some several papers mentioned about that
and any other Solutions something like
that you can raise questions you can
also answer questions
I'm going to have an actual grader to
grade that she's going or she what he is
going to
look at everyone's discussion so because
I didn't find too many students raise
questions in The Piazza let's use that
okay
so another way is that if you choose not
to if you choose not to
discuss discussions in The Piazza you
can also raise your hands and
participating in the classroom
discussion for example every class I'm
going to
um like ask you guys questions right so
you can raise your hands and answer this
question and uh yeah if I remember you
like normally I if if you raise too many
questions I'm going to remember remember
you I'm I was going to automatically add
your points into that okay
so either way it works
okay
uh
so we are going to have a quick review
about about what we have learned so far
in the process and stress okay uh
let me close that so
okay so first so what is process what is
process
so you're going to
Implement your data structure about
process
what you are going to put into that to
represent the process
we learned that in our last week
I think Tuesday is class
anyone heard of the forgetting curve
heard of that forgetting curve
one I think one research a very famous
researcher he's he's analyzing human
brains and he finds out the forgetting
curve so it's it's like that it's like
that
um
if if you uh not like this okay it's
it's something like
so this is the forgetting percentage for
getting percentage okay you do not need
to memorize that
because then let's say it's 100 100
means you totally forget you totally
forget and then at the beginning at the
beginning we remember everything
we remember everything but then
days after days
you kind of
you're kind of starting for forget these
things especially if you do not
understand that however there is a one
way there's one way to extend this
period to extend this period which means
that is you need to refreshing what you
have learned
let's say the second day
for example I I learned this Monday then
you'll refresh it on Tuesday then at
after three days you refresh it again
after one week you'll refresh again then
then if you continue doing that continue
doing that eventually you you're
forgetting Curve will be like 30
percentage so it means that you can
almost remember 70 percentage of the
knowledge
for very very long time that is a
forgetting curve
all right so um
yeah so this is just one thing yeah what
is the process let's refresh it yes
encounter like an input and output
yes very good very good very good
uh
say again
what is my graph have to do with what
oh okay that is um
that is the forgetting curve that is uh
I hope everyone I hope you guys can
because in this course we are going to
learn our
um 300 Concepts New Concepts forgetting
curve means that you need to after you
learn that you need to continually
refresh that like
like look at the slides look at the
textbooks that
So eventually you do not need to
um you can easily remember everything
okay
so a process of
variables right we have variables inputs
outputs right and address space so the
dress phase means like where exactly the
location of this process in the memory
when we load that and what is the
process process is a running a running
program right program is like your code
so a process is a running program
when we loaded that it is starting to
execute that okay and what is
multi-programming what is
multi-programming
yes yes very good very good what's your
name
thank you genre right
so multi-programming is is a first what
channel mentioned that is very good is a
time sharing approach right so time who
is doing the time sharing CPU is doing
the time sharing right so
multi-programming we
we run multiple programs at the same
time and CPU is
evenly distributes the time between them
and why we need to do multi-programming
because we want to improve the system's
throughput
because we do not want to just solve one
user one program we want to serve many
user many programs nowadays now we
learned uh some interesting
Concepts about programs process States
so there's three states
what are they
yeah what's your name
Angelia Andrew
or running ready on the Block okay very
good so running ready and block
so um Can anyone describe the
relationship between these three states
yes so running is when the program as
the name States is running and it's in
the CPU and it's running ready is when
it's ready to be run there's nothing
stopping it other than the fact that
like all the other there aren't any CPUs
available so it's in like a queue I
believe yeah there's a cue
yeah waiting for Iowa for something the
relationship between these three states
the relationship relationship
but a running program can go from ready
and a writing program can go go to run
but
I forgot whether yeah I believe a block
program can go to ready and yeah block
program can go to ready and running
programs go to block if I remember
correctly
yes very good very good so why why is
why okay uh question why why block why
block
process cannot go directly to the
running stage
very good very good
so this this is it needs to be loaded to
the memory to the queue to the
scheduling queue of the memory first
right and uh
while running State why ready States
cannot go to block state
again
the ready why the radius The Wider ready
process so the ready process is in the
cured CPU scheduling queue right it's in
the queue right so it's waiting to be
scheduled waiting to be scheduled
so why why the ready process cannot
be blocked
why they cannot be blocked
it's a tricky question yes
yes very close very close very good so
why why the ready process cannot be get
blocked
who can get blocked when you block a
process you need to send a single what
is a single interrupt single right you
can only send the interrupted single to
who is running
right the ready the ready the ready
process is it's not running he he is
staying staying in the queue in the
schedule queue so no one can stop it he
cannot receive the single interrupt
single so that is why he can we cannot
send a process from a registry to block
space okay okay let's quickly review
this okay
okay and then
um I'm asking you uh a formula okay so
if I have a process which is 30
percentage I always we know that this
process is P1 it has 30 percentage of i
o weights
I always means
means
he's doing the IO
okay he's doing the io
he has let's say this P1 right his pen
is 30 percentage of time to do the i o
to do the i o wage
still
then what is the CPU utilization
what is the CPU utilization or the OS of
this OS
yes
yeah what's the percentage of that
percentage
one just one
you're very good 70 percentage right 70
percentage so what if I have P1
I have P1 who doing 30 percentage of the
io weight
and another P2 so the multi-programming
degrees two right we have P1 P2 is doing
this 20 percentage of the i o weights
then what is a CPU utilization
yes okay
what will be that
yeah
if I have two process running
concurrently on top of the OS one
computer okay one
P1 have 30 percentage of IO weight
time and P2 or 20 percentage of ioa time
what is the average CPU utilization
of this system
yes
how much uh one minus 0.3 times 10.2 so
uh 94 percent
very good very good
okay
so there's a formula in our slide so you
feel free to look at that okay another
question is that what is the What is the
thread
we as process
the differences between thread and
process
yes
and if I understood
um and I've understood this morning's um
discussion section properly
um
a direction where the process applies to
the entire program
what's the difference is between these
two
they come they have they have the same
stays right but what's the difference is
that that is the they are common scenes
yeah yeah
very good so if if multiple threats they
are they are created by the same process
then they are going to share the same
address space however if different
threads are if there are two threads
they are created by different process
than they have independent independent
or just space so one one day if they are
created if I have three threads they are
created by the same process they share
the address space means they are going
to be loaded into the same memory and
then they are going to share many
registers if you register so when we do
context switch it's much easier
so that is why thread is more
lightweight
together
okay so what is a race condition
oh it's a race condition
before that what is IPC
IPC
in the process communication very good
then what is race condition
what is the race condition
in which scenario race condition will
happen
when two processes or threats look at a
share variable but
to be
because they read anything comes those
develop
ment they read they read
they read
not exactly
yes
they are all writing each other very
good they are overwriting each other
then why what is race condition what
scenarios race condition what happened
they are all writing each other and then
they are all writing a race condition
happens very rarely like if I for
example I ask several persons to share
one variable by share I means not just
read not just read you need to change
the value read and write read and write
right so each other they can they can
override with each one right and then
but the race condition may happen or may
not happen in which scenario it will
happen that is just one presumption
and then
so if we have several process
we're going to
read and write the same variable
together
concurrently
and
yes very good so when they are when they
are read and write the values the shared
values this read and write operations
are not Atomic operation if they are not
Atomic operation and the contact switch
happens
when they are doing these operations
then raise conditions will happen and
release conditions it's uh is why the
race condition happens because we we
have no assumption about how the CPU is
gathering between different processes in
the first class at how you CPU can only
run one core of the CPU can only run one
process at a time and the scheduling or
speed is very fast in Nano seconds so no
one can no one can expect estimates the
order of how when the contact switch
will happen so it's so that's if color
switch happens in the case one different
process are read and write the same
value the race condition will happen and
you got unexpected results okay that is
what we learned the definition of the
textbook
so what we are trying to go trying to do
to avoid the race condition what we what
we have tried to do to avoid the race
condition
how to fix that
how to fix the race condition we have
tried several approaches yes
yeah very good critical region so a
critical region is just a term it's just
a term so what technical we have do we
have to do to
enable critical region
well technical we proposed
semaphone mutex is very good okay
so what is someone what is mutex
some forms mutex
okay let me
excuse me some of us
would be
what's the difference between some
phones and mutex
yeah
no no no not really your slide okay
let's
look at me and answer that
is the word
figuring mechanism very good and
restricted number of the share
availables to access and
okay and uh
[Music]
the first differences of the mutex in
some form is that
yes
I remember the bathroom example where
you have where you have all the um where
you have all the bathrooms that are
locked and you have like the and you
have the um and you have the
which I which I assume is the view text
in this in the in this analogy would
basically just assign threats like
different CPUs in a way or like
different parts of the no different
parts of the memory I think
but but yeah basically different threads
get assigned in different places
other threats have to be queued up for
like going to those places I think
um
uh not exactly it seems it means some
for a little bit okay okay first first
they are both integers right
they're both integers right
right
non-lactive integers right learn active
they have to be
they have to be equal or larger than
zero right long lactive right and about
per mutex
is a lock
it only has two values right
zero or one true or false right either
you get it or you lose it
because also fixing of their balls to
integer mutex is just a special someone
with just a special Symphony
but some of them is
it can be a value of n right as long as
it is larger
is now negative value okay it can be
so why we use some form we use some
phone to represent the number of
resources that we can share between
different process right the mutex is log
so mutex has
ownership
remember that ownership
so you either get a key or you lose a
lose the key
that's a good question you do you
remember the producer customer problems
produce a customer program right you
remember that
producer customer for how we
what do we sell some form for
forward
for the number of
is
yes very good so in the producer
customer problems you remember we set
two samples
right
one is for the number of
number of
the buffer right the buffer the buffer
says the empty buffer size and the now
empty buffer size
let's see
so check this check this okay so so
check this let's refresh this okay
here mutex is only has two values one
was zero right
so when we when we use new text you see
this when you enter the critical region
when you enter there may be many
producers there are maybe many customers
right
there are many there there will be many
producers there will be many customers
okay it can be larger it can be larger
than n it can be larger than n
you see for any pro and what is the
critical region what is the critical
region the critical region is here
right
the critical region is here
the critical region is the buffer it's a
buffer when we when we change the buffer
when we when we insert the item we
remove the item out of the buffer that
means this process is entering into the
critical region so we need to protect
that to protect that you gave you gave a
lock
to the process who entered the critical
region so we only have one mutex you see
that we only have one mutex why we only
want new text because we only allow
this example remember we only allow
one process to change that
you you guys will remember the critical
region definition
Mutual exclusion right Mutual exclusion
no process outside clear region can
block other process low starvation so we
give this example one process a is in
the critical region process B cannot be
in that also process C cannot be into
that now in this example in in the
producer customer example
we look at that the buffer is the buffer
is the critical region right
only one process only one process can be
there can be many producer process or
customer process only one can enter the
critical region so that is why
they fetch we don't know this
notice
is there so only one
can get the lock
you see this is the down means you get a
log you get a lock and the apple means
you release the lock
right same thing happens here you down
the log you release the lock
right however however we are
manipulating a buffer producer customers
and they are working on the buffer the
buffer has
the buffer has earned number of
shared items right so we need to use the
here we use we use the
here the Mt and also this is the four
we use this to represent the
number of the variables that are shared
between between the uh between uh
multiple process
okay
okay so a barrier then as a
um our last class we learned about the
barrier so why we lead barrier why we
lead barrier
why read it barrier
yeah what's the name what's your name
Ariel
Aryan
before go to the next stage right so why
we need a barrier any student think of
that investors in what kind of scenario
we need a barrier
what kind of scenario we need a barrier
in real life in real life
uh yeah very good yeah so um so any
students know real life example real
life means it happens it happens every
day
uh tickets or that's a tricky question
tickets asked is um
any other sort any other sort of the
real life example why we need a barrier
yeah
very good very good that's very good
yeah if you play a game you need
everyone to be prepared right you need
everyone to be for help
so so everyone is ready everyone is
ready you remember that when you play
the games right the League of Legends is
see everyone is ready then we we go in
and then we still have a synchronization
process
remember that the loading page the
loading page sometimes it takes just
several seconds sometimes it takes one
minute what they are waiting for they
are waiting to they are waiting everyone
to reach the barrier to reach the
barrier so we can open a shared scenario
the game scenario is a shield scenario
yes
what chapter
oh okay that's a very good question
there's no chapter in the textbook but
this is one important
slides are from the textbook or um or
one thing I I think I mentioned that I
have the solution menu for the textbook
but I cannot share with you to just
publish it on the converse because I I
think I it's illegal I
um please understand that but if you
really want to gathers you can you can
ask my ga and uh so um
oh so he can share with you okay uh
so uh what else oh okay so this today we
are going to start learning the
scheduling algorithms this is very
interesting okay scheduling algorithms
um
why we need this Gathering algorithms
yes what's your name
okay
anyway sometimes you want threads to run
at the same time but you have a limited
number of CPUs so you need to know
whether or not you want the feet to use
to share to share time or have time
distributed among the threads like
they'll each run at different times or
if they're going to run in the same uh
or if they're going to share the space
but I've been running like different
places and yeah basically if you're
dealing with multiple threads you need
to know what each thread is doing it at
each moment or maybe yeah yeah like you
need to know what each thread is doing
and when they're
and that's where scheduling comes in yes
yes very good very good so um
so we have very limited resource uh
still this come to our first lecture we
talk about Osos is just oh any students
still remember the law of the Lua of the
OS
to rules right yes
a resource manager okay so obstruction
resource manager so what we have learned
so far process and stress we have
learned the abstraction of process and
stress now we are going to learn the
resource management mechanisms about the
process and threats so scheduling
algorithms
is one is part of their most important
part of that so Gathering algorithms
um there's many scheduling
thank you
so there's many scattering algorithms
while computerized multi-programmed it
frequently has multiple process and
threads Computing for the competing for
the CPU at the same time
so this situation occurs Whenever two or
more of them are simultaneously in the
already States they are all in the right
state so the queue the radical is larger
than two okay then larger than two if
only one CPU is available a choice has
to be made to decide who to run next who
to run next remember that we have a
radical right
suppose we have more than two processors
or as a rally then we need to decide who
go next
so the part of the operating system that
make the choice is called the scheduler
and the algorithms it used together use
is called scheduling algorithms
so who does not care about scheduling
algorithms so if there's all in one user
who only competes with himself for the
CPU so if there's only one process then
we do not care about scheduling Parts in
today's OS
they're almost more than two processors
okay so uh
where is it
so let's look at the US Gathering
process Behavior so these two these two
so this true process they are actually
on two process Behavior so we can see
that this is the
um
one is the CPU bounded process we call
it we also call it a data intensive
process data intensive process means
that it it
um
it used a lot of it use CPU most of the
time you CPU most of time okay so what
are the examples of the data intensive
data um sorry it's the computation is it
should be called computational intensive
process
a computational intensive process
um
in your in in the in the library in any
uh
so if you are designing a mathematical
process process it will be mostly
um CPU bounded process because it's
doing the computation most of time for
example The Matrix computation
or you if you if you like the doing the
machine learning workload AI work they
actually machine learning is all about
the computations like Matrix
computations right so it's random Matrix
right
so it's it's all CPU bounded process and
then another another kind of process is
i o bounded process
um
iob on it process means that these
process are if it's not it's not using
CPU most of times most of the times
it's just the way for the inputs like
transfer data receive the data copy the
data
so that is the i o bounded process okay
there are two process okay
a key issue related to Gathering is when
to make scattering decisions it turns
out that there are variable situations
in which the Gathering is needed there's
many situations for example when a new
process is created a decision needs to
make whether to run the parent process
and child process
since both process in the United States
is almost Gathering decision and can go
either way okay if a process creates a
child process they are both ready they
are both ready so
you can schedule a parent process or you
can schedule the child process
well when IO interrupts occurs as
Gathering decision may be made if the
interrupts come from IO device that has
now completed its work some process that
was blocked waiting for Io may be ready
to run so what what process
transfer the space from the Block stage
to ready stage then you need to design
whether to go for this first so we'll go
for the other process who is already in
the ready queue
so there's many situations like a
process exists process blocks IO
interrupts happens so there's one to
make this is the situation why we need
to make scheduling decisions
um
these are different category uh
different different kind of machines
okay the batch machines interactive
machines and real-time machines
so different system they usually have
different scheduling goals Gathering
goals so batch system batch systems um
any students know what are batch systems
so here batch interactive and real time
real time
they are
um
batch system interactive system realized
systems all these three different kind
of systems operating systems are widely
used today why did you use it today
so example of the batch system so you
can think of that is that uh what do we
have yeah yeah oh what's your name
I tried
definition of the batch system okay
batch is a batch or what is the batch
a lot of stuff okay uh yeah uh oh that's
interesting okay what is the batch okay
um I do stream processing system this is
my uh that's in my research Direction
okay uh what I do I actually I built uh
several stream processing systems why is
the batch stream processing systems when
it's events stream processing systems so
batch means that when you process
when you process this the units you
processing it batch of the batch of the
batch so batch means the input inputs of
the system inputs of the system think of
that think of that I have I have
a lot of data I have a lot of data
think of the data is just the document
documents I have a lot of documents I
can process 100 documents at one time
like I loaded them first I loaded 100 at
one time and then processed them
together this is batch then what is the
what is the what is another non-batch
like events we have the micro bashing
event what kind of that means that
whenever you have a new data like a new
document a new event a new text comes in
you immediately load it into the system
and process it that is non-batch so
batch
means the import size is large okay so
what are the example of the batch
systems Battery Systems are in use in
business in business in business
especially in the bank in the bank
because they need to do the payrolls
inventory accounts receivable accounts
payable interest calculation
for a large amount of accounts
um
like Chase Chase Chase Bank the Chase
Bank will not have just uh 100 accounts
it will have 100 million accounts right
they cannot process everyone's Accounts
at time for example you make a
transaction
the bank they were frankly immediately
refreshed to you but they are actually
not just the work for you it's actually
at one time one even one second a lot of
requests to come to the bank and bank
process them together that is a bench
system okay an interactive system what
are the example of interactive systems
yes
magician
yes very good I need anything with the
UI is interactive anything with the UI
is interactive okay it's a real-time
systems that
um whenever we we whenever we enter what
is the interactive if um
so in another OS session they focus on
the network or systems so they have
server and clients right this seems more
like an interactive whatever clients
send the request is expecting a response
that is the interactive okay the what is
the real time what is the real time
what is the real-time award or real time
to me it's the same thing to Earth is
like they are the same right interactive
and real time they are they are the same
right they're the same but they are
actually not
they're actually not so uh well here the
interactive means that
is needed a user to frequently
frequently
gather on interact with the system but
real time real time is only it's usually
associated with the debt deadline
that nine definition always we also call
it SLA server level agreement server
level agreement SLA
so there are many real-time systems
you are embedded systems are mostly
real-time systems embedded area of your
embedded systems and many systems are
both interactive and real-time
interactive and real yes
invent invented
I don't know if I'm I'm pronounce it
right in Bandit
invented
see some
I watch
for example your eye watch
your your uh
what your your GPS towards like a
Tracker
tracker the uh your activities your
activities right your running activities
these are all embedded system
abundance system
okay so let's go over to that
okay let's look at the scattering
algorithm score scattering almost all
systems today focus on the fairies
fairies give each process a fair share
of the CPU fail means that's not means
equally share
okay guys here Fair film that's normal
means equal
it's not equal okay it's not equal not
equal
Fair
means
for example if I have a login process
and I have an interactive process I may
give 10 so for fair share it means like
I have gave most of the time to the
interactive process but if like the
right the rest of time to the log
process that is a fair sharing what is
unfair sharing on Fair Share means that
I
I gave most of the time to a log logging
process and give much less time to a
integrative process so fair sharing does
not mean a equally sharing is that not
means five and five half and half no
okay fashion means it's original sharing
policy in first months seeing what state
policies carrying out and balance okay
load balance keep all parts of the
system busy keep all parts of the system
busy
uh
that's interesting about the load
balance okay you you do um you use
Amazon and anyone heard of Amazon ec2
Amazon ec2
no no one using it
you use that right what is Amazon ec2
yeah yeah I I you you guys you guys uh I
recommend you strongly recommend you to
try that because I remember
um several years ago they gave every
user a trial that you can test you can
use a tiny you can get a free tiny
virtual machines yeah
AWS yeah
AWS AWS Amazon ec2 iws AWS ec2
yeah it's it is so
so for the AWS easy tool is actually a
data center right they have a data
center they have the data center we have
not known virtual machines but we will
learn that in our later sections so what
is the virtual machine they have a data
center this data center have many
physical machines physical merchants and
inside the physical motions they create
many virtual machines so give the give
the use issues in illusion that they own
each of the physical machine but they're
actually not a physical machine can
create so as many as like 100 virtual
machines
for now like a very good server
and the you know the average CPU what is
that one one
I think this is interesting and you you
guys need to know that
Amazon hire a lot of software
engineering every year every year right
especially from our school I think uh
like you you need to know that it's
Amazon where how the Amazon are modeling
the aaws is they are one of their group
right Amazon AWS ec2 Amazon ec2 which is
actually
is is a data center right what they did
is that they they have a data center
thousands of machines into that the data
center
today doesn't have many zones
right
songs okay okay we might have not hover
up that like let's say this is someone
this is zone two but in each Zone in
each Zone there's
there's a data center let's say each
Zone has only one Data Center
in each data center it's you already
have
you can think of a data centers can be
as large as uh
the size of our classroom our classroom
and there are a lot of racks there
it's not like this it's not like this
they do not have monitor they only have
the server and the server is is not as
as store as we are using it's not a
stores we are using it's just a braid a
braid as like a size of this height of
this and they have a rack so each rack
each rack have will have like 20 to 40
servers
servers so this is Amazon
and in Amazon there's one importance
departments called Resource Management
Department I was I was I was entering at
another company vmware's company's DLS
group DRS is doing Dynamic resources
scheduling group
um so I kind of know that
um
what do we do what do we do or what
Amazon do is that in in their
departments they do it's all resource
scheduling is resource Gathering and our
goal is to do what our goal is here wise
power saving
and load balance
so why we do what is the power saving
power saving means that I have let's say
I have this data center I have one
thousand one thousand servers one
thousand servers like in this racks 1000
servers
and this data center is in the
California
so it's in the California right we know
that most of time work at daytime they
are not going to work hard night time
your users you run the virtual machines
you are run then what do what what the
Amazon or the VMware going to do at
night
when no one is using their servers just
a few users are using their servers
where they are going to do they're going
to turn off turn off these servers
right white one of it because
we need to do Green Computing
save the money right it's it's a huge
huge amount of money because the server
they are very uh
power uh
a lot of they they cause a lot of
energies because a lot of Energies
if you are building a game PC you you
need to pay a lot in the electricity
bill because game PC they already have
Watts in the in the uh um Power in the
power okay
so that is uh one goal is to do a power
power saving another goal is to the load
balancing so what is the load balancing
load balancing means that
we do not want to have a server have a
like 19 percentage of the utilization
another server have only 20 percent of
the utilization that is not good that is
not good why it is not good we think of
that you have you have to CPU it runs
over 70 or 80 percentage you your server
comes comes very slow and easy to to get
failures the same as these data centers
they do not want their any of the server
got overloaded and what we did is that
we migrate the virtual machines from the
high loaded ones to the light loaded
ones and we Implement many algorithms
about that like in VMware they
implements uh
a lot of algorithms because we need to
take the inputs of users priority users
inputs and we need to take the impulse
of about the capacity under the
available resource of each servers and
the their
and we also need to consider in the
user's budgets right users badges so um
there's a lot of
a lot of uh policies here so well here I
talk a lot okay here are the takeaways
like is that you need to and you need to
understand in real world in real world
every system they have their own goals
they
have their own goals in our in this text
with textbooks mentioned that several
goals almost every system every systems
they focus on the fair list they focus
on policy enforcement policy
enforcements means that
if we have a policy we want to make it
we we need to ensure that it it'll work
we want to ensure it can work and
balanced load balance means keep all
parts of the system busy we do not want
to overload anyone we do not want to
like load everyone
and for the batch systems remember the
batch system right the bank system yes
policy policy enforcements means that I
design a policy
like for example I design a load balance
policy I want to ensure everyone is
everyone has the same exactly same
CPU utilization
policy enforcement means that
here these algorithms need to work
I will tell you which kind of policy
will not work for example I want every I
want every if you are opposed if you are
the servers I want everyone have exactly
50.9
CPU utilization at any moment it will
not work no one can guarantee that but
policy enforcement means that you design
policy you need to ensure
you satisfy that
okay
um
batch systems
batch systems like a bank system they
focus on the throughputs right and they
focus on turn around time what is the
terminal runtime what is the terminal
wrong time the time between the inputs
and between the outputs
you send the inputs to the systems you
get the output the time between the
inputs and the outputs is a turn around
hand so it's the true or
minimize the time between submission and
the termination so small turnaround time
means High supposedly true
small turn around time means High
throughput
small turnaround time means High
no wrong right we we talk about that no
okay and the CPU utilization bash system
keeps the CCU busy all the time okay and
for the interactive system we want to
ensure the response time what is the
response time the time between
the time which we we recently submit a
paper that we um we're building our
service engine for the age Computing
platforms and we reduce the QA time the
deployment's time the scheduling time
there are different times okay I tell
you what is the response time response
time means
means for example I go to the Amazon I
go to Amazon I choose a I choose I click
item I put into in it into the chat I
want to charge immediately refresh my
changes that's really spawn time like
the time I send the request and the time
the server responds to me the server may
not satisfy my yes
latencies turn around is the same as
lenses many times it is
many times it is well let's go to the
response time the response time means
the time the time that I got a server to
response response to me is reply to me
it does not mean that the server has
already finished my request
what kind of system have good response
time but it will not have a good uh
like uh processing time many systems
have good response time but not
not every system has good response time
there's sorry process time they are
different okay interactive in the for
other interactive
interactive systems they focus on the
response time because if you ask a
think of that you you you you you you
um
Amazon did quite a way of reduce the
response time single that you call the
agents representative right you have
something required you will immediately
answer the phone it will immediately
answer the phone okay that is that is
the response time so what is the process
time process time means
how long did your your problem got
resolved how long did your inputs got
processed that is process time
so most interactive systems like the
e-commerce systems they are really good
at response time because they there
there was a paper about that if the
response time is longer than I think
it's a limit then the company will lose
like billions of money because of that
because users are very tired if if I you
think of that you call agent you never
get a response how how angry you are
right
okay real-time system real-time systems
you need to meeting the deadlines okay
real that's the difference between the
real time and the Integrity okay
real-time systems focus more on the
process time they actually wants to
get the response quickly also get the
process time quickly meeting some data
and this data is the server level
response agreements server level
agreements okay
scheduling goals well the takeaway here
is that you need to understand almost
all the systems they focus on the
fairies and the low balance
focus on the fairness and the lower
balance and uh then different systems
they have different different priorities
for example system they focus on this
drupal's turnaround time interactive
system they focus on response and
real-time system they focus on meeting
the deadlines meeting the deadlines
now we are talking about just Gathering
uh in uh in these systems okay
scheduling these systems the OS
especially the OS is in a
uh give me one second
okay uh so we are going to learn several
different algorithms
um
it's not that difficult to understand
okay difficult on soundstand so uh so
firstly is that I've
yes I hope you guys can remember the
aberration of that fcfs fcfs because
so firstly is fcfs first come first
serve first to come first serve so first
to come first serve so what is the first
come first serve
um
we have the CPU queue right cpuq
let's use this slide
if we have several processes who who
joins the queue first be ready the state
first then we got a processed yes
uh what do you mean not exactly what
sounds like
yes it is exactly what it sounds like
it's very easy to implement
it's very easy to influence okay it will
not you don't want let's first look at
what is this okay oh sorry oh no
I do not have an example of that
oh God I don't have that
so easy is easy to implement why is it
easy to implement
you do not need to track
anything about their states you do not
need to track
like how many times they left how many
times CPU they have used
you just need to you just need to track
their
their calm their common orders right you
need just a little truck they are coming
orders so you can Implement that using a
ring you can Implement that using a
you can use either you start you do not
need to maintain any other information
so it's easy to implement
so the
the bad thing about that is unfair it's
very unfair it's called the staff Asian
it's starvations that is a
star uh v a t i o n
starvation
why
yeah Charlotte
and so you're getting through the jobs
and then halfway through
another process comes
the
and you keep getting processes that are
that are shorter than
the wall so the long but important
yeah yeah very good very good that's
that's exactly it means so we we have uh
single over the case we have a very long
job it's in front of
all these small jobs the small jobs are
blocked by the long job because the loan
jobs comes first so the CPU needs to
process the loan job first
however the case is that what if the
short jobs are really important they
have high priority but still if this is
the f
first to come first to serve then you
need to weigh that you need to weigh
that is it's the same thing like you
know
in in Amazon right you remember in the
Amazon like what
um
there's you only have two items but in
front of you there's a person who's have
hundreds of items in the chat but since
you are late you are behind of him
then you have to wait wait until his his
finished then it's your turn that is the
first come first serve this is it to
some extensive it's fair
then you realize how how they fix that
if you think of that how they fix that
in Amazon
they have a policy to do that
you remember that in
oh in California there's no Walmart
right
there is
there is right there is Walmart in
Walmart we we have the long line right
you you have to you have no you see the
there's many agents right but there's
one agent who is specially handling the
item less than 20. remember that that is
the way how how we how we
partially ensure the F first come first
serve but also gives some priority to
the short jobs that is the real life
real life fix okay but in here you need
to take away here or the disadvantage of
the first circumference Reserve okay now
let's take a look at Short is the job
first so what is the shortest job first
yes
yeah so what exactly it sounds like
you get the shortest job in the radical
goes first okay the shortest job in the
radical goes first when you have
multiple process then you find out who
is the shortest one and then you let it
go and after this finish you you look at
the others let's say I have a full
process
I see who who is the shortest I let him
go first then I go for the second one
who is shortest and then let him go to
first so you need to know here for sure
is the job first goes first you need to
know the runtime in advance you need to
know the runtime in advance that is the
disadvantage because many times you do
not know you only have an estimation you
only have an estimation about their time
based on the historical data in the real
life you do not know how they are but
that is the shortest job you need to
know that you need even you have the
estimation
um
it's a long preemptive algorithms what
is preemptive algorithms
what is preemptive algorithms what is
long preemptive algorithms preemptive
any students want to guess preemptive
and online preemptive
yeah sure
okay
so
yeah yeah okay
um so so let's first first take a look
at the targets of the preemptive and
algorithm alarm empty algorithms
so yes
Jersey is the that is the detailed
concept but let's go from the beginning
preemptive means pre yes
what is algorithms start to work to work
answer process of once something
very good interrupts whether you can
interrupt and change the order that is
preemptive and long preemptive
preemptive means that preemptive means
that
I run something I designed you go first
you go second you go search now you you
start running then you go first then I
found out that okay you're not good
you're not good so I immediately
put you back and ask him to go first
that is preemptive preemptive means I
can interrupt the processing order I can
interrupt it I can use the CPU who can
interrupt that the CPU can interrupt
that that is preemptive so long
preemptive means that no one can
interrupt whenever you decide the water
you need to follow that you need to
follow that that is long preemptive okay
so this is very important because this
is something we are going to learn in
our next chapter
we are going to refresh this okay we're
going to learn this again so preemptive
in the long preemptive
so the shortage this is this is not F or
FCS so FCS is is a pre mt4 or
non-preemitive
it's a preemptive or non-preemptive
yeah
it it
yes
very good when you are shopping at the
Walmart you shopping at the Walmart you
see the the the for example a lady in
front of you carries hundreds of items
then you find out she's very slow can
you interrupt her you say like stop let
me go for first you can you do that
you cannot it's it's illegal there's
alarm preemptive okay that's
non-preemitive okay
the fcfs okay that's long preemptive
okay okay
short is the job first
draw first
it's also long preemptive long
preemptive you give you have an
estimation about the runtime each
process runtime in advance you have the
estimation of their time and then run it
run it okay
so
let's calculating that okay I'll give it
to you to calculating it let's say we
have four jobs we have four jobs we have
four jobs they have the runtime as a b c
d okay they have a runtime of the ABC
team
and the a is more than b smaller than C
smaller than D okay this is P1 P2 P3 P4
they have a b c d okay a is more than b
is more than C is more than D okay what
is the processing order
of the shortest job first if they are
they are all in the radical water
processing order
um
yeah yeah a b c d okay what is the
turnaround time of that turn around time
to turn around the turnaround time is
the
the turnaround time is the time
sorry it's what is the average
turnaround time of this the total
runtime means that the moments the job
arrived
the time gap between the the jobs
arrives and then the job finishes right
the time Gap that is the time Gap the
differences okay how much what is the
average turnaround time of this oh
a plus b a plus b plus C plus d divided
four okay any students have other sort
what's this average turn around time of
this turn around time what the average
turn run time is
a plus a plus b
plus a plus b plus c
right
a plus b plus C plus d
okay any students since a is Right any
students in B is right
who votes for a
can you say it now who votes for a
Andrew you vote for a
you owe it for a so this is the average
turnaround time anyone votes for B
well then how about the other ones
you have other sort
you have other source
what's the average average we are
calculating average turn around time
run time right average turn around time
average return wrong time
yes
they are in the ready queue they are in
the
they are all in the radical
now we need to process them in some
certain water is sure this job first
order now we need to calculate in their
average turnaround time
we need to calculating their average
turn run time
so for the first job what is the
turnaround time for the first job let's
look at that for the first job
because the a needs to let's first
confirm that let's think like this first
if for the Georgia short is the job
first we need to processing them as a
and a b and a c and a d right
because a is smaller than b smaller than
C smaller than d right
so a go first right and then we wait
until B and then on TLC and then after
ABC all finish that we we go for d right
so what is the turnaround time for a
is a right it's a what is the turnaround
time for B
b or B is the arriving at the same time
as a right they are both they're all
four processing the radical what is the
turnaround time for B
a plus b is a plus b right because you
need to wait a to finish first a plus b
what is the turnaround height for C
the a plus b plus C right
turn around times for D is a plus b plus
C plus d right right right are we clear
and so the average time is
with this and then divide four right
that is the turnaround time average turn
run time
we are going to test that in the example
in your midterm okay
I might write that okay memorize that
okay
yeah Andrew
this is the turnaround time average time
around time
yeah very good that is the average
execution time yeah
yeah I'm asking ask question time then
that is the average execution time okay
so let's go to the shortest remaining
time first okay short is the remaining
time first
time first first it is a
preemptive algorithms it is a preemptive
algorithms okay it is a preemptive
algorithms
okay
so uh in in the case in the case in in
this case if we have
uh
so we pick the job we pick the job with
the shortest remaining time to excuse
the next okay we execute sign next so
Compare running time of the new job to
remaining job of the existing jobs also
or what exactly of the shortest
remaining time okay so here's the thing
steer the uh steal the Walmart example
okay
um
look at this they're the Walmart
examples maybe not good okay but let's
do this okay
here there's a lady it's a front of you
and the
she has a shopping cart so Russia has a
shopping cart there's a lot of items
a lot of items 100 items goes in you
only have two items okay now what is the
shortest time remaining time next means
that
she's in front of you if you if she's in
front of you okay and then after the
time at the time you you arrive
we check we check the system are going
to check how many items in her card
if this if there's
around more than two items more than two
items that means
she's slower than you she has the longer
remaining time than you so you jump in
front of her
but if if she only have one item by the
time you arriving by the time you
arriving she only have one items left
then she's still ahead of you because
she has the shortest remaining time
Okay so
so the idea why we need the shortest
remaining time
any students know why we need that why
we need that why why we design these
algorithms
you remember the the disadvantage of the
shortest time first
the remaining time of every process
changes because sometimes like
so basically if the remain time the
then yeah you're going to want to call
the one with the shortest remaining time
because that way you can get through all
the processes
yeah yeah whatever good so so the reason
is that you remember the disadvantage of
the shortest time first so you remember
that the disadvantages that you need to
you need to get everyone's running time
in advance the estimation by the most as
I told you most of times you cannot
estimate how much time they are actually
using you do not know how much time they
actually using many process they claim
they're owning these five minutes to
finish but actually they cost like 100
minutes you never know you never know
because they are waiting they are
waiting they have a lot of interrupts
they are waiting for Io they are waiting
for like the inputs right you you'll
never know so the system design a
shortage remaining time next so whatever
a new jobs comes in or they can also set
in a Time periodically time like every
five seconds they check they check how
much remaining time of of the current
job like the current job if if any of
them is it's not good it's not good then
it immediately preemptive like means
immediately get it back and put the new
process in the radio goes in okay so we
combine the running time for new job to
the remaining time of the existing job
combine the running time of new job
whenever new job comes in we compile it
to the remaining time of the existing
jobs and if existing job any of the
ecosystem job takes longer than the new
jobs then we
throw it back okay we get it back and
the last new jobs
join the queue sorry join the uh goes to
the running stage
that is the shortest remaining time next
actually shortest remain time next
okay another algorithms let's look at we
have learned we have learned a
we have learned the algorithm first so
this these are a very famous algorithms
in the batch system okay first come
first serve should his job shortage the
remaining time next now what are the
jobs what are other what other
the Gathering algorithm in the
interactive systems we have the wrong
Robin wrong robbing approach so what is
the wrong robbing approach
ES
um do you have a rotation basis rotation
very good
how to rotate between all the drops
each job have different times how you
rotate between these jobs
just to see from picture maker gas
some jobs are long some jobs are short
right how you going to rotate
I'm going to rotate
some jobs have three some jobs four
times four units some jobs need five
units some jobs need six units so how
are you going to rotate
Irene right Arie
you execute like B for a set amount of
time
a second then you yeah very good one
second so like one unit we settle units
we settle units and we we give the first
it's like a lock clock right a clock one
minute at one minute so we change your
job by minutes we change your job at 11
minutes we change your job this is a
wrong Robin we have a we have a slot we
have a um
we have a we call it the quantum we
thought this these words we call the
Cottons and so you need to set a good
Quantum if quantum is too short if two
column is too short we have a lot of uh
contact switches so we need to switch
between the process right if it is too
short we need a lot of contact switches
if it is too long if it's too long why
is it saying waste the CPU time why
if the quarter is too long why we say
it's called waste yes
yes yes
let's say I approach the quantum to be
one hour one hour and then the process
is just ah one of the processes just
needs six minutes to finish like it's a
60 and a six sixty and the six
minutes okay then I gave it a one hour
then it's the next quarter is only used
six minutes the other 54 units it's just
waiting okay
okay so um
now priority scheduling priority what is
priority scheduling so priority
scheduling is that we run the jobs
according to their priorities
um
it can be static and can do it
dynamically okay
um
so it can also combine with the wrong
Robin with priority let's look at this
we combined a priority with the round
robin so first we give the um high
priority ones as four and three and two
and one so what is the processing order
of this
we first we
any student know that what is priority
water
so we are going to give we're going to
process the high priority ones first but
when we providing high priority ones we
gave the
the same slot to this to this process
three process so we are going to switch
from this to this to this and then to
this to this to this until we finish all
these three then we go to the priorities
three and then we go straight that is a
combination okay so this is today's
class uh
uh yeah thank you so remember your
homework is due today