hierarchical structure so in in the
introduction section we mentioned that
because we do not have we have we do not
have in love
to support everything in cash or in
memory so we need the hierarchical
structure then we put the most important
things in the register and then the
cache and then the memory and so on and
so forth so that is why we needed a
memory hierarchical structure then
we're talking about the address space
the address space when we are talking
about address space we specially
mentioned that each process has their
own address page so what is exactly the
address space
so what is exactly the address space
or does it means
the addresses in memory that belongs to
a process right so the memory can be
very large it can be very large has like
16 gigabytes 64 gigabytes and 128
gigabytes so it can be very large
continually addressed
space right and we allocate some part of
it to a process and then this is called
this process address space so then we're
talking about so to
how to how to identify the location of
that process in the memory
so we use two parameters to identify the
location of that process in the memory
so any student remember what these two
parameters are
yeah Aaron
the base
the base right the base we call it the
um
we put that in the is the base we put
that in a bit yeah
yeah the limits it's also called the
size the size of that process right
and we put them in the base register and
the limits register
so
so basically what it does is that we
have a
so this is the physical memory right
physical memory
so it
so if we have a process called P1
then we we can allocate allocate this
part of the memory to this process this
process and we call it this part of the
space is the p1's address space memory
address space
and then so this this place is belonging
it's belonging to P1
and the P2
may also have
her own
address memory address space
they also have P2 also have its base and
limits right base and limits
in the
um
and we're talking about a disadvantage
of for of doing that a disadvantage of
doing that
the disadvantage of doing that and any
student remember or is a disadvantage of
using this kind of swapping technology
what we call it swapping because like
whenever new process comes in we find
the empty space for it and the update is
based and limits then puts the process
in and after you finish it we swap it
out and let the new process comes in so
that is the swap technology right swap
technology
and we use the limits parameters based
from based on limits parameters
represents the address space of that
process in the memory so a disadvantage
of this approach is that there's a
disadvantage of this approach
foreign
space but the but the chunks of empty
space if that makes sense are to
um are to
are too small to into the to throw the
whole process in
yeah sure
uh it's not
it's not oh yeah yeah okay so uh let's
talking about the swapping the
disadvantage of the swapping technology
so
um
so the the disadvantage of the swiping
technologies that when it runs for a
long time a new process comes in all the
processes swapped out we were we were
this approach will generates a lot of
memory fragmentations we
we call it holes but we most certain
times we call it a fragmentation
it'll cause a lot of fragmentations so
it's very little holes
and it's very inefficient very
inefficient
um diffractive fragmentation is for the
uh for the storage system it's not for
memory okay
so let's continue so when we are talking
about the um after we're talking about
fragmentation then
we're still continuing the design of
memory management system based on the
swapping technology we're talking about
the
most important issue is that how can you
keep track of the free memory
slots right the free memory address so
we talk about two technologies it's the
using the bitmap and also using the
linked list
so big bitmap bitmap when we are talking
about bitmap the
um
the key idea what is the key idea of the
bin map
yeah Magic
it's lightweight and uh yeah it's
lightweight and it can the key idea
first
so it's using our
bitmap data structure right one bit to
represent whether this memory
this memory units is taken or not I use
what one bit okay if it's one that means
it's taken if zero means it's not taken
it's free so it can use a bitmap data
structure to track keep track of the
free available memory
address so the advantage of the bitmap
is that once the advantage of the beam
map approach
yeah
it is very compact yes Compact and uh so
the in the slides we call the compact
way to keep track of the memory but the
award means by compact
why do you think it's compact means
yeah yeah lady
you're very simple to implement it's
very it's very lightweight right this
data structure is very lightweight it's
very it costs
little memory over hard
to support this data structure because
it's just you think of that you can use
a long integer to represent the bitmap
okay and then what is a disadvantage of
the Adobe map the key disadvantage of
that
yes
yeah whatever you want to find the K
let's say
consequencive empty slots whatever
because you do not know it has no way to
tell you where exactly the k k
consequence consequence if memory
slotted it so you every time you have to
search from beginning and find out it so
that is a um
that is the very best thing then we talk
about linked list so what is the key
idea of the linked list
yes
please list
portions of the memory or the program
that are being used and then
the different nodes that show you
show you how much of the memory is being
used
yeah so it's it's a linked list to
represents either a process or a hole in
a memory right so
it can be used as like one linked list
or double link crease okay so in the
when we talk about linked list there are
several algorithms to
to help you
like what what we use the link list to
track the available resources in memory
right and then what a new process is
joined in the memory you need to find a
way to put that new process so we have
several algorithms to find out the empty
space
for that process by using the linked
lists data structure so the algorithms
we have the first feeds pass the feeds
worse the feet next feeds
quick fits right so
what is that
the characteristics of each approach
let's say the first of it
what advantage of the first repeat
is very fast okay then how about the
best defeat what is the advantage of the
best fit
the best surface is always find out
stuff
small is the hole that fits the process
first of fate
okay
there's the feet
where's the feet
so first of the feet is very fast right
the best stuff is you always find out
the smallest holes the smallest holes
that
feeds the process so it's slow
right however it can minimize the I
think they also typo in my slides I will
fix that later this will minimize the me
minimize
the fragmentation
because it's always fine trying to find
out the optimal size of holes that fits
the process so every time it was
searched from the beginning to the end
so to find out the exactly sides that
can fit the process and we have the
worst fees what we the worst physics is
that every time you find out the largest
hole that fits the process okay you
always find out the largest
right so the it is not good as the name
is called the words but why we need that
because we need to know when we design
algorithms we need to know our upper
bounds and lower bounds so this is like
all our lower your balance the best of
it made like our optimal feeds right we
have our
upper bounds then to do the so we use
the word surface mostly for the
experiments to evaluate whether our the
performance algorithm isn't good or not
and then what is the key idea of the
quick fix
quick fit
so the idea of the Quick Fix is that
it's
what is the key idea of the quick fit
yes Magic
show what quick fix this is that it's it
it can
you can use the table or you can use um
several pointers if you are going to
keep track of some common sizes like the
for example the size of 2 4 is the 16th
13 264 like this okay
these are going to keep track of any
sizes fitting this category
the idea structure is very similar to
what we have learned like the the
priority queue right priority queue so
it has different sizes and each then we
can track
the location of each empty spaces we
just keep track of them keep track of
them then whatever you think of that
whatever new process comes in right it
can always fits in any
of these common sizes
right if let's say a new process comes
in it has the size of 30 then we can
push it in the 32 to 30 the
the empty holes that fit in the 32
category so that is a quick fix
okay so that is what we have learned in
our our
last class so today we are going to talk
about the virtual memory so what exactly
virtual memory is what exactly virtual
memory is
sure
[Music]
um
no what is exactly version memory it so
you do not need to remember the exactly
keywords so talk about the key idea of
the virtual memory really
if you ever go to up
starting
the technical in the virtual memory how
is how they did
so we have yeah magician
different like empty slot but you can
keep track of all of them with the with
the page table or with some sort of
pager or something like
that okay so I I would just say we're
using a very simple example to
to this
describe the key idea of the virtual
memory okay the key are you don't need
to remember the key idea so the key idea
of the virtual memory is that so I have
a process right
this is my process
I gave it some virtual memory address
space it's not real it's not real it's
fake okay I gave it a little virtual
memory
address virtual memory address space
okay
so let's say this process it's a frog
4GB okay 4GB so I'm going to give it a
virtual memory address space from
zero
to 4GB
so this is the process one process one
for GP
one when I loaded that into the memory
when I compile this this process before
the before it's running it is still a
program right a code we call it program
then we combine it
then
they also components called mmu memory
management units we are talking about
that later okay it's going to transfer
this
to a process and gave it a virtual
memory address space is fake and it's
not loaded in the memory or it has not
yet loaded into the memory okay 0 to 4
gigabytes then then
the idea of the virtual memory is
virtual memory is now I gave it the
this is the fake right this is fake but
here I have the rear right the rear
memory is a physical memory right
physical
physical memory
so in the physical memory there is a
real memory
real address space right the real
address phase so what next next CPU data
is that it's going to it's going to
divide
divide this process the virtual memory
address space into many small parts
small parts and we call each part each
fragments we call it a page page and
each page is 4 KB each page is 4 KB so I
divide this process right this process
you loaded that you you just first you
gave it a virtual address space no
matter how large they need no matter how
large they need if they want 4GB 4GB
then OS gave it 4GB if you want 8GB I
gave you the OS gave you AGB so no
matter how large you want OS can always
give it to you that is the virtual
memory address space then it's going to
the OS the CPU are going to divided that
into many many parts small parts each
part is 4 KB 4kb
then what is the next step the next step
is that the physical memory is already
divided into many small
frames we call it a page frame page
frame
page frame so it's the the physical
memory so far has no process it has no
processes you understand the differences
between a photo and a photo frame right
a photo and a photo frame you understand
that right
a photo you insert a photo into a photo
frame right the same idea comes to here
the physical memory is like a
lot of photo frames a lot of Amity photo
frames now here the virtual memory the
virtual memory address space for this
process for the P1
it's like I divided that process into
many
Pages many pages that is Pages like many
photos like this processes single
varieties process
so like Hue has a lot of photos personal
photos
and then the physical memories like the
photo frames has are limited size of
photo frames now here's the thing if I
have if this program this process has
let's say
800 Pages 800 like your 800 photos but
the page frames The Limited the physical
memory page frames can have only 100
page frames so what we need to do we
need to pick the pages what pick the
pages that
that currently is mostly importance into
the physical memory right we need to
pick the pages put it into the memory
and then CPU can process it remember we
call we learned that in our first
chapter owning CPU can
load the data from the memory right CPU
cannot load data from the disk whatever
you have you have the
code or programs you need to load it to
the memory and the CPU can load to it
and this process we call it mapping we
call the page mapping okay page mapping
and so who is doing the page mapping
the page table the page table so page
table are going to decide right decide
it's going to decide which Pages let's
say this page is mapping to display then
on this page this page is Peak to this
physical memory okay then this one is
also mapped to this we put this Pages
pick that to the page frames okay and
then who decided the mapping there's a
page table
inside the mapping so that is the
what you do to learn about virtual
memory virtual memory
so in the textbook there are maybe a lot
of
a lot of contents about this but
think of the key concept think of the
key concept
I will repeat again okay I will repeat
again
you have a program right a program you
write some code it's very large very
large it's a program you have not loaded
that in your memory yet then we combine
it we combine the code it's
code binary code right and then we load
it out in this view can loaded that
Things become a process the first thing
people are going to do is that
provides the virtual address space to
that process
so if that process is as large as four
four GB it will going to give the
virtual address space of 4GB if it is
8GB then you are going to give the you
know it is going to give the virtual
address space as 8 GB why because it's
fake so you basically you how much you
ask I give to you okay no matter how
much you'll ask I give it to you that is
a virtual that is why it is virtual
ok so these parts are let's say this
process is 4kb so it then I gave the
virtual address space from 0 to 4 GB I
will it always starts from zero the
virtual address for every process is
always start from zero so if it is AGB
then it will become 0 to 8 GB from 0 to
8GB right but the the thing is that the
difficulty is that the challenge that we
have only limited size of the memory
right we have the limited size of memory
we cannot hold everything over process
into the memory because we have limited
size of memory our memory needs to share
the
by difference process
not we cannot just support one process
we have many processes that waiting this
has process P2 P3
they are waiting to map to the to to be
allocated by the
memory the our physical memory then what
we can do what we can do we need to pick
Peak from the virtual address space
where you can only pick parts of the
virtual address space the p1's virtual
address space picked some important
contents and put start in the physical
memory to run it
most of times we call it is the active
Pages active pages
but the problem is that we there we need
to define a unit we need to Define units
so we can better manage them manage them
we can not we cannot
like
independently decide how much protein do
that because
it's not easy to to manage it what we
did is that for the physical memory
think of that is similar to your photo
frames we have many photo frames that's
the same size they are both empty photo
frames we have 100 Floor frames like
this he's called page frames page frame
so page frame has the same size of page
it's also 4kb it's also 4kb so one page
frames can hold one page one page then
this empty page frames
are there they are there they need they
are waiting for the CPU to design which
page which page of which process to map
to this to Maple to this okay then this
mapping
we call it the
um
page mapping okay and the mm you use a
page table to design the page mapping so
after we after we select the important
pages of the P1 to map it to the memory
this is then we can select what we think
is important for P2
P2 and also P3 to map to the map to map
the into memory so you see P1 we're
already mapping these three pages into
this physical page frames right so we
have still
several left okay so P2 we can map in
the 2B here that to be here
like here
right
then P3 we can map it to here
to here
then by doing that we can by doing that
we can implement the abstraction for
space sharing of the memory right then
these
this memory memory here the memory can
is able to
concurrently supporting many process P1
P2 and P3
right so what we need to do that because
we have limited size of the memory and
for every process when we run it we do
not run them
as a whole we only run part of them
almost of every process like your office
your office office has many
products rights most alarms we only use
the word right we do not use the PDF or
we do not use the
[Music]
um
like the the other products the the
Powerpoints most of time we just use one
product then we'll use one product you
only pick the
process the process the pages that
relates to that process loaded in memory
and then the thing is that when
there's a lot of issues a lot of issues
after this mapping technology yes
what do you mean locality this is a very
fancy word
or at the locality first let's define
what exactly locality is locality
you think of that because locality
locally can
can have different meanings in different
situations right in your situation what
do you mean by locality
very good very good that is what we are
going to learn in the so where you are
what are you well I think why do you
mentioned that correct me if I'm wrong
when you mentioned there's like for
example if I have a mind if I have a
process right this process has some data
a large amount of input data so you you
may want to that inputs data to be put
in the continuous phases of memory
spaces so when when we access it they
can be concurrently accesses instead of
jumping to different places to access
them so in that case we we discuss that
in our later chapter about the
fragmentation fragment that is after the
paging that after paging okay so there's
many issues that you we may consider
about this or any student can guess make
a guess what are the issues
so I already tell you this is the
virtual memory yeah
yeah if it's full
it is four if the physical memory is a
four it's four we need to kick out some
kick outs the pages right kick out the
pages then that is the page replacement
algorithms right there are many page
replacement algorithms we are going to
learn what are the issues what are the
issues
think of the artist says there's another
storage this is called a disk
other issues are what are other issues
so let's say when when my system got
started I only have P1 P2 P3 process
right and I have an initial page table
that can tells me the mapping of this
page to this this page we select these
three of these seven pages to map into
the physical memory
then also time goes by right we
the physical memory may become full so
the first issue is that if it becomes
four
then you need to design who whose
kickoffs and whose goes in right that is
a page replacement algorithm so what
else
what else yeah Andrew
if you want to access the memory you
want to but what is the problem
performers
I'm not quite good at
any other
gas
so what do you what if what if the page
that I want let's rephrase what you what
you mentioned a little bit right what if
the page that I want
is not in the physical memory it's not
in in the physical memory
what if the page that I want is not in
the physical memory if it is not in the
physical map means like for example I
need this page I need this page but
there's no mapping from this page to the
physical memory right the physical
memory still has spaces but there's no
space for this
for this page
this
well right now the remember what I teach
you last in our last section right and
virtual memory is just so we put some in
the physical memory the rest of them is
in the disk right the rest of them is in
disk so this page May in the disk really
you have a go to the wrong way you need
to go to the disk right go to the disk
and find out the pages then updates the
map the page table
because there's no mapping of this right
you need to maybe add one mapping of
that because you you need to find out
the page the page is not in the memory
you need to mapping that into the memory
so you need to update the page table
about the mapping so that is the core
page for the handling page fault
page fault handling
okay page Force handling and then page
replacement algorithms
the reason why we are going to learn
in today's class okay but let's have a
brief idea first
page for handling page replacement
algorithms what else
or else
what else
well if I make changes to the pages to
the contents what if I make changes to
the pages
in the memory
and you still don't want to make a guess
what if I make changes to the physical
the pages this page in the memory
and then power off okay yeah Irene
you have to updated in the disk right
you have to updated in the Disco If I
make make changes on the physical memory
the physical memory is the IEM right
random access memory is
if I make changes to the memory make
changes to this to this page
I need to synchronize large to the disk
otherwise otherwise
it are going to wind power of my changes
will be gone right there will be no way
to remember my changes
you heard that was
frequently is called 30 pages 30.
so we are going to learn what is exactly
30 pages means that is the concept of 30
pages you make changes to the page read
you write the page but you have not yet
synchronized the writing in the disk
then that make the page to be 30. that
is why we call it 30 pages the 30 does
not mean the page is 30 okay the 30
means that there's inconsistency between
the you see in the face called Magic
then
how does it work
better the physical memory have let's
say they have unsolutely let's say 100
slots and equals to 100 right so what
are your question this one these have
101 yeah
one or one that you need to decide which
how many of these 101 to be mapped to
the physical memory right
you need to decide that that is why pay
we need a page table if we can put
everything in the physical memory
physical memory is inference
yeah yeah that is the page replacement
algorithms works yes what's your name
easy
okay that's a nice name easy yeah
it's it's it's that's normal matter how
free how how the higher the priority of
them we only have this amount of
physical memory
yes
how can you pour memory what do you mean
by poor memory we cannot extend it that
it's it's just you you only buy 16
gigabytes of memory right you cannot you
can not using the disc as a fake memory
memory is memory right so you need to in
kick them out right then that is the
page replacement the algorithms worked
okay so
let's let's learn these Concepts these
are all the important Concepts we are
going to learn in today's class
okay so the first thing we need to learn
okay the virtual memory okay
virtual memory so the program's address
space is broken up into fixed size of
pages and we call it a page
page right we call it a page fixed size
what is the default size what is the
default size
the foresight
I mentioned it five minutes ago
Andrew
four kilobytes 4 KV right 4kv that is
the fixed that it means the fixed size
Pages means and then pages are mapped to
the physical memory right pages are
mapped to the physical memory
so this is the uh we are going to learn
that later about how to handle the page
Force okay so you need to hear the
takeaway the pages and mapped to the
physical memory okay and then who is
doing the mapping who is managing the
mapping there's in the CPU there's a
units called mmu it's called memory
management units you need to remember
that memory management units memory
management units are going to generate
the physical address from virtual
address provided by the program
so
um here's the thing okay the memory
management units we have the CPU right
okay the CPU the memory management units
is there
the memory
the memory management units is there
it's there okay the CPU sends the
virtual address to the memory management
units we have the program right we have
a program and then we combined it then
we loaded that into memory then it
becomes a process the first thing before
it loaded into the memory
CPU needs to generate a virtual
address to that process we call it a
virtual address we call the virtual
address
and it's always done from zero to a to
uh maybe very very large number of that
process then
then the mmu
mapped virtual address to physical
address physical address and puts them
on the memory bus put them on the memory
bus and then another concept that we
just discussed pages and Page frames
okay the virtual memory divided into the
virtual address divided into the pages
right divided into the pages
so the pages can be a small page to a
very large page okay
so here is the example of mapping the
virtual pages to the page frame to
physical page frames
this is the physical memory address this
is the virtual address space each
process each process okay this is a
signal it's easy to get confused each
process has this virtual address space
okay each process not just the whole
memory it's a virtual address space no
no each process has a this each process
has this but memory this physical memory
address is shared by multiple process
but each process has a virtual address
space each process has a virtual address
space
then then we owning we only when the CPU
is is running is only loaded the
important Pages because active pages
into the memory into the memory
who decided who decided which page I
should put in the memory is actually you
decide that because you you are the
programmer right you write a program
then the CPU has to register the
instructions like the instruction
pointer it points to the program so it
will find out okay this line for the
code is in the memory if not so it's
going to load that into the memory
updates the page table so mmu are going
to decide the mapping the mapping
so this is the mapping okay
so the virtual address virtual advances
and it's sent to the memory management
units the memory management units sees
that the virtual address
it's going to see you
this put stop put stiff puts the
different part of the code into
difference
page different pages okay
and then we have a page map sometimes we
call it page table a page no matter what
is Page map or page table they designed
a mapping from a process virtual one
processes virtual address to the
physical address physical memory address
it's going to design
which
for each process which part of the page
is puts in which part of the physical
memory and any students know what the
1100 means here
my first
photos are where
the bureau isn't so one so one basically
says okay we there is this is being used
in physical memory zero means this is
not being used
yeah yeah okay and the
yeah Andrew
yeah the dirty bits okay the 30 bits
okay so there's many there's many
there's many terms but it's here okay we
are going to learn that
now we talk about
after we after we learned the mapping
with the first thing we talked about the
page force all right what if the page
that I want it's not in them is have not
mapped to the physical memory it's not
in the physical memory
then
we have the present absence B tells
where the page is in the memory cities
if it is it's one if it's not it's zero
right so it's had this so what happens
the pages that I want is a lot in the
memory then
and then
it will trigger a page Force so page
force is our interrupt single
it's going to Sender interrupt single to
the CPU then CPU going to handle in the
page Force handling the page Force so
how to handle the page first we are
going to learn that later
now we talk about the page table the
page table so page table
here is how to do the page table page
table
so when we're talking about the page
table we need to learn about the page
table mapping so how to translate from
the virtual address to the physical
address how to trans transl
Verge from the
virtual address to the physical address
okay
so the virtual for any lines of the code
for any lines of code you have the
virtual page table virtual page table so
each page is 4kb right for KB but your
instruction is not as large as 4 KB
right so your instruction is on offset
I need lines of your code it's just
offset into the
into the page it's like I have a book I
have a book
this is a process process one process
one the whole the whole book is my
process process one I it is all right on
book okay I I first divided it into the
many pages right so the pages they have
the same size right page line same size
then
I select the
the CPU has um mmu memory management
units these are going to this it is
going to help me
putting put helped me to put the
important Pages the active pages
grab that mapping that into the physical
memory so for example this page this
page
this page needs to need to loaded into
the memory so I'm going to be there
going to map here from the physical
memory physical memory so CPU can access
to it but CPU access to it CPU has the
largest to registered in the program is
called the program program counter right
program counter and instruction
instruction
register so it points to the array
instruction is just a life of the code
in this
it has many lines so it has an offset
see
if I need to read this line of the code
then this is the
offset okay officers if I need to run
the CPU pointer is point to this line of
the code then this is the offset offset
that is why it needs first to have a
page page number so page number is 55
this is my process right the virtual
this is the hold that is my virtual
address space it has different pages
like from 1 to 55 so so first I selected
55 and let's select the lines of code is
in the offset of this so is one of
virtual memory has a virtual page number
and offset so are we clear about that
are we on the same page okay this
concept is very important now you need
to you need to
translate this virtual address
into the physical address because this
page this page are going to be loaded
into the physical memory plot physical
memory frames so it would not be
page 55 right in the virtual in mind
virtual memory is page 55 but who knows
what the pages will be in the physical
memory you need to change the physical
memory page number right so that is the
key idea of we do this mmu operation of
translates the virtual address into the
physical address so how we do that okay
how we do this
you say you see this
see this it has the
um this is the page table right page
table so we have the
so this this bits represents is one
means it's enough in the physical memory
zero means it's not in the physical
memory right so here let's see
this is the incoming virtual address in
common virtual address this we see this
is the page table this is the page this
is the virtual page table like let's say
let's say this is my virtual page table
55. it's a virtual page table now you
need to find out where exactly this page
is loaded into the memory in the
physical memory you need to find out the
real page table of this the real page
table so you you find out the zero zero
one zero right it's it's equal to two
Okay it's equal to two and you find out
okay what is the two maps to maps to the
physical page table physical page number
is one one zero one one zero one one
zero is how much
is one one zero so you you add in that
into the one one zero this is the
physical page remember the physical page
number and then adding the same offsets
right adding the same object the offsets
will not change this is the offset the
offsets will not change
okay are we are we in the same page
okay
so here's the thing here's the thing
okay this is my my virtual my process my
process I divide my process into many
pages it has 100 pages okay and the code
I need to read is in page 55 so page 55
is my virtual page number right my
virtual page number now the virtual page
number I look at this page number the 30
and sorry that with the absence present
piece if it's one that means that this
page is in the physical memory it's in
the physical memory so I need to find
out where exactly it is in the physical
memory because the physical frames then
maybe let's say this is my physical
memory physical memory is has only three
page three page frames so I need to find
out whether it is in the page one or
page two or page three the whole tell me
that the page table can tells me that
that is the
we have the
the page right this page you see that
this is a virtual page number is 2 is
mapping to the one one zero so one one
zero is my real physical page number so
I using the real physical page number
plus the offset after we do that then
that is the outgoing physical address
after I found out the outgoing physical
address
then CPU can put this address into the
program counter register and then doing
the pipeline operation right the decode
ask you um yeah
write a fetch decode and execute execute
the code
that is how the story goes okay
so let's look at the structure the more
detailed structure of the page table
entry
so we already know this is the presence
absence Beach right and then we have a
protection right production base means
that is if it's read only what read can
read Council written white or also white
only and the modified base means that if
it's 31 knots so what means is that
is already is have to zero means that it
does not have to write to desk what
means that it's already modified so if
it is modified then it needs to be
white to the disk if if you have not yet
right to this that means the page is 30.
the page is 30. so we use this to
represent the pages 31 nodes the
reference being so one means it was
either read
or right turn
is used to pick page to be mixed
so the reference base is what we have
what we are going to use in the page
replacement algorithm
the page replacement algorithm
okay so there's a technical to speed up
the address translation and we recorded
the translation local side buffer
translation local side buffer so what is
the translation Luca side buffer
um it's it's also registered it's also
registered so page table sometimes can
be very large and most of times we put
the page table in the memory and in
memory so and the tlb you can think of
tlb as a cache of the of the page table
it's going to save the most frequently
used page page mappings into the tlb the
page table saw the page mappings right
the tlb stores some important page
mappings
so it stores the frequently accessed
frame frequently accessed frames
so for example it's going to the
translation look outside buffer is going
to store the same thing as the page
table so the same thing as page table we
show the mappings of the virtual page to
the physical to the page frames okay
that is the virtual page right that is
the real physical
page frame number okay and the one means
that is multiplied or not if it modifies
means that it's 30 it needs to be right
to the disk the production means that
whether it's realized will read write
only
that's the tlb translation local side
buffer
so um
so before we look under the multi-level
page table let's look at a video okay
let me
cut a video for you good
and during a page fault so let's
understand exactly what happens during a
page fault service so when the thread is
executing on the CPU it generates a
virtual address
and the hardware takes that virtual page
number and looks up the tlb to see if it
can translate that virtual page to a
physical page frame that contains the
contents of that page now the tlb lookup
fails that's a Miss in the tlb and at
that point the hardware if the hardware
is doing the page table lookup it'll go
to the page table and look up the page
table to see if the mapping between the
virtual page and the physical page is in
the page table and this would have been
there if the operating system is already
put the contents of that page in
physical memory but if the operating
system has not brought in that page from
the disk into physical memory then when
the hardware goes and looks into the
page table it may not find the mapping
between the virtual page and the
physical frame and so that will result
in a pay stable Miss and that mess is
the point at which you have a page fault
so your page fault now that says that I
don't have the page in physical memory
and so what the operating system at that
point in the Handler what it has to do
is to locate where on the disk that
particular page virtual page is residing
on the disk and as part of the page
fault service the operating system has
to allocate a physical page frame
because it's now missing in physical
memory and do the i o to move the
virtual page from the disk into the page
frame that it has allocated and once it
is done the i o the i o is complete then
at that point the operating system can
update the page table to indicate now it
has a mapping between that virtual page
and the physical frame number which was
missing in the original scheme of things
and that's the reason that we had this
fault and we handled the Fault by
bringing in the missing page from the
disk into physical memory and we update
the page table to indicate that the
mapping is now established between the
virtual page and the physical frame
number and then you can update the tlb
to indicate that now we have the mapping
between VPN and pfn and once the tlb has
also been updated the page fault service
is complete and life is good so that
that's the whole workflow in taking a
virtual page and mapping it to a
physical frame when there is a mess now
let's analyze this picture and ask the
question where are potential points of
bottlenecks now what I'm showing you
here is
that
um
Okay so
any student can repeat how to handle in
the page fort
the steps the steps to handle the page
for it
the steps to handle the page Force
yes
but it also has to replace
graphical disk
to
where you have to update the table to
reflect your chain
and then once you've updated the table
so before we find out a page board
before before so let's say we have a
process right we have a process the CPU
going to generate the virtual address
for that process then then the CPU are
going to read the virtual address right
to find out the first instruction so to
find out the first instruction so it
needs to find out the page is in the
memory or not so the first thing is that
we check the
so take a look at this if I have a
program right combined to be a process
then I generate a virtual address for
that process then then the pointer the
instruction pointer points to the first
virtual address
according to the first virtual address
then I need to know whether it is in the
memory or not so the first thing I need
to check
yeah
first check the tlb very good first we
check the tlb I checked the tlb to find
out the mapping right the mapping from
the virtual address I need to find out
the link I need to find out link the tlb
has the link right then the second thing
yeah
you check the page table so if tlb is a
Miss if tlb is a miss
then I find out the page table so
there's a true first question the tlb
Miss means there is a page force is that
true or false
a tlb Miss means there's a page fault
fourth why it is a force
it could be in the page table Yeah the
pl tlb Miss means that only means that
the Tob does not contain the mapping
from this virtual address to the
physical address but we do not know yet
if it is apps
presence in the memory or not if it is
existing memory physical memory frame
frame or not so we need to check the
page table
so
a true first question if a page table is
a Miss there's if the page table shows
there's no mapping from that virtual
page that you want to the physical page
frames then there's a page Force true or
false
true or false
Aryan
I see yes it's true right the page if
the pair both the tlb and Page table do
not have does not have the have to have
the
have the mappings then there's there's a
page Force right so through another true
false questions
if there's a page mapping big if there's
if is there any page mapping that
existing in Tob but not existing in the
page table
so you see yes or no
the question is that okay question is
that
they are existing a mapping of the
physical frame the virtual virtual
address pay virtual pages to physical
frame there's a mapping that existing
only in tlb but not existing page table
true or false
false right Force white is a force
so because tlb is just a cached
frequently mappings in the page table so
tlb is just a cache is just pick the
frequently use the mappings in the page
table okay in the page table okay so the
first thing we look at the tlb if it's
Miss we look at the page table if it is
still miss what we are going to do is
still miss
if it still miss what we are going to do
how to handle the page Force if it is
still missed
what we are going to do
you go to the disk and we get the file
we go to the disk and get a file and
then
put it in the page frame you have a good
memory
for saying in a page frame and then
updates to watch
updates page paper first right
type of page table and then
update the tlb
and then life is good okay that's the
that's the how we handle the how we
handle the page Force how we handle the
page Force okay now let's look at
another video
contact switch contacts
fresh no contact switches contact switch
contact switch happens the CPU to
managing the
um scheduling order between different
process right
oh okay you mean why you you change from
one process to another process it will
Flash the tlb or not
the trb is a page table is shared by
many different process right
page table is shared by many different
person page table does not only hold the
mapping of one process page shape holds
the mapping of different process
mappings like memory right
so when we do contact switch some pages
some page tables entries may be
refreshed but some may not it's not
going to flash the whole page table no
okay the page table is like a memory
when you do the contact switch are you
going to flash the whole memory
no right no right yeah
the second process is that when you do
the contact switch the first thing you
are going to
remember is the status right and the
states of that process right so you also
remember the active pages mappings into
the register
foreign
Sims from Andrew Authority it seems to
date everything has the word virtual
stuck in front of it we have virtual
reality we have virtual currency we have
virtual machines well before any of
those existed we had virtual memory and
it's a technology that we use every day
you'll find it in Windows in OS 10 in
Linux in iOS and of course in Android so
what is virtual memory and how does it
work well let me explain
[Music]
any program that's running on a CPU has
access to the entire physical memory and
it basically assumes it's the only
program running on that CPU and so if it
writes to a particular address let's say
address
495 that address is actually somewhere
in physical RAM and it is addressed 495
and it writes something there that's
what goes if it writes to a different
address it goes there and you there's a
one-to-one relationship between the
addressing of the physical RAM and the
addresses that the computer program uses
now that's fine when you've only got one
program running but when you've got two
programs running things now become a bit
more complicated first of all you have
to decide where you're putting each
program in memory
secondly each program in memory has to
be careful not to overwrite the data and
the program used by the other task
that's running
and thirdly all addressing has to be
relative that means you can only ever
say do something 10 bytes forward from
here or 15 bytes back from here you
can't use an absolute address like
4095 because that could actually belong
to somebody else it might not be your
address
there's also the issue of memory
fragmentation if you're trying to run
two programs and you allocate one bit of
the memory for one program and another
bit of memory for another program and
then what happens is the first program
exits and then you try to write a second
one it might fit in that space of the
first app but maybe it's a bit smaller
so there's a gap left and then when you
run a third one it can't fit in that
gaps it goes somewhere else in memory
and then you actually get these little
gaps starting to appear until you get
this thing called memory fragmentation
so and that's a real problem eventually
you'll run out of memory just because of
fragmentation
to get around these problems we have
this technology called virtual memory
and in virtual memory each app that's
running on a mobile phone each program
is running on Windows or on OS 10 thinks
it's the only app running it thinks it's
the only program running and it has
access to all of the address space
in fact it doesn't even have to have uh
that amount of physical memory on a
32-bit machine that process thinks it
has 32 bits worth of a memory to play
with which is of course four gigabytes
and the way it works is this when the
process when the app wants to access a
particular address there is a particular
piece of Hardware in the CPU called the
mmu the memory management unit and what
it does is it maps from this virtual
address that the app thinks it's running
in to an actual physical address
somewhere in memory and so now the idea
of partitioning up the memory is
actually taken over by the operating
system and the app doesn't need to worry
the app thinks it's the only the only
app running it can write to whatever
addresses it's allowed to whichever
memory has been given to and actually it
doesn't care about other addresses from
other apps because it's got its own
virtual address space
so if we look at this diagram here we
can show that we've got app one and app2
now app one has an address space from
zero through to
5242880 that's about five Giga megabytes
of memory and I've also got app2 with
the same level of five megabytes of
memory and what you actually see is that
although it's from zero to there in the
physical memory it might actually start
at 5242880 and it might run for five
megabytes and then app number two
actually starts at
104.85760 and it runs from there for
five megabytes and the virtual address
zero in both apps is actually mapped to
different places in the physical RAM
now because there's mapping going on
here the apps can be mapped to
absolutely anywhere that the operating
system wants to put them so let's have a
look at this diagram so as you can see
here app 2 is as it was before it's a
five megabyte program from zero to five
two four two eight eight zero and it's
been mapped over to an address in the
middle there of physical RAM but app
number one has actually been divided
into two parts and the first half of it
is mapped into memory before app number
one and the second part of it is mapped
into some memory after app one but app
one and app two don't know anything
about this they just think they're
running in their address space from zero
to the end of their program so the
advantage of the virtual memory system
each app is self-contained it doesn't
write over other apps memory space
because it has its own virtual address
space secondly it doesn't matter where
the app is in memory because it is the
mmu that does the mapping between those
virtual addresses and the physical
addresses and thirdly the app doesn't
need to be in one continuous Block in
memory it can be split up over many many
different parts so this is the OS along
with the mmu that makes sure that each
address arrives at the right place in
physical RAM and therefore you get rid
of that memory fragmentation problem
now what I've shown you up until now is
a one-to-one mapping so that every time
you have one particular dress there's a
kind of a table that gets looked up by
the mm unit tells it where to put it uh
in physical RAM but the problem is even
for a 300 megabyte program which really
isn't that very big you'll need about 79
million entries in such a lookup table
to do such uh mapping and obviously if
you've then got 10 20 30 40 different
programs running on your system that's
going to quickly turn into a huge amount
of data and there'll actually be no
space left for actual programs because
it will all just be mapping information
so to get around this the main memory
the physical memory is divided into
different blocks and they're called
pages and typically they're about 4K in
size
and so now using paging actually you'll
find that a 300 megabyte app only needs
77 000 entries in a lookup table which
at four bytes for every entry is about
300K which is much more manageable
so now what happens when an app requests
something with a virtual address it
actually goes to the mmu and the mmu
finds out which page it's in and
redirects it to the physical address of
that particular page
however what happens when the address is
in the middle of a page at the start of
the page is easier there's a kind of a
one-to-one lookup but what happens if
it's in the middle of a page well
actually what happens is that 4K is 12
bits so the first 12 bits of the address
are copied directly from the virtual
address into the physical address then
the remaining 20 bits are used as the
page lookup that 20-bit address is
looked up in the page table I think
called a page table entry is found and
that then gives you the 20 bits for the
upper part of the address and then the
combination of the page address and the
offset those 12 bits gives you an actual
physical address in Ram
now one
so if we look at this sit up
see we only needs to the
only needs to translate the page right
the page number the virtual page number
to the physical page physical page
blender they have the same offsets right
they have the same officer because your
offsets will not change
the page frames has the same size of the
page you only need to know where exactly
your page is in which page frame then
you are good it gives you an actual
physical address in Ram
now one interesting question is where
are all these tables held well they're
not held in the CPU because even at 300K
or 400k multiply that by many many
processes running and there's just not
enough space in a CPU to do that so they
have to be held in Ram now that leads us
to a kind of an interesting uh conundrum
because to act as a virtual address the
mmu needs to access physical RAM to find
an entry in the table so it can then
translate the vert to address into a
physical address and then access Ram
again so you find there's multiple Ram
accesses happening for one ram access
inside of the app and of course that's
going to be slow if it's like two Ram
accesses needed or three Ram axes is
needed for each uh virtual address and
that's going to slow down your program
by by a factor of three so the way CPU
desires get around is they have a cash a
cash of recently looked up addresses
it's actually called the translation
look aside buff as a tlb and what that
does is whenever there's a dress
translated it gets stuck into this cache
and then the next time an address is
needed actually it looks it up in the
tlb but of course remember it only needs
to look up the page size so if the
program is running through the different
instructions inside of one page every
time it goes to access it it'll
automatically be a tlb hit because that
page has already been found and just the
offset changes which is absolutely okay
in some CPUs in fact the tlb is only 20
entries long it might be bigger than
that maybe 64 128 but you don't need
that many tlb entries to actually
increase the performance significantly
during this lookup
so what happens why tlb is is
so you see the tlb is actually in the in
a CPU right it's in the CPU in the CPU
registers
but the page table page table is in a
memory so remember the rush 3 is faster
than the cash and the memory
if the mmu can't find an entry in its
table for a particular virtual address
where in that case the mmu raises a page
fault and it goes back to the kernel
saying hey I can't find that address now
that can happen for one of three reasons
first of all the app is actually trying
to access an address which is not
allowed to to access it hasn't been
allocated that memory and therefore
Linux will just basically kill it off
you get a segmentation fault and the
program just crashes and just it just
gets wiped out of memory because it's
not allowed to access memory that it
hasn't been given
in the second case it could actually be
what they call Lazy allocation which
means that the kernel said yes you can
have that but it won't actually give it
a physical page of ram until it actually
starts to write to it and so in that
case the page for what happened the
kernels is okay I I told the app you
could use that memory here is where I
want you to put it in physical RAM the
mmu is reprogrammed and then the whole
thing starts off again and the address
is found in physical RAM
and the third thing that can happen is
the mmuses we used to have that memory
but actually now it's been swapped and
therefore the kernel will go and get
that page from the compress Ram The Zed
swap that it's actually put it in
earlier it will uncompress it it will
put it somewhere in physical memory it
will reprogram the mmu and say okay you
can now find that there and then the
whole thing Carries On
and so there we have it virtual memory
we've got a whole load of things going
on here you've got the virtual addresses
you've got physical RAM you've got
lookup tables you've got an mmu you've
got the translation looker side buffers
you've got page faults and all this is
being handled for you by the Linux
kernel and by Android so the next time
you tap an icon to launch an app just
give a thought for all that's going on
in the background just so that app can
be loaded somewhere into memory and it
can run so you can make that little
sprite jump across the screen
my name is Gary SIM from Android
authority and I hope you enjoyed this
video if you did please do give it a
thumbs up there's a
H okay so
um so this is basically the crystal the
key concept of the virtual
the um
the virtual memory the virtual memory
now there's
um
studying from the next class we are
going to learn the page replacement
algorithms so before that there's a
another concept is the multi-level page
tables so any student want to make a
guess why we need a multi-level page
table so multi-level page tables means
that instead of using one page tables we
divide the page tables into into a
hierarchical structure so the level one
page tables and then level two page
tables and then level three page tables
so while we need a multi-level page
tables
so is this already what else you don't
want to avoid keeping the entire page
table in memory because it is too big
right the page table maybe too big so
you do not want to put your entire page
table in memory so by using the
multi-level page tables you can put the
let's say the first level page table in
the memory then the second level and the
third level into the disk right then
then pay them for the multi-level page
tables you can put the most frequently
page mappings in the memory the
hierarchical one page table and put the
last frequently using the page level two
or the levels three and put the rest of
it in the disk the other disk then you
do not need to put the entire page table
in the memory that is very costly
because we do not have that in love
memory space okay
um
so here's the um take home question is
that we may have that in your homework
is that think of that we sell the
default page default page
size is 4kb right but the page size can
be as small as
um 150 to 52 bytes to
um like
um 64 KB is like a very large number of
page sizes so what is the good thing
about a small page size is a bad thing
about small page size and one good thing
about large page sizes and the
um bad thing about the large page sizes
think of that this is a design question
um
okay that's it um
then starting out the next lecture we
are going to learn the page replacement
algorithms okay
okay we still have
um
so for the page replacement algorithms
okay we are going to learn this
just a many different page replacement
of the algorithms they are
but it's very it's very easy to
understand it's like what we have
learned in the CPUs Gathering algorithms
has the same like first day in first
house like first come first serve right
and then we have the frequently most
frequently used page the optimal page
replacement algorithms the at least the
recently used page lru which is very
famous and we have the working third
page replacement algorithms so
um
okay so this is uh today's class okay
so thank you
foreign