uh okay
so
so today we are going to
um so first I'm sorry uh I was sick last
week so I didn't come uh for last class
and uh so today we are going to end the
memory chapter and the in our next class
I'm going to review the midterm so
um so this is the plan so for the memory
chapter
um
let's let's finish this chapter by
beginning with several questions so the
first question is that a design question
now think of that you are a system
designer you are a system designer now
you you you you you let's say you
otherwise ask you to design a new memory
management system and then you can
you can
um
oh sorry it's not page table it's Pages
size okay yeah
no the wiser once you design a new
memory management system and he gave you
a question you you are no longer too
limited to use the 4kb
default page size now you have
you need to decide by yourself whether
you want to use a small page size small
or large page size
or it can be small and it can be large
right the default in the default we use
the 4kb right we use the 4kb as the page
size now
you need to design a new memory
management system and you can
flexibility
choose a smaller much smaller page size
in the larger page size now my question
is what will be the what will be the
strengths and limitations for
small page size and large page size
and let's start with a small one okay
small
page size
okay we'll see the students
so what is the page what is the page
uh first let's let's review what is the
page
so or what is exactly a page a page what
is exactly a page
it's just a
what is a page and what is Page frame
page on the page frame
right the the page the page is the most
important obstruction in the memory
chapter right
page
so what is exactly your page or page
frame is
so we know that we we have let's say
yeah Lily
oh yeah very good a chunks the Bible
which the virtual memory is divided to
two right the virtual memory divided to
it so what is Page frame
or is the page frame
page frame is yeah Lily
so
the limit of what
page frame has the same size as the page
right yeah I think
frame would be
yeah yeah very good very good so so so
a quick review a very quick review so
you have a program
you have a chrome you write let's say
you write some code it's a program and
then we combine it and load it around by
the OS the CPU loaded that right loaded
that into the memory and it becomes a
process
so this is then become a process
remember when we're talking about the
process chapter uh we talk about the
differences between the process and the
stress and we're talking about what is
the process processes has it's called
it's data right and it's called the code
data the ownership the status of the
process and most importantly it's
includes the memory address space
relating to that process and so what is
the memory address space that is the
location where the process needs to be
loaded in the memory so we have a memory
let's say this is the physical memory so
one program become a process then we
need to load that into the memory right
so and then how where to load that into
the memory
the first thing is that you the CPU are
going to CR to
converts this process
into some a very large virtual memory
address space right so this process this
process
it contains the cold input outputs is
data and understand the stacks the heaps
the ownership the
process table a lot of data structures
so what are the CPU did is that is going
to give a very large virtual memory
address space a virtual memory from zero
to a very large to a very large value to
that process then and then
divided to that into many
small chunks small chunks
and the same chunks the same size of the
chunks and which of chunks are page
the default size of that page is 4kb
so that is the that is the page right
that is page then it's the this is the
virtual
memory
a little dress virtual memory okay
virtual memory virtual memory of that
process and then the next thing we did
is that after we divided in uh we gave
big after we the CPU give the process a
virtual memory address space and then
the next thing is that divided into many
pages and then we need to decide which
page we put into the physical memory
right so the physical memory we divide
the physical memory itself is a resource
it's a hardware it's a hardware so we
did what we did is that os are going to
it's like a very large distrib districts
right a very large District like like
you you live in for example you live in
a condor right a condo there's a whole
these trees there's many condos right
the same thing like this so there's
there's this is a very large space so we
need to divide it into that into many
empty spaces we call it a page frame so
this is a page frame
so the page frames are always the same
sizes page
then then the OS or decide which page
which page
is loaded into them is loaded into the
physical memory and physical memory and
they use a memory management units
to do that they use a memory management
units to do that to manage the mapping
so when we managing the mapping we have
use a data structure called a page map
Sometimes some books called page table
right page table
so what what page table did is that it
it shows the mapping about which virtual
address map to which physical
address physical address is the exactly
address in the memory in the memory and
then here the design question is that
now you you advise or ask you to design
a new mmu memory management units and
you can decide
you can use any page size you want so
the question is that what is the
benefits to do to design a small page
size or what is the limitations to
design a small page size in order
benefits to design a big page size
and the limitations to design a big page
size
all right so this is the story
no yeah
very good very good that's a very good
start okay so um
let's say if we have a very very large
page size if we have a very very large
page size then
so if we have a very large page size
let's say the page size is not no longer
like this small right it's no longer
like this small it will be
it will like like this the larger page
size
so this is the page size
okay very large very large page size
if we have a very large page size very
large page size
then the page table entries
will be smaller
will be what will be less right will be
less the page
page table
you see that let's see
if we have if we if we use this
part of the
page size this part is larger page size
like this is the physical memory okay
physical memory
physical memory this is your virtual
memory
virtual memory
of a process of P1 look at P1
so if we if we use a very large if we
use a very large very large page size
we will have we will have smaller page
tables think of that what think of why
why
we will have much less entries of the
page tables
why
pictures
you see this if we only have we will be
using this for only this big this size
of the big pages right we only need two
entries right because you only need
these two entries let's say to map into
here then the page this is the size of
the page table this is the size page
table but if we use this smaller this
smaller
Pages if we use a smaller Pages we need
more
more page table entries why because the
page table entries is the same need the
number of the page table entries is the
same as the page frames right the page
frames or the physical page frames so if
you are using
this is a little tricky here the page
frames is the same size as the page the
page size page frame is always the same
size as the page so if you use a large
page that means we are going to have a
larger
page frames then this memory the
physical memory will not divided as many
page frames at all
divided into much less page frames that
is why
if we we use much large page frames but
the memory the size of the memory is the
same then we will have much less page
table entries that is why if we using a
large
page size then we will have less
so
a large
let me write in here
right if we use a large page size mean
if we use a large page size then it
means
there will be the page frame it will be
our large
page frame
right means there will be large page
frame it means and it means
it means
less
page
table
entry
so it means the last page table entry
then that means a smaller page table
right then it means a smaller page table
so the battlefield is that a smaller
page table
small page table means that we can save
the memory consumption on the page table
because page table is stored in memory
right a smaller page table we save the
memory usage that is the that is the
good thing about large page size so in
office in obsessed in obsessed
a small page size a small page size
means a small page a small page size
means that there will be
small page frames right there will be
small page frames and there will be more
more page table entries and then it will
be larger
larger
page
table there will be larger page table so
it's
it's like
memory
closely okay it costs a lot of memory
overhead okay a larger page table
so that is they are the objects okay
obsessed so what else what else so and
let's go starting from here then it
seems that a large larger page size will
give us a small small page table then we
can save the memory usage right then we
can let's set the
memory the the page size to be extremely
big like the same size of the memory
we cannot do that right so there must be
some limitations about the larger page
size or is the limitations about that
Eric
is less uh
um
larger page size costs more page four
less pages in the page table then
not like that yeah
so my my thinking is that if you have
in your
memories and the harder to
fit like more
very good it's hot it's it's hot it's
hard it's difficult to fit more
processes and it's called wipe why it is
hard to fix more processes
remember when we when we're talking
about Pages or a page cannot be shared
by many process right a page can only be
belonging to one process so if we set it
to be very large
then what if a process is very small
it's very small like as small as this
it's very small
then this part is wasted this part is
wasted because the other process cannot
fit in
so we call this we call this to be
internal fragmentations
internal
fragment
so internal fragmentation so if we if we
use very large page size then we can not
efficiently holds the many concurrent
running process in the memory so it's
not efficient space sharing of the
memory we we cause a lot of internal
fragmentations look at this picture if
you make it extremely large but many
processes are just very tiny small they
only need this much of spaces but since
you push the page to be very large they
will be allocated to be one large page
one large page but they waste many
memory resources like this
many memory resources
so
so the limitations will be like
more
internal
fragmentations
more internal fragmentations
what um
anything else so in the eagle stream
extreme extreme
small small page size means that look at
this picture small page size means that
we can more efficiently
allocates the pages to different process
right and for example if a process size
is
101 process size is 50 51 and if we use
the page to be one if we the page size
to be one then this can have 101 Pages
this can have 51 pages right but if we
make the page size to be let's say 200
200 then that means this can only have
one page and the wasted 99
um
model like around half of the memory and
also for this right so if we give 200
size of 200 pages one page to it it will
waste it one 149.
memory resources so that is the you know
it's it all significantly reduce
significant reduce
reduce internal
internal fragmentation
um
so they are in the opposite right the
larger page size means means
the strength is a smaller page table we
save the memory we save the memory
safe memory
we save memory part it costs more
internal fragmentations in opposite the
small page size it will reduce the
internal fragmentations but it costs
larger page table so it weighs the
memory it's very cause a lot of memory
or hard but no one else
besides the internal fragmentation
besides the page table size what else
think of the page table will be impacted
right and
yeah
Well it's worse
oh we already talked about that the
modern internal fragmentations in
every right
Andrew okay Andrew
managing it will be more difficult about
who is who are managing it memory
management units right it used if we use
the page table to manage it right
and it's used
tlb right
then yeah
not exactly yeah Andrew
say again
you know
it's it's hard to catch fish so let's
think of that uh yeah
um
easy what's your name either Madre okay
let's say page four okay see who
for large Pages you say that page boards
will be more expensive why why page
force is more expensive
page four
so what is the page four page four means
that I couldn't find out
what is Page four page four is a mean
starch
couldn't find out the page in the memory
right
there's another page in the memory so
why larger
course is why larger page size costs
more page for it Lily
weather is still the same thing as the
internal fragmentation
all right that's just they are the same
thing as the internal fragmentation we
say that larger larger page size cause
more internal fragmentations right so
that it cannot hold the main Imports
pages in memory cannot efficiently use
the memory resources cause many internal
fragmentations so it may cause more page
Force but what else what else think
think of where you can think of two
different directions the first direction
is like we know that a page table will
be impacted right but how about tlb tlb
will be also infected right
Tob will be also infected right
why isn't say again
so in why why in fact internal
recommendation what is the internal
fragmentation
the only example okay let me let me make
an example so let's say we have the
memory memory
our memory is 100 okay memory is the 100
okay 100 now we divided in the with
let's say the page size
page size equals to 10 page size equals
to 10.
then how many page frames in memory
turn right
how many page frame in the memory
turn right this is the memory memory is
100 and we set each page size to return
so there will be 10 memory term page
frames in the memory right then in the
office let's say we still using 100 okay
let's say the page size
page size to be 25 then how many page
frames we have in the memory
only four
right
um
do you have any questions for that no
questions right no questions now if I if
if here
if I if there's many smaller processes
come in
this is P1 its size is equals to 2 P2
equals to 3 p 3 equals to four
P four equals to 5.
5 might be equals to one something like
that and we have we have 10 right there
they are all last they are all less than
one and then then ten then for the first
one we one we
when we design design small page size
we can hold
all these term processes in memory right
we can hold them together right
but 14 in this case in this case
after you hold this four
you cannot hold any more
say this is P1 with P1 or P1 and then
this is P2
P2 P3
P3 P4
P4
so look at this
for the first page how much resources
are wasted it's wasted
24 right
this is four pages four page frames
so are we in the same
so that this this 24 wasted mammal
resources is called fragmentation
that is why larger page size will cause
more fragmentations
but in this case in this case
they have all taken for different this
is P1 P2 P3 P4
for ip5 P5 P6
p7
p8
P9
P10 we can hold we can we can hold all
these processes into the memory but for
if we set the page size to be very large
we're very large
we each and then there's many smaller
processes coming because owning hold
much less
processes and we cause a lot of
bigger internal fragmentations so this
part like the P2 then P2 or P1 okay my
fourth
three okay this is 22 guard wasted P3 21
guard waisted
20. so this is all for augmentations
okay
that is the internal fragmentation so
larger page size will cause more
internal fragmentations but larger page
size
larger page size means a smaller page
table because we have much less page
table entries so if we have smaller page
table we also have a smaller tlb table
what is tlb
translation localized buffer so it's a
buffer it's a page tables buffer so it's
a page tables buffer so if we have a
smaller page table
then that means weekend that means we
have
we have a similar tlb 2 right and the we
in this case in this case
in this case we
we can hold more memory address in the
tlb
okay and then and then again
this
it will cost more page
per page Fort okay
but the uh the key takeaway here is that
you need to understand
internal fragmentation what is the
internal fragmentation and you need to
understand how it affects the tlb the
tlb and also the page table also the
page table
okay so that's the first review question
the first review question so let's look
at the SEC
oh okay sure
I'll give it answer
foreign
so where the takeaway here is to
remember this okay larger page larger
page and um
yes
the smaller page small page sizes
strength is that it will reduce the
internal fragmentation but the
limitations is that it will
it will cost much more page table
entries and of course larger page table
and also larger tlb and for the larger
page size it will cost smaller page
table and save the memory the strength
of that and the limitations is that more
internal fragmentation
uh okay so let's look at the second
review question so
um in our last class you have learned
let me show you this
foreign
give me one second
showing in our last class we we
um shouldn't discuss about the page
replacement algorithms right there's
many page replacement algorithms here's
um let's review
um
if I
to take away his data you need to
um
you need to understand what is the fifo
and lru and also there's a there's a
page replacement algorithm called the
optimal page replacement algorithms
right so the differences between these
three the differences between these
three
so
um
let me see
the slides
yeah so we talk about optimal page
replacement algorithms first thing first
out page Replacements Second Chance
clock page leads the recently used are
you working their page Replacements
um
so first what is the optimal page
replacement algorithms optimal page
replacement algorithms
optimal
opt
optimal Optimum
optimal optimal page replacement
algorithms
so this is a real life because I'm hot
okay so uh it's it's a real life example
so uh let's say I own a company my
company is um very good I have 100
workers they work for me
um
um some some come to my company very at
very early times some I recently joined
my company so here the cases that this
year is not good year so I'm this I I
decided to file some some employees from
my company so how should I decide who
should leave my company
yeah Shayla
but how can I know this
he or she is the least efficient so the
the thing is that well this year okay
this year I need to make a plan for this
year right the coming year
well the I have you guys you are all
working for me okay I'm going to decide
who to go who should I file so I can the
thing is that the future the future is
not happening yet so I do not know who
are going to be bad or who are going to
be super good I do not know
but but the thing is that I want to fire
someone
who will not be like who who are most
inefficient right in the coming year but
the challenge is that I will never know
who is because the future will not come
yet
you cannot predict the future
so how to decide
the criteria is that I need to fire the
one who is
who are not produce any
contributions to to my company right who
will not make any contributions in my
company in the coming year
so who should I fire
so fifo means that I fire the old person
right you you come early you old I file
you so that if I have always that this
is very this is this is actually in real
life it happens right so many companies
they just fire when they fire people
they look at the CV and see who is the
old guy
then lru means lru means
l u means
my company has been run for 10 years
let's say it has been run for 10 years
lru means that I only look back to the
past year for the past I only look back
for the past year the recently the least
recently used list recent reviews means
that well no matter how how good you are
in the back of the nine years for the
past year I only looked at the past year
you did nothing then you should go that
is the lru algorithm lru algorithms and
look at what are the optimal optimal
page replacement algorithm means that
I have a superpower I know what will
happen in the future
and I can see I can see what I can like
I have let's say I have this I'm
Superman I have super power I can see
what happens in the future and I know
you are not going to be produced any com
profits in my company so you you leave
that is the optimal so in real life
there's there's in real life there's no
optimal but while we put it there
Magic
yeah we want to get as close to are you
possible so optimal it means that one is
useful for evaluation it's like the
worst fees algorithm remember we talk
about that in our previous lecture it's
the same thing the optimal page
replacement algorithm is that we want to
um
we want to
we we want to design algorithms and we
will rock you know we will use that we
use that as the criteria to measuring
how good my current algorithm is okay
so what will be the second chance page
replacement algorithm the second chance
there's another algorithm means the
second chance
the second chance
is the second chance is is a improved
algorithms
after fifo
right yeah
the racial lie behind the second chance
that is how you're going to implement
the second chance but you need to well
here's the when we design the system we
need to understand the relation line
behind it right let's say the fifo means
that the oh the the first Pages we
we think that the first page is the
first common pages will not be referred
in the future so we just invicted but
the second chance
the Second Chance the ration line behind
the second translator
behind the second job it's it's an
improvements improvements over the fifo
so
why is the improvements because like
many times we only need to remember like
who is the first who is the first
account right we're just using a queue
we see a q
to remember they are they are coming
orders they're coming orders and then
what we need to in week that pages from
our physical memory we just look at the
queue who is the head of the queue then
we remove it that is the key idea of
fifo we we are not going to we are not
going to
um
think whether they are rougher or not
whether they are referred or not so the
second chance algorithm Second Chance
algorithm is that
we
time the time we decide to invict that
pages and make that page because this is
the first is the first loaded it's the
first coming pages
we gave it a second chance we just using
a a bit to remember that we gave the
second chance to it or not and we put it
at the back of the queue
so that is the um
pardon these algorithms they are not
good however it slightly performs better
than the i5fo and then then
someone decide someone
um
designed the algorithm according the
reason the Lord recent lot recently used
a lot of recently used and then
improving the algorithm is the
least recently used page replacement
algorithms so the takeaway of this
chapter is most important is these two
okay these two
these two and the reason why we are
going to review in today's class
so let's do this together okay
let's do this together
let's do this calculator so we have
given the following streams of page
referenced by our application calculates
the number of page fours the application
would incur with the following page
replacement algorithms and fill in the
content of the page frames of the memory
after each memory reference assume that
all pages are initially free
so we have the reference streams here so
this is the this is your memory your
memory only have four frames
for page frames okay
do you want to try
let's do this together okay let's do
this if I have all together okay okay so
we have we have the reference streams in
this order
okay so what a comes one comes with the
course of page four
yes why because the
it's not in memory right it's not in
memory so we need to handle this page
four we need to
gathered from the disk and updates the
page table and update the tlb
there will be a
so here the oldest page right so this is
this will be the and we have using this
as a page Force so when B comes with
your page four
yeah there will be right because there's
no B here there's no B here in memory
here look at this this is the memory
right there's no B here
okay we only have sorry we only have
this August 3 3 3 page three page three
physical pages okay not four or three
okay not four three okay and when C
comes there will be a
there's no C look at this this is our
memory right our memory only have the
page a and the page B there's no C so
when C comes reference streams means
that we need this page so we see if it
is in memory it's not in memory so
there will be page fours right
I mean
make it larger
so let the
okay so here's the thing
D comes okay D comes so we first look at
is the inner memory one notch this is
our memory
there's no D in the memory right so
there
is a page for it right there's a page
for it see there's page force that who
should get out who should get out
in three pages three of pages a b c so
this is fifo algorithm first in first
out okay
who is the oldest guy
Aaron
ayok card a we should kick out a right
and then we should kick out a then B
becomes the oldest page right
and then d d is there
this there right this there b becomes
the oldest page and then C
okay
now a now a again so when a comes we
look at the memory do we have a in the
memory
we do not have a in the memory right we
do not have a in memory
so there there are the page Force right
there's a page four so we do not have a
in the memory there's a page for them we
should kick out who should kick out the
first inverse Out means we look at the
existing pages in the memory to see who
is the oldest one who is the oldest one
so in this case b is the oldest one
right
this B is the oldest one right
so we should let me go out
and then a where we should put a
well you should put a
so a becomes the
newness page right it becomes the newest
page right
so let's continue
and then next we have B
B here so we first look at this is the
memory this is our memory is there any B
in the memory the page B
there's no page B in the memory right
so that there is a page Forge there's a
page forms and then who should get out
the first in first out algorithms
Costa
which one is the oldest
which one should all this C is the
oldest right see the oldest page we
always saved so we put C so C goes out
and then D becomes the oldest page and
then a and then B right
the next e e comes it comes with C first
C is there any e in the in our memory
our physical memory there's no e there
so there's a page four right so since
there's no in
in memory then we need to design the
whole should get out so first in first
algorithms things that they should get
out right
this is the oldest one
the average D get out a should move up
right and then B and E since e is using
the joint so e becomes a newness page
so that is a b e
right
now a
comes is there any page four
no there's no page Force right because a
b e a is already there
right
a is already there
so there's no page Force
there's no page Force
then
there's no page Force okay and B comes
here is there and in page four
yes
yeah we do not we do not because there's
no page Force it's not the new list
Pages the previous page this is the
previous this is not the new list yeah
you know I've I've first thing in first
house remember the differences the the
advantage of the first thing in first
out any student remember compared to the
least recently used algorithms fifo
algorithms they they are very
um in the slides I mentioned that it's
fifo it's very easy to implement
because there's no tracker you do not
need to maintain a clock information
for each pages to remember like how many
times it is got referred you do not need
that information you do not need the
window information you only need a queue
so in this case one a this is a very
good question okay you do not move the
move it to the newness page because it
is not the at least a reason to use the
algorithm
if it is the list lru algorithms we may
need to move because we need to track to
see how frequently they get accessed but
in the fifo we do not we just see okay
if it is already there then that's
already there we're just managing the
queue remember there's a queue there
we're just the menu in the queue like
move the first item in the QRS and
inserts the new items in in this in this
when it comes there's no insert
operation remember that when we designed
the data structure there's only one
queue we do not insert any new items in
because it's already there so we do not
update the order in the memory
okay so there's no page Force right the
same as the one because the bear
there's no page Force because B is
already there b is already in the queue
the queue in the queue is that a b e
we do not insert B again
so that is Abe
now C comes no C comes so we have the Q
as a b e now C comes then C needs to
insert at the back of the queue and then
kick out a right so we have a page four
[Music]
D comes
becomes
it comes
so there's
this not in the memory right it's not in
memory so there's a
page four right and then we need to this
is the height of the queue right height
of Q we need to kick it out
and move the water right so it becomes
ecd
so the same as y e comes
comes to the systems
it's already there so there's no page
for there's no page for right there's no
page for
there's no page force and then we do not
need to change the queue B when B comes
becomes B is not in the queue right in
the queue there's only e c and d there's
only e c and d so we
close our page four
three four
then we need to insert the B at the end
at the end of the Q and then click e out
so it's a cdb right then on a comes the
same thing we need to kick C out
and then move a after there's a page
fourth
okay and then here B is already there so
we do not do anything
there's no page force in this case
okay how many one two three four
eleven
okay so this is the f i yeah
her page force is not the same as the
cash means
we talk about that later okay I think
Sean has not yet talked about cash
um yeah I'll talk about that later
we have not
page for this page Force cash is
um
cashes cash okay
page means that page Force means that
are all better it is located in the
memory what not the pages in the memory
or not
emojis
because the memory is empty
there's no page a and no page B is there
memory is empty
the memory is initially empty right
but a cash Miss not having or vice versa
yeah let's talk about cash late um in
our maybe next next lecture okay
let's finish this first oh I have
another
so caches there uh
let's talk about that later okay
so you well you see cache is not in the
cap when we are talking about cash cash
is in between the register and the
memory right
right so page fourth only means that
whether it is in a memory or not
no matter what is the cash or memory
they are not at the disk they are not at
this everything's at the disk versus
Less on the same page okay everything is
on the disk everything everything is on
disk but whenever you have a new
programs you need to load that in the
memory to process it if we frequently
usage then we may put that contents in
the cache
or in the register but that is the CPU
design the page Force means that if we
cannot find it in the cache we cannot
find it in the memory then means that
well this thing is in the disk so we
need that we call Page four that will
cause a page Force
so let's look at this lru so you want to
try
you want to try this
I'll give you some time to try this okay
okay
so let's do it together so still
um
when it comes it's it's a it's a
it's a page Force right because it's
empty right so the first three are the
same he has magic
yeah yeah yeah it's not a matter is that
matter yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah you come
for that
it's actually it's it doesn't matter
it's that matter if you can put it there
so yeah
yeah yeah it's done so that's why it
doesn't matter yeah
you can do that it doesn't matter you
can put it
even exam we have some similar questions
you can have it there was there it
doesn't matter you can you can cause
examity you can put it anywhere this
reason to use the one when there's new
contents comes then you need to
differentiate that they are like who is
the most recently used who is not the
most recently used so but is this so
same thing like if there's only a you
know who is better there's no
differences you can say a is the best or
you can say a is the worst but if
there's a b and a c then you need to
distinguish who is the best who is the
worst that is the case okay so the ABC
is the same
then okay when D comes okay D comes then
they are definitely a page fours right
because
there's no page no this page in the
memory right there's a page Force so one
Z joins the system when they joins the
system
so we need to see who is the most recent
user page see see right then who is the
least reason to use the page a right so
a should get out and we put D to be
there then when we put D to be there
D becomes the most recently used page
right
and the b c are moved up
B becomes the least reason used page
okay now a now look at a when a comes
there's only b c d in the system in in
memory so there's a page fort
there's page fourth now
we need to remove the least reason to
use the page out of the system
then we put a to be here right a to be
here and then C become the least
recently used page
okay
are we following
yeah
not be
let's reference B we have not found a
we haven't already found a B in the in
the memory right there's no B in memory
so they are definitely a page four
right
then
B becomes the most recently used page
all right and then we put a b it will be
there right okay now e e when you comes
there's no e in the system right there's
no e in the system so there's a page
four
so we put e to be there
remove a b to here now this is the
tricky ones here the tricky one is here
uh
pay attention Okay so in the fifo one a
one a comes and we found a in the system
we do not change their order right
because there's only they only maintain
a q but in the list replay Pace
replacement algorithms when a comes we
see a is there
right so there's no page four there's no
page Force this is empty however we need
to change A's order in in memory a
becomes the most recently used page
a becomes the most recent used page and
EB are move up
EB a move up this is the challenging
part is there the others are the same as
the iPhone
okay
now B comes now who should I put in the
most recent page
BSB
and
remove the others up right and the C
comes now there's no C in the system
right there's no C in the system
so there's a picture there's a page four
there's no C in the system there's a
page for
then we put C
in the most recent page right and then
we move a b up e is the least reason
page so e should be T card
now D comes there's no D in the C
Samurai
there's no D in the season so there's a
page fourth and we put D there in the
most recent page because we just use it
and then BC BC move up now e comes here
right there's still a page fort
we put e there because e is the most
recent page and then we put CD up
now B is here since there there's no B
in the system so there's a page for it
and we'll put B here and the c e d to
move up
then a here so there's a page four
because there's no a
then we put a to be here
b e to be up
and now b b is there so there's no page
four no page fours right no page fault
then
we put WE Post B there
and move a e up
okay
so 12 right 12.
page four
okay so this is the second review
question so let's look at the subtle
review question
oh okay
yeah you can um
take a photo of that and practice in uh
after the class
okay okay so
um
so um
and the third question is that on the
workflow
the workflow of handling
a page fort
the workflow of handling a page fault
the workflow of handling a page Force
the onions still didn't want to have a
try
so we first have
um I think I gave you
um
so we first have the CPU
generous of virtual address for that
process right and then
and then we let's say we want to look at
the address look at a physical page we
want to see if it's in a memory so we
first look at the first look at
generates the virtual memory address the
virtual memory first generates the
virtual memory address for that process
right the virtual memory address
for that process and then and then let's
say we need to the CPU the program
counter is points to our instruction now
you need to find out that instruction
you need to know if that instruction is
in the memory or not the first thing you
need to look at is the
the first thing we need to look at the
yeah
the tlb yes look at the tlb translation
look aside buffer the translation look
outside buffer save the frequently the
most frequently used mappings the
virtual page to physical page mappings
of the page table so you can single the
TLP it's just a buffer a cache of the
page table it's just a cache of the page
table so it's saved the most recent use
the mappings of the virtual memory to
the physical memory that is the word tlb
did tlb most of the time tlb is a
registered in the CPU that is why CPU
first look at the tlb because it's very
fast it's super fast register
is faster than the cache and the memory
so that is why CPU are always looking at
the tlb first to see if the exactly
mapping the virtual page to the physical
page mapping if it find out if it
Finance then it can perform a address
translation right you remember the how
to perform the trend address translation
we just exchange the page number the
virtual page number to be the physical
page number and adding the offsets then
we can find out the exactly physical
address in the memory and then locate to
the exactly memory address and find out
the code that we want that is how it did
so firstly we look at the tlb and the
second we look at the
yes
page table Yeah second we look at the
page table and if it's some means so if
ttlb is a means if page table is a Miss
then that means that means they have so
paid Force at this time there means the
page fourth right
page fourth so we next we look at we
we go to the disk all right we go to the
disk we go to the disk and then we
locate the file then we
put start we put that in the we locate
the file we fetch the file
we initialize our IO interrupt to the
CPU and ask CPU to load that file in the
disk actually the page in the disk into
the page frame
in the page frame when we do that if
page frame is is empty then we simply
can load it that into the page frame but
if it is not empty if the page frame is
4 I mean that memory is four there's
four of all four page frames right
there's no empty page frames then we
need the page replacement algorithms to
help us find out who should get out
which page should get out there's fifo
algorithm Second Chance algorithm
um least recent use algorithms we just
reviewed right and then we find upload
we find out which page should get out
then we put our new pages comes in
then we need two we need two
updates
we need to update the page table right
we need to update the page table
mappings the physics the virtual page
number to the physical page number
mappings because right now the page
frames is not exist it's it's the new
contents so you need to change replace
the old mappings to be the new mappings
that map to this page the exact page
that I want after I recover updates the
page tables I need to
recover the tlb right we need to recover
the tlb
tlb
and then
and then in the end right
that is the that is the how we how we
handle the uh the work frame of handling
a page Force handling a page fort
yes
oh that's a very good question you
remember the remember the pay in the
page table we have the we have different
entries there's one bits that are that
tells you whether this page is 30 or not
right so after you click it out you
first you first need to find out if it's
30 or not if it's dirty means that it
has not yet
right to the disk then when you kick out
the first thing if it's 30 you need to
write it to disk if it is not dirty that
means it's read Odin so you basically
have a copy of the disk there's already
a copy of this so you just remove it
see yeah okay so uh I I um yeah let's
grab me
I think I have a better picture
let me do this
so look at this look at this just look
at this picture just look at this
picture
is there anything missing there is there
anything missing there
hence not this one this one
look at this this is the this is the
workflow of the page Force
but it isn't one Arrow there's one arrow
in this workflow
with an arrow in the in this workflow
yes
Andrew
yeah
yeah no trophy yes there's no TRV right
there's no TRV but we can
this is a very good picture this is from
the old textbook in the old textbook
there's no trb yet as I got it from very
old textbook all right this this is very
this is very intuitive picture so we
have to see we have the
you have the let's say the um operating
system right you the load the load Visa
is a compiler in instruction load we
have to you load and add maybe push this
is a company instruction right your your
code is going to be translated to
combiner code and then CPU generates a
virtual address
space memory address space for that for
that real code and then point to the
instruction of the each line of the code
the first thing that it needs to find
out okay you know that you know the
let's say you load this page and you
find out where you need to find out that
whether it is in the physical memory or
not so here this is the physical memory
so to find out whether it is in the
physical memory or not you need to look
at the tlb first and then look at the
page table why you need to Patient look
at the page level because the page table
is like the index
you know in a in a book you you all read
a book right in the books we have a
chapter right we have the chapter is it
shows the index it tells you uh which
exactly chapter goes to which page so
the page table is like the chapter of
your book the chapter of your book you
so the one when I read a book like the
OS book right you need to find out the
memory chapter then you need to look at
the index of the chapter index of the
book to find out oh well the page number
for the like chapter four memory so that
is why we need to look at the page table
first the page table first within the
tlb what is tlb tab is like a very
smaller page table it's like the
the front page of that book right it
only shows the most important contents
and tells you exactly the page number
like give some keywords and tell you
where exactly these keywords is that is
like a tlb so we look at the page table
and then we can find out oh okay the
page number of that contents and we look
at the page number if it's there in the
physical memory then we are good if it's
not there we need to go to the where we
need to go to
we need to go to the disk right that is
why if there's a Miss if there's a Miss
then we need to find out the page in the
disk this is a chart operation is why is
the chart operation causes you need to
the operating system to do to locate the
page from the disk yes
correct is it TLD like a smaller page
table that has information about like
recent uh
the recently accessed mappings the
physical the virtual address to physical
address mappings
so it's like a cache
um say again
yes everything is in the disk of course
your programs your everything's in the
disk right
you he's the same he's the same
um
you you guys still remember have the
intuition remember that I told you like
you have a very large programs you have
a very large program this is very large
but you cannot hold that everything in
the memory but then but then when you
load that programs
right when you load this is your program
while you're loading that the CPU are
going to
pretense they know everything about they
it's already in the memory so that is
why the CPU are going to generate a very
large virtual address from 0 to a Max
number to the to your code so this is
already in the disk in the disk
you can think of that we put it from the
disk we ask CPU to generate a virtual
address space to that process to have a
program and then CPU points to one page
let's say the loading page the loading
page then CPU are going to process that
the CPU make can only process everything
in the memory so CPU needs to know
whether this contents in the memory or
not that is why CPU look at the page
table but if you cannot find the page
level is or you always in the disk yeah
yeah yes yeah sure
let's say windows
10 years on backing stories on the disk
it's only this
is
um
you can think of this it's on the disk
it's just on the disk there's no no
backing store this kind of keywords in
the OS
yeah if you think of that it's just a
disk okay and then and then we bring out
the missing page in the memory the
memory so this is a free free what is a
free frame you know he's put a free
frame if it is so why is a free frame
because initially if it's four we've
already replaced it out at this time we
need to replace the old the for example
the not recently used this recently used
Pages out we kick it out and we put the
new pages in because we put the new
pages in so the mapping is changed right
the mapping specifically relates to that
page is changed that is why we need to
update the page table then we update the
tlb and we go back
yeah Andrew
yeah yeah pretty much yeah
okay so um okay this is how to handle a
page fort
okay and this is the let's say this is
the um okay Refresh on the page for
service okay
um
yeah we uh yeah you need to remember
this workflow because this is very
important you need to remember this
workflow okay um and uh you should be
able to draw this workflow
okay and so another refresh so when we
calculating you when we calculating the
um
to do the address translation okay we
only need to change translate the page
number The Logical page number to the
physical page number so page mapping is
about which virtual page map to which
real physical page
okay so that is the mapping okay
um
okay another thing is about the uh okay
so this is already covered
so um you need to understand the
differences between different algorithms
section already mentioned there so this
is the comments okay
um fifo is always
um it's very easy to implement so the
ariu is excellent but difficult to
implement why it's difficult because
this need to remember a lot of things
like when you come when you first
referred how many times have been you
have have you been referred for the past
like a sliding window it needs to
remember a lot of things okay and
working search okay what is the working
set algorithms
the key idea of the working set um
things to mentioned that the key idea of
the working set because
when you in when we initially load
something like boost OS we cannot we
cannot like what we did in the exams
like put one page after another page
after another page it's too inefficient
so working set means that
we do not we do not fetch Pages after
Pages we start fascist batches of the
batches and each batch is called working
set that is the key idea of without
about a working cells okay
okay under another key points to the
memory chapter is that the differences
between paging and segmentation so
so what is exactly segmentation
segmentation uh means
um in the in the in in maybe 20 years
ago um there's some systems that are
used only in paging some systems use
only segmentation and some system
operating system use paging plus
segmentation so a segmentation means
that we
we we divide the memory into many
different parts and each part we save
one type of data that is segmentation
for example this part we only save tax
the code and this part we only save the
like the images and this part we only
save the uh
the
hips like the um
a dynamical or located memory so that is
the key idea of the segmentation so if
you look at the segmentation you can see
that
these are the you they always see they
always puts the symbol tables there and
the source tax constraints callbacks so
there's many different segments and puts
different types of data that means the
key idea of the segmentation we do not
use segmentation a lot we use
um
we we mainly use the page in paging
technical in the model OS okay so this
is today's class and uh um so I'm
thinking doing a review of the midterm
in next class or maybe in the class
after next class yeah and then after
that we are going to finish the file
system and the Hot Topic yeah
uh I didn't get that what's the question
like why does Beijing why the page 40s
exist
be like thankful