is
okay so if you have any questions about
your exams or your grade
Grace if you have any question about the
grading of your project assignments or
exams you need to send email to my heart
here okay you can send email to any of
the Tas it doesn't matter but then and
then if they cannot handle that they
will send me email so the reason is that
we uh I'm not the one who's creating
your homework or projects they are the
ones who create your projects or
homework and they can
help you regret if you have any concerns
about that so if you do not know their
emails you need to take pictures and
these slides are in our canvas okay
I received many many emails about that
about the great issues uh what I did is
that I will I will just forward it to my
head here but I suggest you directly
send email to my hatia to get a promotes
reply
um
okay and I know I know many of you are
not happy with your project once great
uh
um well uh so the thing is that um we
cannot regret the projects every time
okay but for this time I'm I'm going to
ask my ta to do an exception so to
if you want to so today will announce
that about how to do that if you are not
satisfied with your grades you have a
chance only one chance to uh redo that
okay but this is just a warm-up for the
other projects to you you do not have
that opportunities
okay the only exception that is that you
you may find out some if you receive a
comments like suspected plagarisms then
you do not have any chance to redo that
that means you failed in that project
you will receive zero and if that
happens again you automatically cut F in
my class so are we sure about that
we do we if you got the comments about
suspected algorithms that means we have
enough evidence to to prove that you did
cheating okay no matter so what is the
cheating
um
borrow code from a report from someone
reading previous Solutions giving codes
or reports to someone copying called a
report from anyone including from the
internet
howling someone to write your code or
your report submitting someone else code
or reporters you own look at everyone
else code or report
so okay so uh
so in summary so for your project one
you have
um this is the only one-time exception
we I'm going to ask my ti to announce
some directions for you to redo that
project if you are not satisfied with
your grades so you have one chance to do
that but the exception is that if you
receive a comment saying that you
TI is expecting you paragraphisms or
cheating or copying the code then you'll
have no chance to reduce it to redo the
project one
you got zero on that project
and uh remember if you did that
repeatedly
you are automatically fail in the class
and I will not talk to you I will not
discuss with you I just directly reports
to the school okay
so I hope we are clear about that
uh okay so this is the
so another thing that we all have our
midterm we will have our midterm in the
next next
Thursday
next Thursday so it is your
responsibility to attend the midterm or
final The Only Exception we can make so
I need to be fair to everyone I will not
release or schedule anytime earlier than
the final midterm for one or two
individual this is unfair because I do
not want my exam papers released before
the actual exam day so I hope you guys
can understand that and the only
exception that I can make is like urgent
situation like medical situation and we
need the doctor notes about that like
for example you go to an emergency room
something like that then I'm going to
schedule a makeup and the makeup exam
will be different than the uh the others
exams I have two separate papers and
there's no guarantee that they are in
the same difficulty level
um
so in the um the exactly
final dates of the the final exam day
and Midterm will be you can see that in
the converse okay it's um the next
Thursday the next Thursday we'll have
our
midterm we will not have any class in
the Tuesday the Tuesday is for you I
will be in the zoom to answer you for
any questions about exams but we will
not have any class in Us in the Tuesday
okay and in the Thursday the same time
we will have our midterm here
okay so are we clear about that the
midterm we were testing the introduction
the um what we have learned so far
before the midterm before the midterm
like the process threat dialogue
dialogue is what we are talking about
today okay
oh
my God that's what seems not working
foreign
okay so today we are going to start
learning another new chapter dialogue
um
so before we go to the dialogue section
the chapter
uh
so any questions about your projects as
homework assignments grading
midterm final
any questions
oh that's very good question you are
going to on there are some coding
questions there you're going to write
the code there are also some multiple
choice single choice questions uh I
think there will be no no multiple
choice or in single choice questions and
there are some uh
some short answers some short answers so
it's a mix mixing mixing
uh questions mixing there's different or
different formats there are also some
algorithms questions that may need you
to
to do some math math remember what we
did in our last class we calculating the
scheduling right and we also calculating
the average turn run time the QA time
something like that
um
yeah there will be uh
there will be different formats not just
not just I know some of them I know some
some exams just have the
single choice or multiple choice
questions it's easy to grade but it's
not easy it's not good for you because I
want you to um
understand what we have learned yeah
what
what what what do you mean by that 30
someone tell you what
ah
well I can I'm gonna try to give you
some hints in our next class
yeah and it will be closed the loads
closed book
uh you cannot bring anything you need to
bring your uh uclc card and we we I I
I'm going to ask all my graders or my
Tutors or my Tas to come here to
to help with the exam so they will check
the your identity the only thing you can
bring is uh
is is the is is the ID card and the pen
and we are going to give you the papers
the papers so you have a empty paper
that you can do the math
Okay so
yeah
you gotta yeah it's one um yes
no calculator no you do not need to with
the calculator to do that you should be
able to do the math by yourself
yeah because in some calculator we know
that some calculator can
memorize something we want to know what
that happens yeah
because we have not some very smart
calculator I heard of that
yeah the math should not be a problem
the math should not be a problem
okay so uh
okay so um
here my suggestion for you you start to
go over my slides especially what we
have discussed in the class because and
uh
review your homework review your
homework
um
in this in in the next chapter's
homework we are going to give you some
coding questions and the midterm may not
exactly the same but it will be the same
style so if you understand if you can
finish your homework by yourself and in
a good way then you should be okay with
the midterm
I do not want to challenge you give you
a bad time hard time like I'm only going
to test what I have thoughts in the
class
okay yeah so everything is in the slides
that's everything
okay so uh today we are going to learn
dialogue
here the takeaways you need to remember
you need to understand the condition
what is dialogue the conditions for
dialogue there's four conditions for
deadlock to happen so what that means
means that all link all in four
conditions concurrently happen
dialogue will happen if only three
conditions happen in one condition is
not satisfied then the Denmark or not
happen so we and you need to understand
what are these four conditions and then
correspondingly there's
um
for strategies to handling the dialogue
deal with the dialogue okay that is the
takeaway so let's start from the
beginning what is the dialogue okay
so before we go to the deadlock
the deadlock uh definition let's do some
review about what we have learned a pre
-emptible resource and a non-premital
resource okay so the resource um
the resource has two types preemptable
and non-preemptable
so here in the slides if you look at
that so what is preemptable
what is preemptable means preemptable
emojis
you can cancel out of the uh you can
cancel out of a process when another
process enters and another and another
one dot Edge one of them is preemptible
one of them is not predictable I
the uh preemptable is the one where you
and it's like cancel out of the process
but I I might I might be mixing it up
yeah it is it's actually there is like
one is like the resource can be taken
away taken away by whom so here we also
process and stress interchangeably okay
use processors interchangeably we have
so what that means we have a lot of
process we have a lot of stress think of
that the same same meaning in in this
definition we have many processors that
share the resources so the preemptible
means that it's if the resource can be
taken away like can be taken away from
one process to another process like I'm
the process a I'm running I'm using the
CPU now and then someone can take take
the CPU resources from my
from my end to his end to her and that
means this is preemptable so CPU is a
preemptable resources
um so how does CPU take away between the
process we have learned that how this
will take away
pitch any anyone still remember or
there's three states
three stage of the of a process
three states what are they
three
yeah what's your name Andrew Andrew
you you're another Angel okay boss
Andrew okay yeah
blocked already blocked and running and
already so um
blocked running and the rally right so
you remember like one week when when we
are running right one process is running
there's a chance
that is goes to the block stage right
block State and that means it's why why
they go to the brook States
because it may receive some IO interrupt
request
they asked him to wait some IO requires
then start running again right and then
there is an example about it it is taken
away the CPU okay
and non-preemptable what are the
resources of long preemptable the disk
files okay disk files new text from your
text
sorry
this files in the text they are
non-preemitable
um
for example if that means it cannot take
away
for example if you have a file in a disk
you you have a file in your disk
only you can only can
like delete the file right only you will
also write the owner the other process
these are the other process without your
permission they cannot delete the file
for you and relieve the space
okay
then let's go to the other definition
and then another definition is request
request use and release
so request means process a proportions
away once the CPU freedom of the spill
time or the memory memory space is
requested you request that requested
once it requires the guard satisfied got
committed then it can use the resource
and what is the release release means
that it it releases the space right
release the resource to other
and another definition is establation
starvation means the process waits in
feet indefinitely and it is and it is
waiting so if we have many process they
are sharing with some resources like for
example if if several process entered a
share resource we put a critical region
like prop to product the resource and if
process a is entering that critical
region and runs for quite a long time
then the other processor goes to a
starvation why because mutex cannot be
taken away so some non preemptable
resource so you have to wait outside the
critical region and the result is that
you are going to be very hungry you will
not get the result that's that's a
situation that scenario we call it
starvation
and that lock what is Deadlock
so dialogue is a set of process
it's a it's a subtle process have a
dialogue if each process is waiting for
an event there are only another process
in the search can cause
I'm gonna try to understand that okay
try to understand that
so uh what I'm thinking the dialogue is
that well you you a process let's say
process a and process B process a
holding some resources and request
process a holding some resources
requires another resources from process
B while process B is holding the
resources that process a wants and he
he refused to release to process a and
in the meantime he is also requesting
the resources that process a holds so
they have a loop you will see like they
they were they were they will create a
loop and we call it if that happens we
call it or that then knock scenario
because none of them can guard
successfully
proceed so this is process a this is
process B so it
will look at that later okay
so preemptable and alarm Preamble
resources sequence of events required to
use the resources well again this is
definition but you need to request to
Resource use resource and release the
resource let's look at the real life
example
Let's uh look at this
process a is holding resource R right
or you need to know how to draw this
resource allocation graph okay because
this is the audio header we can we can
manually find out if there's any
dialogues in our system so you need to
learn how to draw that we use a circle
we use a circle to represent a process
we use a square to represent a resource
and if resource if process a is holding
a resource then we use this
array this array
so since this is not showing very
clearly there's a direction here
then this means process a process a is
holding the resource R its resource r
so process B requires the resource as
process B requests
process B we use a circle to represent a
process we use a square to represent a
resource process B requesting the
resource s so it is the direction like
this okay now a circle in a resource
allocation graph then that calls the
dialog that causes a dialog
if a let's see for example a requests
for S right a requested for S while
holding r a's holding R right is holding
r and the B is holding as B holding s
and the requesting for R so you can see
if you look at this this picture you can
see that one of them
now none of them
can get what they want
so this is like the uh
what we have learned in our last class
if we remember the philosophy dying
problem right
um the philosopher leads the two forks
to
to start eating the pasta pasta so it's
like the a needs the resource S and R to
run and B also requires resource SNR to
successfully running but
they each just got one right you
remember the philosophy that are dining
problems we have six philosophies we
have six folks right and the the extreme
case is that is that each of the
philosophical one folk and none of them
can start eating the pasta so that it
causes that look
I'm doing let's look at this example
so we have the process a we use a circle
to represent the process okay we have a
process a process a
and process B okay
so this process and what they need to do
is they'll copy the file from the tape
to the disk and print the file to the to
the printer
so
so both of the process needs to do these
things they need to they need to look at
they need to get the tape and copy the
needs to each of them needs to get three
resources together the tape the disk
printer
then what they need to do is that
what they need to do is that they the
process
copied a file from the tape to the disk
to disk energy
print the file from the disk to the
printer
but the the so there are three resources
what are three resources the tape the
disk the printer printer
so here we can see a deadlock happens
why it happens like a holds the table in
the disk right hold the table disk then
requests a printer where B holds the
printer holds the printer and requested
tape and the disk
what are the resource allocation Circle
in this graph
how many we have
how many Circle we have in the graph
two right
yeah we can see it from
this is one right
this is one
but this is one right
and now another one is from here
right
so uh let's look at again the dialogue
definition we have a several process is
dialogue if each process in the set
waiting for an event and the third
events can be caused only by another
process
so there is a dialogue definition okay
dialogue definition
so the condition so remember the
takeaway of today's class is four
conditions and four strategies so we
look at the first condition uh the the
first takeaway is four conditions
so four conditions that must hold
concurrently
this is very important
owning four countries can currently
happen then there's a Deadlock
okay so we have the mutual exclusion
Mutual exclusion presumption
one meter exclusion means that each
resource is assigned to exactly one
process each resource is is assigned to
exactly one process
so
if there is some memory if we coils
memory then memory may be not mutual
exclusion why because mining process can
share memory right they cannot share
they may not Shield exactly the very the
units like the page of the memory but
they can show but they can share the
whole memory so mutual occlusion means
that this is the units the units of the
resource is atomic it can only be
assigned to exactly one process
and another
another definition is hold on the weight
so what is the hold on weight
Holden weight means that process holds
resource can request new resource for
example resource can
request new resource
and then what is non-preemption
means the result cannot be taken away we
have been talking about that a lot of
times okay and a circular chain
condition means that there's uh the
resource allocation graph there's a
circle in the resource allocation graph
so let's again to review that the
conditions for dialogue Mutual exclusion
hold on the weight hold down the weight
there's some process that today hold the
request that they can they are not
allowed to request new resources then if
in that case in that presumption then
there's no dialogue okay
so you need we need to satisfy all these
presumptions like Mutual exclusion means
that well you you the resource can only
be assigned to the one process hold on
with a non-preemption the resource
cannot be taken away
the results cannot be taken away
uncircular chain requests there's a
circle there's a low circle so here the
um
one thing that is very tricky I used to
test that in my previous exam is that I
ask a student to give the resource
allocation graph and I ask students
whether there's uh there's uh I asked
them whether there's a dialogue
and the answer is that the answer
is that it's uncertain it's uncertain
why because you do not know whether
three conditions can be satisfied
so
that's something you may need to
especially notice that okay
so let's do something okay uh
let's do a dialogue motoring a practice
okay
um
so uh where again we use a circle to
represent a resource sorry a process we
use a square to represent this is a
resource resource we use the direction
direction
of the row to represents whether he's
she's holding the resource or she's
requesting the resource now
um
now could you could you try
let me see
it's there
yes let's do this let's do this example
okay the example of the system is it
dialogue let's do that let's try this
okay so yeah I'll give you uh some time
to do that okay
foreign
something
well enable this
is
how many circles they are
one
a little
let's see okay I think this is not
difficult okay
so do you want us to do it together
or you can just
you want me to do it
oh well let's do it so we have the a
holds R right oh not here no
so we have the it's signal process a
holds our process a holds R once s once
that's so it won't S then
s right then we have process B holds
nothing so process B
holds nothing so nothing's there now
since they are and once G so process B
wants t
is there and then we go process C
process C
holds nothing so it's a process so it
holds nothing and the ones s so it wants
s so C holds nothing so there's nothing
here
process they holds you
process d
holds you
how you wants s and t Okay horses
D holds U is one
PC see how
do you wants s it won't
s right
and T
well it's holding you
holding you
you use the resource right and then
process e holds t
where's the person e
hold t
process e holds T so it's holds T So T
super point out to this and once we
we right once we process F holds W
process F holds w
we need to point F here this whole w
once s is one's s
process G holds V this is U process G
holds so we have a process G
holds V
holds V right yeah
oh
he wants U is once U
it's like this looks like this
looks like this so we have um so the
question is that is it the lock
is it the locks who thinks it's
deadlocked
so if you think it's that locked please
raise your hand
if you think anyone think he's not
deadlocked raise your hands
Andrew why you think it's not that
locked
yeah I just talked about that one minute
ago I remember that so this is very
cheeky you do not know the other three
conditions it's satisfied or not right
what are these three conditions the four
conditions
there are four conditions right
one two three four
what are the four conditions
yes
Mutual exclusion very good Mutual
Mutual Acts
conclusion
keyword Mutual exclusion
you if you can then yeah
preemption right prayer preemption
what else
yeah
hold on what is a hold down weight
that is not the definition of Holden
weight yeah
hold on what Holden weight is the
so here media's many systems that they
have a policy they say that you want
these three resources to get started if
you do not have this all together you
are not allowed to get started many risk
many many
systems actually have this policy and
when they implement this policy they
like they use a barrier right
if the gamers are not ready then we do
not start a game something like that so
hold on with means that this systems
allows you to hold some resource and
wait for another resource it give you
the option it gives you the option
since there's an option that you can
hold the resource and Away the other
resources like for a long time then that
creates the scenario that a dialogue may
happen and one last one
of a Deadlock
secular chain of the request right
so it's a circle okay so cool so cool
there's a circle of that so that is the
four conditions so is it a dialogue so
if you find this answer if you find this
question
so if they ask you like they ask you to
draw the resource allocation graph and
ask you if it's their logs then the
answer should be
um it's uncertain right we cannot we do
not know if it is it will be dialogued
one notch right only if this or four
conditions there's other three
conditions are also satisfied and we can
say that okay this system will be
dialogued will be deadlocked
Andrew
no in the diagram is actually
do not tell you anything do you you may
get some you you can get some
presumption about hold with but you you
do not get anything about the
preemption or Mutual exclusion from the
graph you can what you can only be sure
to get get information from a graph is
the secretion of the uh the the
relationship and the hold and weights
you can get this is what you can get but
you cannot know if it is mutual
exclusion or laundry I'm sure
so we have the strategies to deal with
the deadlock
the first strategy is to uh we just
ignore the problem
we think it's a
we think it's used as Fort and we just
say growth program and then uh
restart the system okay another is
detection and Recovery that means that
we let the problems be there and if the
problem is
the problem happens problem happens then
we fix it so it's like a very passive
approach because dialogue is it's like a
race condition race condition when race
condition happens it's not like when we
when we run the system many times then
we may find out the race condition
happens same as dialogue we meet right
for a long time then a deadlock may
happen the system hunts and there's no
response so the detection recovery means
that you just
um
which on the other until the problem
happens and then you fix that
and another another solution is dynamic
avoidance so Dynamic avoidance means the
um
it's a very active approach
so Dynamic avoidance is large I keep
tracking I keep tracking
the process each process schedules when
they are running I keep tracking it and
I do some dynamically resource
allocation I do some Dynamic resource
allocation
um
and the third one is prevention the
third one is prevention that is if we
can
just avoid
we can just if we can like
look at the four conditions if we can
obey any of the one of the conditions
then we can avoid the deadlock because
that one dialogue happens there is other
only they need to satisfy all these four
conditions so the most active ways is
that we do not we we just pick one
condition and then we prevent it from
happening forever then we can avoid we
can definitely avoid the uh
the dialogue okay so um think of that
what will be the first uh the the
solution that you example any real life
example about the equal problem
is actually very very
straightforward right we can just reboot
the system we can remove the device and
then reinsert that if the like device
driver locks up if a kitchen house role
responding we just kill the application
restarted
if application runs for a while and then
hungry checkpoint the application change
the environment restarted from the
previous checkpoints
this is what we have do we have done it
every day every day okay
so engineering will ask how often the
problem is impacted how often the system
crashes or other reasons and how serious
that look is so if if the dialog is
occurs on um like very rarely very
rarely like only happens once in every
five years then
then and then the circumstances is very
minimal right then what we can do is
just let it happen and then we restart
the system
so most Engineers would not be willing
to pay a large penalty in performance or
com uh convenience to animate the
dialogues that is why if you look at you
we should be very familiar with like
that
Rhino does OS is very mature and very uh
well designed but still the applications
May runs right the system not responding
then you just restart it it fixed all
problems most of times
okay then let's look at the second
solution the second solution detection
and Recovery the detection
and recovery so remember this is a very
passive approach this maybe not as
passive as a global problem but it's
still very passive approach it what it
did is that you are going to scan the
resource graph
can the resource Source allocation graph
detect the circles detect the circles
and then we know that we we scan the
resource graph and we found the circles
right like what we did before then
we just let the system runs for a while
for a while and one once the dialogue
happens happens we just kill the process
we can just secure the process and roll
back the action no back from the
beginning
and do it again okay do it again
so it is not always good right white is
not always good
why it is not always good
yes
it will still let it happen yeah
yeah that's it yeah so so here's the
thing so can you it means the question
asked can can we always well
can you always do this like a clear
process rather than the low back the
actions of that lock thread so
many times many times it's
one system hands like
We Care process we can cure it it's no
problem but we can it's not it's it's
not possible that we low back from the
like from the Arrow where the arrow
happens so look at the think of that
think of the tape disk printer example
think of that
after we've been printed for a while
then we found out there's that lock then
you carry you can process then you
restart the system but you cannot
continue print it right you have that
experiment right I I do have that I used
to print printer papers and then the
printer just not working then what what
we need to do is that we pull out the
paper and then print the whole paper
again we cannot print we cannot print
from the where the error happens
it is okay for just the printer paper or
short file but in the real life it is if
it is a very large
heavy long workflow it may not be worthy
to do that so detection recovery is not
good for this situation right
that so let's look take a look at how
the detection how the detection
detection recovery works in the code
okay so this will already finish the
code right we found out that
so the algorithms the algorithm to
detect the dialogues
um
so I want you to try that because you
are a good software engineering okay you
you need now now already give you the
you have the you have this graph right
now write an algorithm to find out that
that the circle in the graph
you learn the algorithms and data
structure class right
yeah the design design algorithms
through design algorithms to to detect
the deadlock
so you first need a data structure to
rapidly to
yourself
okay so let's look at how the textbook
data so you first need to see what kind
of you want to try okay man just
looks like it would be a basic wrap
algorithm where you'd have like some
sort of stack and but the main way that
would work at least efficiently is if
you could ID everything like ID that you
Traverse to be or Traverse to T like
yeah
yeah detects the loop that
that yeah like my first instinct would
be graph algorithm
yeah well kind of data structures do you
want to use
to implement that
yeah Lincoln is very good any other
options
yes back
yeah
what
is a start
okay
we do not talk about python
Let's do let's to see let's do three
okay see
what is that set in C Raptor what it can
be a vector it can be a ring right
okay so here's the thing what is the
python python language is a very
beautiful language but um
uh the problem is that the Python
language is actually wrapping a lot of
the
um
like low level or language programming
languages libraries right
they give the
they make you do not need to worry about
a lot of like libraries interfaces and
the complex this complicated data
structures but what I'm asking is uh
here's the takeaway is that you can use
any data structure to implement the I
mean the data structure what I refer to
is like see like in the C if you use the
Heap right you can use the arraylist you
can use the some Vector to represent the
Matrix right you can you can use
anything
okay so let's look at how the system did
how the textbook did okay I think I have
the algorithms here yeah yeah they use
this
so for
each node in in a graph performance
following five steps with a starting
starting notes okay initialize R to L to
empty list so if you use on release okay
and
as a marker and adding the current mode
to the end of our check to see if the
node now appears in our two times right
if so the graph contains a circle and
algorithms terminates there's a actually
there's a code in the in your textbook I
show how to implement that
so from giving notes if there's any
unmarked outgoing uncles if so goes to
Pro step 5 Notch goes to step six so
step five we pick the unmarked outgoing
uh
to add a random then Mark it then for
the new current snow then go to step
three if this is the initial notes the
graph does not contain circles
algorithms terminates otherwise the
third and the end
and this
um
Advanced version of that of this is that
if if there's multiple resources of each
type if the the multiple resources each
type then how they use that how they
detect that okay
let's keep that
so that is detection that is detection
well the takeaway here is that you
you can Implement any I believe you will
have a homework about a project about
that like user implements are in data
structures or algorithms to detect the
and if there are any circles in a
resource or location graph and then how
to do the recovery recovery there's
possible method of doing the recovery
with the
what we can do is that we just do a
preemption preemption means that we take
the resource away okay and then we Rose
back another another approach is that
we're loading back loading back means
that okay this dialogue happens we're
loading one step or two steps before and
then try it again because not every time
it has a Deadlock
as long as we can keep the
keep the
the sequences
and then the killing process healing
process do it very beginning okay so
this is the opposite approach of
detection and Recovery
so avoidance
dynamically avoidance dynamically
avoidance is a
it's a active algorithm this is an
active strategy for handling the
dialogues
and there's a very famous algorithm
called the bank Bankers algorithms it is
designed by the
at this gesture it's just really heard
of this I he developed a very famous
algorithm right and you still know that
the shortest
yeah yeah yeah
we find there's there's others map right
we have we have many Source node and the
destination nodes in the digestral
implements our algorithms to calculate
like from amine source to any
destination what is the shortest path
right shortest path
yeah in the
or he also designed this anchors
algorithms okay so the key idea
so you need to the key idea about the
algorithms that
um
the the details of the algorithms is in
your textbook I will not go to the very
detailed but I will tell this is a very
uh
it's called dynamically avoidance
ceramic avoidance so it's going it is
going to Dynamic change the resource
allocation so
so you see they use they use stories so
they use the credits to to represent the
resource and then dynamically dividing
the credits a long difference processes
and the the trick here is that
it will not it will not passively detect
whether the
the um there's a deadlock it will it the
key idea is to let it let it runs for a
while
and then check then check if there is a
possibility of the dialogue if it is
then you know going to dynamically
changing the water and the resource
allocation between the process okay
Dot
okay and another approach okay this is
more important because most of
most of the in the real world
most of times what we did to if we do
really want to prevent the dialogue we
choose the force approach dialogue
prevention that is the most active most
active approach
so we just assured that at least one of
the condition is Never Satisfied is
never satisfied
you guys can think creatively about how
we can how we can do that how we can do
that
so mutual exclusion what a mutual
Absolution means that a resource can
only be given one person so how can we
how can we avoid that
yes
will quickly put it on the kill right
and then the printer will print each
item in the queue right so it's not no
longer like mutually exclusive that one
process can print at a time this is
actually not this situation the the
queue adding the papers in the queue of
the printer
okay then how about we do this we do
this first hold and wait
how can we avoid the Holden weight
like a like um process one needs a tape
or disk printer to start the process and
it's hold the tape and the filter and
the requests for the
disk yes
very good actually it is the answer if
you do not you if only in the situation
that I hold some resources and request
them for resources then just to kill
kill this process because
we do not allow you to wait if you find
you do not have enough resources to
start you just we just let the OS to
kill it kill it then we start a new one
a new one may request some other
resources that can it it can like it may
just request one resources to get
started right it's a hold on this is how
we how we how we um how we um
prevents the holding weight how we
prevents the non-preemption
how we prevent the lung preemption
who prevent the non-preemtion prevents
non-preemption
yeah we just let it can be taken away
right
preemption means that
preemption means that you can take away
non-preemption means that the resource
once you gather resources we cannot
we get away right then we just allow for
example if that is the case in the tape
for this situation there's a
Circle in the resource location graph
we just let one of the process to
um like admit
like to let go right Let It Go
make it to a surrounder and give the
resource to others so that is long
preemption and the circular ways
circular ways so how we avoid the
circular weights so let's look at let's
look at the how did okay so um
okay
so the mutual exclusion what with this
that we are going to uh support
everything so support everything for the
whole done ways we are going to request
all resource initially
for non-preemption we just allow you to
take them take the resource away from
circular weight which what we do is that
we order the resource a new market
um this is something tricky this is
something tricky so I I'm going to uh
so what is how have we avoided a
circular weight circular weight how to
avoid the circular weight
how to
avoid
so if you
flower weight
out of white circles so we ordered the
resource numerically numerically
order the resource
so in this situation in this situation
who are the results
the square resource right
what we are going to do is that we gave
them number we gave them number let's
starting from this okay A B C D E F G
yeah how about the a b c d e f g
e f g one two
Hy
oh r s t
u v
r r r s r s
I'm really bad at this
so we're going to give them a number
give them number and we
we ask uh
forces we also a process
you can only get the resource in a
sequence in a sequence
for example if the a if a
is holding
if a is holding r r means the number
three right and requesting four
right then a is allowed to go
a can succeed okay so a
because he's doing something requesting
records pneumatically three and four
right three and a four okay then let's
see let's see f f is holding eight
holding age and requesting for four
so
do we allow F to succeed
sorry
f is f is another resource so f is a
process okay it has this number it's
holding the W and request of four
we do not allow allow you to succeed why
you can only request resource
sequentially sequentially
like a you can request the resource of
three and then holding three and request
for four but F can match holding A's and
requesting four
request a holding is and requesting some
resource that has a marker saying that's
nine will turn something like this okay
then let's look at the D right these are
holding four is holding four right this
holding five and
sorry these holding six and they
requesting for one of five so it's not
it will not happen okay we are going to
delete this because you cannot holding
something larger than what you have you
need to request the resource
sequentially then that is how the how
are we going to how the algorithms can
avoid the circular the uh the the
circular weights problem right now let's
say t right T
oh sorry
e is the holding holding t five and then
one seven right it has succeed okay we
allow this to succeed we allow this
succeed
okay
and same thing let's see
g g is
holding
seven and request for six so G
G is not g converter right
right the same as d d cannot hold six
and then requesting four and five so are
we in the same page yeah okay so that is
how we're going to avoid a circular
weight problem
okay
um
yeah yeah
so if you just avoid trying to uh avoid
the number four condition
yeah that's this case you can hold
something and request something but the
thing is that you need to order the
resource pneumatically you can you can
hold the resource and request a new
resource but the resource you hold needs
to be have a number smaller than the
resource that you want yeah
oh
you can number it in any way you want
what I do is just
like in the order of ABCD effigy yeah
then it doesn't matter it doesn't matter
you can order it in any way
you can order it any way you want and uh
if you if you follow this rule it will
not happen yeah not happen the the the
resource
um
a very interesting question uh very
interesting let me show you okay what is
that
okay so uh here
okay a computer has six tapes six tapes
with unprocessed Computing for the image
process may need up to two drives for
each value of n is the system guaranteed
to be dialog free please explain
for each value of um
which value of an N can be
oh you don't you do not need any
calculator or formula to answer this
okay
or using your paper
into some across the Zone there's some
processes only mean one drive
with some processes only need one
yeah
yeah you need to have the Assumption
some process may need just the one
but each process may lead up to two up
to two Okay up to two
for which value of n
the system is guaranteed to be dialogue
free
it's guaranteed to be deadlock free so
you need to think of the worst case you
need to think of the worst case
are we or are we assuming that you can
make any assumption you can make any
assumption but I'll tell you that each
process may need up to two drives yeah
Andrew
there's only one process
as if there's two there could be
formed into a dead box
so your answer is one
where you you said n equals to one
how about we said that only equals to
one equals to single n equals to one who
have the same answer
raise your hand
we'll have one one okay how about n
equals to two
I'm not just using n equals to how about
n equals to three
and equals to three one two three four
five how about n equals to four
no one thinks n equals to four
how about n equals to five
one
about n equals to six
n equals to seven it is single n equals
to six now
we guaranteed the other three conditions
guaranteed to be deadlock free using the
uh
that's only think about that the the one
condition that's the closing okay in
this case
n equals to six whole thing n equals to
six
so let's make it simple okay
each process needs two drives this are
exchangeable drives
it's like change your drives each person
may need to drive to
which forces leads to drive
so these are same drives the processor
the same the unprocessor the same
non-preemptive we assume this is
non-preemptive we assume this Mutual
exclusion we must we assume this Holden
weight
we assume all three conditions are
satisfied in this case
we just ask you like for which value of
n the system guarantees to be dialog
free
so anyone thinks equals to six
seven
eight nine ten
five who thinks is equal to five one
student
four
no one thinks four
three
two
one
n equals to one so let's first go go
look at this okay it's it's very it's
not that difficult to try right it's not
difficult to try that uh
let's see
we have we have six tapes it has six
tapes these are six tapes
six tapes right and we have
um process we have unprocess so let's
say if n equals to one we have only one
process so P1
P1 and P1 needs how many P1 this P1
needs to two drives to get started right
two drives up to two drives to get
started right
so there's no dialogue right
and if n equals to one there's no
dialogue right
so because for example P1 can get any
two any two no one is fighting the
resource with it and P1 can get the
resource and then successfully run it
right so but how about p e n equals to
two so we have P1 and P2 is there any
dialogue
is there any dialogue
is there any dialogue yes they are aware
why there are
yeah what's your name
March
mache
can only take two requesting take one so
the question answers you that which
value then the system guaranteed to be
dialogue free so this the tapes are the
same
the table are the same the table are the
so let's say I know what you are talking
about you you said P1 holds P one
um getting one and two and then P2 needs
two and three something like that right
but I'm talking that these are the same
type these are the same thing they are
empty they are available
it'll know which ones are being used or
not
the question answer for which value of
the system guaranteed to be deadlock
free guaranteed to be guaranteed to be
download free so it's not across
es or it is
well
so I
let's see let's see if for one process
there's it is guaranteed to be dialogue
free so any can you can equal to one
right what is the post what possible
value of the question answered yeah I
ask is that what are all the possible
value of an right the max value of n so
if P if n equals to 1 that is guaranteed
to be
dialog free but if n equals to two we
have two process so P1 can get any of
the two process P2 can also get any of
the two processes so they can
successfully finish their job there's no
dialogue right even even let's say P1
got one and two and P two one one and
two also or two and three but P2 can
wait it for a while and then try another
approach okay it can get other resources
so they can still finish their job they
can still finish their job
you see that they can still finish their
job why because even P2 let's say P1 got
one two one p two one two and three or
P1 can eventually finish
then P2 can go to another three
let's think of that right so any how
about n equals to three
so we have P1 P2 P3
right
yeah
six copies of the same resource rather
than 60 degree sources yeah we think
yeah they are in the they are the same
tape right the same six tape drivers
drivers they are just to drive
even uh here's the trick even they are
unique even you said they are unique the
they're not still will not happening in
n equals to two let's say P1 definitely
need one and two
right and the P2 will definitely need
one on the two
but P1 will finish right
this is think think of Dar think over
there okay so let's keep doing okay n
equals to three p one p two P3 so and
they they can still as long as as long
as you have the resources they can start
finish okay and n equals to four things
for the same thing right
oh this is something tricky
let's directly go to n equals to 5.
let's go to this let's go to this okay
let's sorry let's close this I know this
is a little tricky
okay
what if n equals to six let's directory
go to a equals to six
we said that this the
each Force has many two drives to get
started if n equals to six if n equals
to six
wait a bit that look
no
n equals to six there's six tables right
each process get one tape
each process got one tape
concurrently
each process got one type con
and they are waiting for another
tape to get started they holding ways
right they hold this they hold this
they hold some they hold the tape they
hold the tape right here the same yeah
let's do this hold they hold the tape
these are four a tapes each of them hold
one tape
each of them hold one tape and they are
they want another tape
then because they need two tapes to get
started
once they once we break the we break the
so-called then if any process is
finished then it can release the
resource right request hold and release
the results request to use and release
the results so if n equals to six
there's a deadlock right it definitely
has a deadlock right because if they
each of them
concurrently requesting sorry holding a
resource and they are requesting any
other tape
then none of them none of them can get
proceed none of them can get proceed
right so n equals to six they are
definitely a deadlock but how about n
equals to five and equals to five
and equal to five
then the worst case is that the first
the first five four sorry English to
five the first
the first four process each of them hold
one resource hold one resource but the
last suppose I still have two resources
to get started
the lasso process still have two
resources to get started
right
so think over
all this all this let's say we divide
the resources to each the tapes to each
of the process and then we have one tape
rest one tape or the rest right we have
one tip whoops yes
yeah that is that you remember the
definition with dialogue right I hold
the resource I request another resource
who is hold by someone else and she
she's also waiting for my resources that
is how the deadlock
formed
a sequential sequential sequential one
with pneumatically ordering the
resources that is our solution
you mixing this concept
that is our solution to avoid dialogue
you remember let's let's come again okay
what's the four conditions of the
dialogue Mutual exclusion run hold on
weights preemption sorry non-preemption
and
and the circular chain right and what's
our four four strategies to handle that
lock ignored problem right and then
detox recovery a passive approach right
and the third approach dynamical
avoidance we talk about the bankers
algorithms the digest chart design that
algorithms and the first approach
prevention problem and under the fourth
strategy prevention problem we we think
that the strategy is to avoid any of
these conditions satisfied so for the to
avoid the
avoid the mutual exclusion what our
Solutions do what to Spring everything
right to avoid the Holden weights what
we do is that we request the resource
initially right to avoid the situation
of preemption we
we can allow them to take the resource
away to avoid the solution to the
situation of circular chain the circle
the circle in we
ordering the resources that is our
solution right remember that we wouldn't
we give the like for example we gave the
watering number to this and we ask them
you can only ordering the number but
this is not uh this is not ask that okay
this is asking you for what number of um
it is guaranteed to be download free
okay so first I tell you the answer okay
n can be this value
one can be one two three four five and
can be this value so n cannot be
anything larger than six larger or equal
than six so it's actually so look at the
six one one six one one there's six
process then each of them hold one tape
and they hold it forever
they need to
right they're holding forever they need
to wait at least one process to receive
what do you want to say Andrew
I'm just like so the first example you
gave was with the two like there's the
three resources for the printer and then
two processes and there is still a
deadlock there even though there was
less
one of the processes can finish and then
the process can go but this is
guaranteed for no deadlock but the
example she gave there was a deadlock
right it doesn't well it says so things
seems that uh
and that's a good question okay so in
this case you think of that these are
different from that example these are
they are the same resources okay the
tape drives are the same okay the tape
drives are the same and the things is
the things is that that each of them so
we asking for watch which value of and
the maximum possible value of the end
that the system guarantees to be
dialogue free
okay
yeah the example you gave satisfied that
condition but still showed a Deadlock
so I'm I'm just like confused is it was
it just like an example for example's
sake or was it just like
let me let me open that okay
the other one
actually you are you you let me use this
okay you
so think of that think of what I did oh
sorry
basically you're asking the same
question like this
[Applause]
we have owning two resources right we
have 22 resources
p is holding p p is holding
two and asking for one P1 P2 is
holding one and asking for two
right that is dialogue right but here in
the case in the case there's a six there
are six of them
there are six of them so and they are
same they are the same so it's
guaranteed if the question answers that
it's guaranteed to be dialogue free so
P2 can get it from someone else you see
that in this case it's only two it's
only two available resources
um
what I want to say is that the drive are
the same the drive are the same yeah
yeah you got what I'm saying okay
okay so this is today's class so if you
have any questions you can feel free to
comfortable and ever help you okay thank
you
hey